<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="duk.00010">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Thomas Arnold's Lectures on Modern History</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
                <author xml:id="unk">Unknown</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="jb">Joelle Byars</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2019</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>duk.00010</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>kprice@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Ed-Folsom@uiowa.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>bbarney2@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability ><p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain exceptions,
            public domain works may be freely copied or used in the creation of derivative works
            without permission, or authorization, of the former copyright owners.</p><p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and is governed
            by a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0).</p><p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners
            of the originals for this publication only.</p></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Thomas Arnold's Lectures on Modern History</title>
                    <idno type="callno">MS 177</idno>
                    <date notBefore="1851-01-01" notAfter="1851-12-31">1854</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="duk">Trent Collection of Whitmaniana, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book &#38; Manuscript Library, Duke University</orgName>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from digital images of the original item.</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl type="base" xml:id="rd_441">
                    <author>Unknown</author>
                    <title level="a">Territorial Aggrandizement</title>
                    <title level="j">The United States Magazine, and Democratic Review</title>
                    <date notBefore="1845-10-01" notAfter="1845-10-31">1845</date>
                    <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                    <biblScope type="vol">17</biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="issue"></biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="pp">247-252</biblScope>
                    <note type="project"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="h1" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h2" scribeRef="#unk" medium="typescript"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h3" scribeRef="#ww" medium="black ink"/>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#jb" when="2019-11-13">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="marginalia">
        <body>
            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="duk.00010.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <note type="authorial" place="top" resp="#h3">Arnold's Lectures on Modern History</note>
                <fw type="header" place="top left">1845]</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">Territorial Aggrandizement.</hi></fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">247</fw>
                <p><note type="authorial" place="left" resp="#h1">X</note> among them, as we trust they may at some future day, and they shall come to understand in some measure their relative duty to each other and to government, and can maintain for themselves individually their right to a free and equal representation before the law, let no one doubt that they will be but too anxious to ally themselves with this republic, from which they will have every thing to gain; and that an armed force will be as superfluous to effect the alliance as it has been to make the same purely acceptable to Texas. It is by its fruits that a good government shall be known; and when its merits shall become manifest, the nations of the earth will not be slow to imitate them. It is by moral influences such as these that this republic is to extend its sway&#8212;by a "wise and masterly inactivity" which will bring other nations at our feet, suppliants for protection, not for forbearance. it is in this wise, we make no doubt, that the whole of this vast continent is destined one day to subscribe to the Constitution of the United States; and if a gun be fired or a sword drawn to hasten the event, it will impair the value, if it do not procrastinate the period of the acquisition.</p>
                <p>To maintain man's capacity for self-government, it be observed, it is not maintaining that that capacity is equal among all nations, at all times; or that all can dispense with government  control in equal degrees. Even in our own community, if a class of people prove incompetent to use without abusing their liberty, we deny them the elective franchise, and perhaps shut them up in a Bedlam or a Penitentiary. They are allowed all the liberty which, if society were entirely composed of such defective natures, they would themselves concede to society. So if a nation be ignorant and corrupt, or corruptible, its constituents will unite in tying each other up for their own protection. The Roman people made Augustus Emperor and prostrated the Senate, because that under their constitution, with an army and a population composed in controlling proportions of barbarians and slaves, they needed the protection of a vigorous government. They wanted some supreme power to whom the republic and its more wealthy citizens might be made accountable. The population of the Empire had become <cb/>so excessive and incongruous that there was no prevailing and conservative <note type="authorial" place="right" resp="#h1">14)</note>public opinion which could direct the enacting or the administration of the laws. All despotisms grow out of similar necessity. They are generally established for the protection of the people, though, of course, perpetuated through ignorance and fear. So Mexico at present needs a much stronger government than the United States. Her people may govern themselves, but they have long since learned that their happiness is concerned in being protected by a much stronger central police, and more restrictive constitution than the American people would submit to, and hence they leave to a few what they dare not trust to more. It is, after all, this mutual distrust among the Mexicans which makes them yield the management of public affairs so fully to individual rulers; and it is this same distrust of the popular intent which the world over gives the despot his perilous power.</p>
                <p>We may seem to be taking a great deal for granted, in discussing thus early the consequences of extending our territorial limits further to the westward than the boundaries of Texas, and to be unmindful of Mrs. Glass's instructions in cooking a fish&#8212;first catch it. We believe, however, that our word, if the wise in itself, is not premature. It is an opinion dangerously prevalent among some of our over-wise politicians that the events of the late presidential election was determined entirely by the views which the successful candidates entertained in favor of the Annexation of Texas to this Union. The enthusiasm which this alliance has since awakened throughout the country they have ascribed to a prevailing appetite among our people for territorial acquisition. Misled by this conviction, every engine is likely to be</p>   
            </div1>
            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="duk_nhg.00026.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">248</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">Arnold's Lectures on Modern History.</hi></fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top right">[October,</fw>
                <p>employed in enlisting public favor by endeavoring to anticipate its tendency in this direction. If our party prevailed by annexing Texas, why cannot another by annexing Mexico, and a third by annexing Canada, and a fourth, when our neighbors are all absorbed, by crossing the seas and annexing Ireland? This misapprehension of the true feeling which disposed this country to look with such favor upon the annexation of Texas is very likely to produce the very state of public opinion which is erroneously supposed already to exist, and which would lead to that very result, the consequences of which we have endeavored <cb/>to consider, much sooner than is dreamed of by those who are most reckless in giving the impulse. The feeling upon our western border, we are pained to think anything but healthy upon this subject; and if, as there is certainly <hi rend="italic">some</hi> reason to fear, we should be obliged, in self-defence, to assume an aggressive attitude towards Mexico, and our armies should once enter her territories, wise must be the statesman that can foresee an end short of absolute subjugation at once, or by fomenting a spirit of national hostility between us, which must ultimately lead to such a result.</p> <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
            </div1>
            <div1>
                <head>ARNOLD'S LECTURES ON MODERN HISTORY.<ref target="#n1" xml:id="ref1">*</ref></head>
                <p>No person can read one of Dr. Arnold's books without being impressed with the fearless honesty of the man. He must have been one of the truest-hearted men that ever existed. The spirit that animates his productions realises the strictest requisitions of literary ethics; and this spirit will keep them alive long after the death of many books containing more positive truth, and displaying greater breadth of understanding. He influences his readers as much by the conviction he gives them of his earnestness and rectitude, as by his intellectual attainments and force of thought. They know that he will mislead them by no sophism or prejudice which has not first misled himself; that if his mind seizes the truth, the truth it will express, at all hazards. This direct honesty of character, this freedom from the <hi rend="italic">badinage</hi> and monkey tricks of the logical faculty, is a very great and very rare merit. A considerable portion of literature is the exponent of a different spirit. There are, comparatively, few authors in whom complete confidence can be reposed; who are wholly sincere, and make their readers their confidants. Bishop Thirlwall happily characterises <cb/>Mitford, as "a writer who considers it the greatest business of history to place royalty in the most favorable light;" and his "History of Greece" as "a work which, though cast in an historical form, is intended not to give historical information, but to state opinions, and then to give such facts as square with them." Even where no strong prejudice or natural <hi rend="italic">penchant</hi> for falsehood leads a writer to pervert facts, he is often disingenuous from the mere desire to display his capacity in arrangement and argumentation. In the present century, it has been too much the custom to consider unsettled questions merely as good occasions for interminable arguments. A writer chooses his side, and then forces his logic and rhetoric into its championship. Interest or accident determines the position he takes, and his intellect is tasked, not to ascertain the truth, but to frame plausible "facts" and arguments to sustain his position. Rectitude of understanding is a rare merit in contemporary literature; there "Reason panders will." Dr. Arnold was singularly free from intellectual immorality. Though from the impetuosity of his temperament, and the ardor of</p>
                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
                <note xml:id="n1" target="#ref1" type="authorial" place="bottom" anchored="true">* Introductory Lectures on Modern History. By Thomas Arnold, D. D. Edited from the second London edition, with a Preface and Notes. By Henry Reed, M. A. New York: D. Appleton &amp; Co. 1 vol. 12mo.</note>
            </div1>
            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="duk.00010.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <note type="authorial" place="top" resp="#h1">&#9759; What is the definition of History?</note>
                <fw type="header" place="top left">1845]</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">Arnold's Lectures on Modern History.</hi></fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">249</fw>
                <p>his religious feelings, he does not always reason in straight lines, he still never consciously substitutes antipathies for arguments, or investigates for any other purpose than to reach the truth.</p>
                <p>His "Lectures on Modern History" are good examples of the moral honesty of his character. Though replete with bold generalisations, and often grouping long periods of history under one idea, they still exhibit all that cautious qualification of general principles by individual exceptions, which a conscientious induction of facts produces. The book contains much just and weighty though and important information. Few students of history are so well read in the subject, as to rise from its perusal without having received additional knowledge. The general remarks on the right mode to study history, and the insight given into the philosophy of modern history, are especially valuable. The style is plain, energetic and business-like. The clearness and directness of the expression come from the orderly arrangement of the author's ideas, and the due subordination in his mind of the greater to the less. The dictation of every lecture shows that it was thought out before it was written out. There is no parade of learning, or illustration or ornament; but rather a disposition evinced to cram the thoughts into as small a space as the proprieties of spoken composition will admit.</p>
                <p>In his Inaugural Lecture, Dr. Arnold introduces the whole subject with some general statements and speculations. <span xml:id="s1" from="#s1" to="#s2" rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1"/>He defines <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">history</hi> as <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">the biography of a society or nation, being to the common life of many what biography is to the life of the individual.</hi><anchor xml:id="s2"/> Theoretically this common life finds its expression in those who are invested with a State's government; "for here we have the varied elements which exist in the body of the nation, reduced as it were to an intelligible unit; the State appears to have a personal existence in the government." Governments being thus the representatives of nations, it would seem that when they are lodged in the hands of individuals, biography and history would melt into each other, as one person combines in himself his life as an individual, and the common life of his nation. Historians have accordingly thought they were recording the life of a commonwealth, <cb/>when they were recording the actions and fortunes of its monarchs; but as governments, practically, have less represented the State than themselves, as the individual life has predominated in them over the common life, history has thus often become merely biography, as it "does but record the passions and actions of an individual, who is abusing the State's name for the purpose of selfish rather than public good."</p>
                <p>The life of a commonwealth is partly external and partly internal; the former expressed in its dealings with other commonwealths, and the latter in its dealings with itself. The external life of a nation being chiefly displayed in its wars, the government is always here, to a certain degree, its representative; for here there is something of a community of interest and feeling, the glory or shame of a war affecting the interests or passions of the whole nation, and the government being compelled to act and suffer, to a considerable degree, for and with the body of the people. History, in recording wars, has remained true to one portion of its proper object; and in this it has been sufficiently bust; for "the wars of the human race have been recorded where the memory of everything else has perished." This is natural, for the external life of nations as of individuals, is more easily known, and more generally interesting, than its internal life. The effects of action, being visible and sensible, are universally intelligible; and the qualities displayed in it we instinctively admire. The descriptions of battles, either in history or poetry, Dr. Arnold contends, are attractive, not because they feed any fondness for scenes of horror and blood, but because they give play to our sympathies with the great qualities displayed in them, such as ability in the adaptation of means to ends, courage, endurance, perseverance, the complete conquest over some of its most powerful temptations; and he is inclined to think that a person who can read these descriptions without interest, differs from the mass of mankind rather for the worse than better; "he rather wants some noble qualities which other men have, than possesses some which other men want."This we deem to be an incorrect statement of the case.</p>
            </div1>
            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="duk.00010.003.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">250</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">Arnold's Lectures on Modern History.</hi></fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top right">[October,</fw>
                <p>Wherever great powers of intellect or virtues are displayed in war, the advocate of peace may consistently admire them, while he is shocked at their direction. He yields to none in admiration of the qualities, but he desires to see them exercised for beneficial, instead of destructive purposes. He would disconnect essentially noble instincts from their accidental union with bad passions. He feels that "under the sky is no uglier spectacle than that of two men, with clenched hands and hell-fire eyes, hacking each other's flesh; converting human bodies and priceless human souls into mere  masses of putrescence, fit only for turnip manure." He is also inclined to echo an old piece of quaint wisdom, "that he who preaches war is the Devil's chaplain;" for he knows that good men have often been led into unjust wars from being blinded to their essential folly and wickedness; by thinking merely of their occasional influence in developing great and noble qualities. And he is indisposed to abate his disgust at annals black with rapine, lust and murder, because Napoleon displayed incomparable skill at Austerlitz, because Sir Philip Sidney displayed the <span xml:id="s3" from="#s3" to="#s4" rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1"/>most touching humanity at Zutphen.</p>
                <p>The inward life of a nation next engages Dr. Arnold's attention. This he considers the most important, and from this he deems its outward life also is characterised. The history of a nation's inward life is the history of its institutions and laws; by institutions, meaning "such offices, orders of men, public bodies, settlements of property, customs or regulations concerning matters of general usage, as to do not owe their existence to any express law or laws, but having originated in various ways at a period of remote antiquity, are already parts of the national system, at the very beginning of our historical view of it, and are recognised by all actual laws, as being themselves <anchor xml:id="s4"/>a kind of primary condition on which all recorded legislation proceeds." The term laws is confined to "the enactments of a known legislative power, at a certain known period." The inward life of a nation is rightly to be subjected to the same tests as are applied to the life of the individual. and is determined by the nature of its ultimate end. "What is a nation's main object, is, therefore, a question must be <cb/>asked, before we can answer whether its inner life, and consequently its outward life also, which depends upon the inner life, is to be called good or evil." If the main object be power, or even national existence, it is not the true object, for neither is an ultimate end, but is to be tested by its being employed for worthy purposes. If a nation has any other object of every individual in it, then the attribute of sovereignty, inseparable from nationality, becomes the dominion of an evil principle. If its highest object be wealth, dominion or security, and as a nation it is not cognizant of the notions of justice and humanity, or deliberately prefers other objects to them, then its sovereign power in human life, by which it can influence the minds and command the actions of moral beings, is immoral and evil. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">The ultimate end of government, therefore, should be moral, not physical;</hi> the promoting and securing the nation's highest happiness, not the protection of their persons and property; in short, "the setting forth of God's glory by doing his appointed work." In this view, Church and State are not so much united as identical, the highest object of the government being made to consist in the diffusion of moral and religious truth, so as to promote corresponding virtuous and religious action amongst the governed; that being their highest happiness. Of course, in the institutions and laws of such a nation, religion would have the most prominent place. As the government would be sovereign, and its primary end would be religious, its power would be exerted first of all in disseminating the religion of the government; and it would not be idle to say that it would not command the obedience of the reason to speculative opinions, as well as the obedience of the will to moral laws. It would at least place those who dissented at matters of faith on a different footing from those who assented. Dr. Arnold's theory of the State, however, has reference chiefly to English controversies on the subject. The opinion on this side of the Atlantic, we trust, is, that the less the government has o do with the Church, the better for both. It is curious, however, that Dr. Arnold's theory convicts that English government of "being the dominion of an evil principle."</p>
            </div1>
            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="duk.00010.004.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <note type="authorial" place="top" resp="#h1">&#9759;</note>
                <fw type="header" place="top left">1845]</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">Arnold's Lectures on Modern History.</hi></fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">251</fw>
                <p>Passing from history in the abstract, Dr. Arnold proceeds to consider modern history, the essential character of which he conceives to be, <hi rend="italic">that it treats of national life still in existence</hi>&#8212;that it commences at a period when all the great elements of the existing state of things had met together. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">The great elements of nationality are race, language, institutions and religion;</hi> "and it will be seen that throughout Europe all these four may be traced up, if not actually in every case to the fall of the western empire, yet to the dark period which followed that fall, while in no case are all four to be found united before it." It is contended that modern history records no addition to the elements of this national personality, all the changes which have occurred having merely combined or disposed these elements differently. The interest of modern history is supreme, treating, as it does, of a national existence not yet extinct, "and exhibiting a fuller development of the human race, a richer combination of its remarkable elements." The moral and mental influence of the ancient world is continued in our modern life, with the addition of a new element, <span xml:id="s5" from="#s5" to="#s6" rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1"/><span xml:id="s7" from="#s7" to="#s6" rend="bracket-right" hand="#h1"/>the English or German race. Dr. Arnold considers that the period of history he calls modern will never become ancient; that the national life now in existence will be immortal; that we are representing the first acts of drama of which the catastrophe is in an unknown future.<anchor xml:id="s6"/></p>
                <p>We have devoted so much space to Inaugural Lecture, that we shall not be able to treat the others at all in detail. The first lecture of the course contains some admirable remarks on the true method to study modern history, so as to comprehend the external and internal life of the nations to which if refers. He advises the student to fix upon some period, to read the contemporary historians of the time, and then to examine the treaties, laws, art, literature, private letters, &amp;c., of the period, so as to get at a full and distinct impression of its events, characters, institutions, manners and ways of thinking. This knowledge of the past must also be combined with a lively and extensive knowledge of the present, or it is mere antiquarianism. In the second lecture, Dr. Arnold divides modern history into two periods, one before, the other after the sixteenth century; and waiving the words "half-civilised" and "civilised," usually employed to signify the distinction, he classes the historians according as their works relate to <span xml:id="s8" from="#s8" to="#s9" rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h1"/>simple or complicated state of things. The active elements of society in the early and middle ages are few&#8212;kings, popes, bishops, lords and knights being almost the only object of attention; while <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">since the sixteenth century, new classes<anchor xml:id="s9"/> or bodies of men have been introduced into the active elements of society,</hi> and produced wide varieties of opinions and interests. The criticism in this lecture of Bede and Philip de Comines, the discussions of the claims of the early ages to our belief, and the consideration of the papacy, in the thirteenth century, are <span xml:id="s10" from="#s10" to="#s11" rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h1"/>very interesting and candid.</p>
                <p>In the third lecture, <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">the importance of geography to a full comprehension of history is insisted</hi> upon at some length. Dr. Arnold then considers the proposition that the undoubted tendency of the last three centuries has been to consolidate what were once separate states "kingdoms into one great nation." This he illustrates in the cases of the Spanish Peninsula, France, Great Britain, Austria and Italy. The<anchor xml:id="s11"/> "successive excesses of the tendency towards consolidation, and the resistance offered to them, afford some of the most convenient divisions for the external history of modern Europe." The first of these which Dr. Arnold considers, is the Austro-Spanish power held by Charles V.&#8212;the mass of whose dominions seemed such as to put him in the way of acquiring universal power. This was opposed by France principally, and after various tides of fortune, was dissolved by abdication of Charles, and the division of his empire. The power of Spain, however, under his son Philip the Second again caused alarm, and was resisted and dissolved. The house of Austria, after the conquest of the Palatinate, in 1622, next excited apprehension, and was opposed by France, under Richelieu, and my Sweden, Holland, and the Protestant States of Germany. The resisting power again triumphed. France, under Louis the Fourteenth and Napoleon, again arrived at universal dominion , and in both instances was eventually defeated.</p>
                <p>These different contests involved to some degree political and religious</p>
            </div1>
            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="duk_nhg.00030.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">252</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">Arnold's Lectures on Modern History.</hi></fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top right">[October,</fw>
                <p>principles; but what we have most to consider in them are economical and military questions, the purse and the sword deciding their issue. Dr. Arnold devotes some pages to the expense of war, and the burdens it lays upon a nation, discussing incidentally the question of the right of one generation to tax another, by caring on its contests through the medium of loans. He instances the wars of the last century, and the first fifteen years of the present, in which Great Britain contracted a debt of &#163;70,000,000, to pay the interest of which more than half of her present revenue is appropriated. Though he does not absolutely object to this mode of making posterity pay part of the expenses of war, he thinks that it has been carried beyond all bounds of prudence and justice heretofore.</p>
                <p>The fourth lecture treats of the laws of war and military options. The humanity of the author is well exemplified in this portion of the book. The fifth and sixth lectures relate to internal history, principally of that of England, in which a fine analysis is given of its two great parties, the popular and the anti-popular, from the age of Elizabeth down the Revolution of 1688. The strange mixture of political, personal and religious considerations which this period of English history exhibits, is rendered clearer to the apprehension of the common student than in any other work we have seen. The seventh lecture treats of England since the Revolution, and is full of valuable thought and information. The last lecture is devoted to a discussion of the credibility of history, and to a few other questions which the subject naturally suggests.</p>
                <p>The American edition of this work, is handsomely printed and carefully edited. Professor Reed's notes, which consist principally of further elucidations of Dr. Arnold's views by extracts from his other writings will be found quite interesting. We think that he might have made the notes more valuable by throwing in, here and there, a criticism or argument of his own, when his author's principles clash with American ideas, as in the speculations on Church and State; but on this point we do not insist. Dr. Arnold's notions of a state are too theoretical to find a practical exemplification anywhere; and in<cb/> the United States an opposite theory is a common truism. It is a fact that when government have assumed their ultimate end to be moral, morality as well as life and property have equally suffered. It is a fact, that the connection of religion with political power, has had no good influence in making states or subjects moral or religious. It is a fact that the subordination of physical to religious ends, in the action of states, has produced moral evil by the physical suffering it has created. However much we respect Dr. Arnold's character, and his opinions as an exponent of his character, we think that in this case zeal vitiated his judgement, and that he overlooked the great practical truth, which has been expressed with so much eloquence by a prominent English liberal statesman, that "the whole history of the Christian religion shows, that she is in far greater danger of being corrupted by the alliance of power, than of being crushed by its oppression. Those who thrust temporal sovereignty upon her, treat her as their prototypes treated her author. They bow the knee, and spit upon her; they cry hail! and smite her on the cheek; they put a sceptre into her hand, but it is a fragile reed; they crown her, but it is with thorns; they cover with purple the wounds which their own hands have inflicted on her; and inscribe magnificent titles over the cross on which they have fixed her to perish in ignominy and pain."</p><milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
                <p>We publish the foregoing article, first, because of our high respect for the accomplished critic through whose kindness it has been presented to us&#8212;and, secondly, for the useful synopsis it presents of the work to which it relates. There are some peculiarities in this volume of lectures, however, which our contributor has substantially over-looked, of too grave an import to receive the same treatment at our hands. Our ardent admiration for the gifted Professor whose death nearly the whole civilized world united in deploring, would probably have prevented our uttering one discordant note to mar the harmony of such a universal sentiment, if we had been personally compelled to entertain original jurisdiction of the subject of the foregoing article. After what has been stated, however, in the preceding pages, and to all of which we subtan-</p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>