<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="duk.00730">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Philosophy, Psychology, and Metaphysics</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
                <author xml:id="unk">Anonymous</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="jb">Joelle Byars</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2019</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>duk.00730</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>kprice@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Ed-Folsom@uiowa.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>bbarney2@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability ><p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain exceptions,
            public domain works may be freely copied or used in the creation of derivative works
            without permission, or authorization, of the former copyright owners.</p><p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and is governed
            by a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0).</p><p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners
            of the originals for this publication only.</p></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Philosophy, Psychology, and Metaphysics</title>
                    <idno type="callno">II-7A 182</idno>
                    <date notBefore="1851-01-01" notAfter="1851-12-31">1871</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="duk">Trent Collection of Whitmaniana, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book &#38; Manuscript Library, Duke University</orgName>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from digital images of the original item.</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rd_462" resp="#jb">
                    <author>Anonymous</author>
                    <title level="a">Philosophy, Psychology, and Metaphysics</title>
                    <title level="j">The Eclectic Magazine of Foreign Literature, Science, and Art</title>
                    <date notBefore="1871-04-01" notAfter="1871-04-30">1871-04</date>
                    <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                    <biblScope type="vol">76</biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="issue"></biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="pp">389-386</biblScope>
                    <note type="project"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="h1" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h2" scribeRef="#unk" medium="typescript"/>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#jb" when="2019-12-18">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="marginalia">
        <body>
            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="duk.00730.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="left">1871.]</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top">PHILOSOPHY, PSYCHOLOGY, AND METAPHYSICS.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="right">389</fw>
                    <p>us; partly we have to discern the unity of character and principle prevailing among the diversity of objects. The philosopher must not, while pursuing the latter aim, neglect the former; or his philosophy will wither up for want of sustenance. He, above all other inquirers, must desire to be Catholic, universal, uniform; but there are schisms in our knowledge which he must tolerate, to which he must at present submit himself.</p>
                <p>Those philosophers who endeavor to bring to its completion this great tendency of philosophy, to exhibit the spiritual unity of the worlds as dominating over and compromising all other laws, are called metaphysicians. Of their methods more will be said presently. Here it will be sufficient to remark, that their end, though that all men must hope for and believe in, is yet not one immediately practical and visible. Time will, as I believe, work on their side; the material will be gradually penetrated and transformed by the spiritual. But we must beware of thinking that metaphysics is the only philosophy, to that the physical sciences will remain in their isolated schismatic state until that final culminating moment when they shall be shown to be subordinate to the spiritual unity.</p>
                <p>On the contrary, philosophy is even now, and has ever been, at work among the sciences. A vast and gradual influence tends to bring these separate portions of our knowledge into connection with each other&#8212;an influence sometimes vaguer, sometimes clearer, but always rising out of vagueness into clearness, sometimes tending to attach only some two or three sciences together, sometimes applicable to the whole range of our knowledge. Thus the nebular hypothesis, if true, would connect astronomy and geology, and if carried far enough, would probably wholly unite these sciences; but it need not touch upon any science but these two, though of course, it might do so. Thus the nebular hypothesis is a philosophical effort, though one of a limited character. Its tendency, as far as it goes, is to make our knowledge uniform; but it does not go very far in this direction. On the other hand, the theory of evolution, of the development of the heterogeneous out of the homogenous, as given by Mr. Herbert Spence, is a very wide philosophical effort; there is hardly any portion of our<cb/> knowledge, material or spiritual, to which it is not applicable; it has a strong tendency to promote the unity of our knowledge. Not that even this, or any effort within our present capacity, attains to anything like the dimensions of a final<note type="authorial" place="right" resp="#h1">? theology</note> philosophy. It is enough that the <span xml:id="s1" from="#s1" to="#s2" rend="wavyLine-right" hand="#h1"/>tendency exists; that all our <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">knowledge</hi> is undergoing a perpetual remodelling, a fundamental change which is not destruction<anchor xml:id="s2"/> but renovation. There is not an atom of it which is not continually being set in some point of view, wherein it is harmonized with other portions that have hitherto been supposed alien to it. This change is the work of philosophy; and it is evident that all philosophy is not spiritual philosophy. The tendency of philosophy is spiritual; those who seek to bring all our knowledge into harmony will be compelled to have recourse to spiritual <span xml:id="s3" from="#s3" to="#s4" rend="wavyLine-right" hand="#h1"/>principles; but as there are purely material parts of our knowledge, so there are purely material ways of harmonizing my those parts.<anchor xml:id="s4"/></p>
                <p>Thus, while philosophy has a clear and universal&#8212;namely, to bring all knowledge, all reality into harmony&#8212;and while philosophy, as a whole (unless the view here maintained be wrong), has a metaphysical and spiritual tendency, and the principles which will gradually shine clearer and clearer in proportion to our increased command of truth are spiritual principles, yet this latter belief is no part of the meaning of the word Philosophy, as it is a part of the meaning of the word Metaphysics; and the philosopher will not bind himself down to any spiritual principle, but will seize upon any facts, any forms of representation, which appear to form him able to harmonize and link together different portions of our knowledge. Thus a philosopher may know his theories to be partial, and not universal, as would be the case with those who thought of the nebular hypothesis; but he could not call himself a philosopher without a belief that his theories directly aided the establishment of a universal harmony.</p>
                <p>Here, however, it is that philosophy touches upon science. For the essential <span xml:id="s5" from="#s5" to="#s6" rend="wavyLine-right" hand="#h1"/>characteristic of science is, that it submits to be partial for the sake of clearness; so<anchor xml:id="s6"/> that when philosophy submits to be partial, even with a view to furthering the universal harmony of knowledge, it touches the border of science. And tin fact there is no</p>
            </div1>
            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="duk.00730.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="left">390</fw> 
                <fw type="header" place="top">PHILOSOPHY, PSYCHOLOGY, AND METAPHYSICS.</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="right">[April,</fw>
                <p>clearly marked line between philosophy and science; though of some views we may say decidedly, "these are scientific," and of others, "these are philosophical." <span xml:id="s7" from="#s7" to="#s8" rend="wavyLine-left" hand="#h1"/>It is the first aim of the scientific inquirer, not to enlarge his range, but to be accurate and complete within his range; it is the first aim of the philosopher to embrace a large compass, so that he is compelled to submit to a want of definiteness for the sake of universality. The solid masses of<anchor xml:id="s8"/> <span xml:id="s9" from="#s9" to="#s10" rend="wavyLine-right" hand="#h1"/>knowledge, which we call the sciences, stand in a manner isolate, like the planets and stars in the heaven; and just in the material universe there floats an ether<anchor xml:id="s10"/> dividing and yet uniting the solid orbs, so those parts of our knowledge which we are entitled to consider fixed and certain are separated and at the same time united by large tracts of obscurity, enlightened by only a few elementary principles. Philosophy is bound not to shrink from dealing with these tracts of comparative obscurity; the scientific inquirer does, with reason, pass them over: but it is not unimportant to our welfare that they should be kept before our notice. Thus, all theories on the nature of things which are too large to be corroborated and verified by such observation of facts as we can command, and yet are such as within this limitation approve themselves to our reason, are essentially philosophical. Scientific men are afraid of vagueness; but it is right not to bee too much afraid of vagueness, though no one should be content with resting in it. Those who refuse at the outset to take into their consideration regions that their apprehension are dark or dimly lighted who confine themselves to clear ideas and irrefutable logic, will never effect anything original. Few men indeed are aware how great their ignorance is; or, if they are compelled to own it in any case, their next resource is to represent the subject as inaccessible to human inquiry altogether, so that at any rate they may not be inferior to others. But the truth is, there are immense tracts, of which we are ignorant now, whit are not necessarily inaccessible to human inquiry, and in which patient observation may disclose to us here one gleam, there another; and it is a most essential part of philosophy not to let us ignore these tracts. Even in such sciences as chemistry and astronomy, how much there is must be true, which will be discovered,<cb/> of which we have not the shadow of an idea now; and how much more when we come to the thoughts and faculties of men or of brutes. The obscure, inchoative character of philosophy is intimately connected with the originality and universality of it.</p>
                <p>And if it be objected that what is here said of the obscurity of the realms of philosophy is not consistent with what was previously said of philosophy being the endeavor to harmonize all knowledge, this is by no means the case. Philosophy is not responsible for the fact of our ignorance, though it is that which convinces us of our ignorance: in obeying the purely free and unconfined impulse to know the world in which we live, we do actually find that the fields of our knowledge are but as islands in an ocean of the unknown. It is possible, in endeavoring to harmonize all reality, to ignore realities which are unknown or half-known, as if they were non-existent? It is impossible; and therefore philosophy, in the endeavor to be universal, must of necessity linger among the obscure.</p>
                <p>Yet, philosophy is not alien from science; and if we like, we may consider science simply as philosophy contracting itself for the moment and bringing itself to a focus. For philosophy is nothing more than thought, the thought of the successive generations of men; and though thought is infinite in its capacity, it can narrow itself to grasp the finite. And when we come to the great generalizations of science, the highest successful achievements of the human intellect, we feel it not unnatural to call the authors of them philosophers. We call Newton a philosopher. And again, if we look at these great generalizations, it is observable that they were, for the most part, distinctly reached by the way of philosophy; that is, they occurred not to men whose minds were bent on the clear and comprehensible, but to men whose minds roamed over the spaces of the unknown. The theory that the earth goes round the sun was though of centuries before Copernicus; and even Copernicus did not prove it; so gradually did it emerge out of the category of the fantastic into the category of the demonstrated. Kepler's laws were not certainly thought of before Kepler; but if Kepler had not possessed</p>
            </div1>
            <div1>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="duk.00730.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <fw type="header" place="left">1871.]</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top">PHILOSOPHY, PSYCHOLOGY, AND METAPHYSICS.</fw>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="right">391</fw>
                <p>an immense imaginative power, such as on other occasions displayed itself in hypothesis seemingly the most eccentric, all the clear thinking in the world would never have discovered what he discovered. Gravitation was though of before Newton; the atomic theory, in quite ancient times; the development of species is even yet rather a hypothesis believed from its adaptation to our reason, than a theorem proved on the evidence of facts.</p>
                <p>One of the best instances of the aid which even a partly erroneous philosophical theory may lend to the formation of clear science, is afforded by the Ptolemaic system of astronomy. And this is especially noticeable; for the Ptolemaic system grounded itself on observation more than most scientific system do; so that if we can see the remodelling impulse, the element native to thought, working in this system, it will be plain how greatly it must prevail through all science, Now the theory of epicycles and eccentrics, on which the whole Ptolemaic system was based, and without which it would have been impossible to register and preserve those observations which were the indispensable preliminaries of the Copernican system, was essentially philosophical. It sprang up in the Platonic school; it was adopted by Aristotle. It was a theory that, rough as it was, still demanded the effort of thought, and not merely the keen eyesight. It had another characteristic common in philosophy; in it we see truth gradually emerging from error, the truth and the error at first commingled in one hypothesis, and then the slow deposition of the error, and the liberation of the truth that had previously been contained in solution. The theory of epicycles, as is well known, was this: that every heavenly body moved in an orbit traced by some point of a wheel revolving round another wheel. Now originally, these wheels were supposed to be actual material, solid, though invisible bodies, and the planets and stars to be stuck onto them, as a stone may stick on to the wheel of <span xml:id="s11" from="#s11" to="#s12" rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1"/>a carriage. In this form the theory was untrue; yet it contained the germ of a truth. Nor perhaps could the truth at first have been set forth, or at least have taken hold of the minds of men, without the admixture of error. The living truth lay in the dead error, as a chicken<cb/><anchor xml:id="s12"/><span xml:id="s13" from="#s13" to="#s14" rend="bracket-right" hand="#h1"/> it is hatched lies in the egg-shell. The hard lifeless shell can withstand the external forces which would overpower the living thing were it too soon exposed to them. And, precisely in the same way, the lifeless, unproductive mass of error may,but the fact of its easy intelligibility, take hold of men's minds far more readily than the exact truth, which is always difficult to understand, could have done; and in this way the truth is enabled to survive till a period comes when it is strong enough to break from the surrounding crust, and develop without fear. This is a process which we constantly see; and where the error is simply dead error, and has not a pernicious activity,<anchor xml:id="s14"/> it is a very beneficial process. And accordingly, when Hipparchus came, he discarded that portion of the theory of epicycles which had been necessary to render the theory originally comprehensible, namely, the materiality of the wheels, and retained the rest. And in this form the theory of epicycles, in its broad features, was actually true; not the highest astronomical truth, not so comprehensive as the hypothesis of Kepler, but still true and for the time most important. And if Hipparchus and Ptolemy would probably have agreed in this further characteristic of their theory&#8212;that it was a tentative theory, which might in time be superseded y something better; and this tentativeness, implying as it does a radical development, and not merely change in the subordinate branches of a hypothesis is essentially philosophical. We know at all events that Ptolemy was as well aware of the cumbrousness of his epicycles as was Milton or King Alfonso.</p>
                <p>no considerable development can take place, either in any separate science, or in the great whole of knowledge, which comprises so much that it is not yet formed into solidarity of a science, without passing through this stage, which is the philosophical stage&#8212;the stage of tentativeness, incompleteness, formation. But sometimes this stage may be contained within very narrow limits. And occasionally, in the development of a particular science, the philosophical stage will be confined to the breast of one individual, so that to the multitude it will appear as if there was no philosophical stage at all&#8212;as if the science had simply widened from one</p>
            </div1>
            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="duk.00730.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="left">392</fw> 
                <fw type="header" place="top">PHILOSOPHY, PSYCHOLOGY, AND METAPHYSICS.</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="right">[April,</fw>
                <p>clear hypothesis to another equally clear and wider. Thus botany, as a particular science, has had perhaps the minimum of philosophical speculation; the Linn&#230;an classification has been superseded by the natural classification, not certainly without tentativeness, but with as little tentativeness as possible in such a change. On the other hand, geology has always been, and still is, open to a vast amount of tentative speculation. And when we come to the great whole of knowledge&#8212;to the connections of the sciences and the interspaces between them, to all the array of facts and principles that cannot be set down as belonging to any particular science&#8212;there must, we may be sure, always be room for the philosophical impulse to work in. Nor will any new science arise except by this philosophical impulse determining itself in a particular direction; so that philosophy may justly be considered the parent of science.</p>
                <p>Let us then recapitulate the <span xml:id="s15" from="#s15" to="#s16" rend="wavyLine-left" hand="#h1"/>characteristics of philosophy. The philosophy of an individual is the view which the world as a whole presents to the mind of that individual; so that, as has often been said, every<anchor xml:id="s16"/> man must have a philosophy. But it is seldom thought worth while to speak of the view which any an takes of the world as a philosophy, unless where the man has tried to grasp and hold consistently the total sum of knowledge possessed by his generation. Philosophy, then, is the effort of each successive generation to contemplate the world as a whole; to look at the universe with its own eyes and not under a merely traditional aspect; to unfold from the realms of obscurity new principles which may unite and harmonize those portions of reality which at present we know only as disconnected; to suggest modes of harmonizing where certainty is unattainable; to arrange all reality in order, from the seed to the tree, from the genesis to the perfect development. Universality and originality are the essential aims of philosophy. And for the sake of these it must resign itself to being inchoative and obscure in many parts, especially in its most fundamental principles: whereas science resigns universality for the sake of clearness. Yet philosophy is not separated by any broad line from science; for what is universal to one man and one age may be partial to another man or another age. There<cb/> is only one assertion in the above pages respecting philosophy that needs further proof&#8212;the assertion, namely, that it has a spiritual tendency, that the universal view of the world tends more and more to become a spiritual view. But the proof of this will come fore fitly when we consider metaphysics.</p>
                <p>II. Psychology is the science of mind considered as a function of the material world. In saying this, it is of course not denied that psychology may gradually disclose the spiritual unity of which mention has been made. But it bases itself on the material unity; this is its primary foundation.</p>
                <p>No one can look out into the world, and not be conscious that he knows a great deal more than the simple phenomena of sense. He knows that there are living beings beside himself, who like himself have sight and hearing and feeling, and moreover, like himself, have desire and pleasure and pain. Men, beasts, birds, insects&#8212;not to go any further into these, it is at any rate unquestionable that these do actually see and hear, desire and feel. The question then immediately arises, What is it that these men and living creatures round us see, desire, and know? Can we appropriate to ourselves truly their mental state, put ourselves into their position, see as they see, desire as they desire, think as they think? We know that within certain limits we can; and we know that we can progress in this knowledge of our fellow-creatures. And just as the object of physical science is to enable us to represent to ourselves those portions of nature which are capable of striking on our sense, but which do not actually strike on our senses, because they are absent from our immediate neighborhood and environment, so the object of psychological science is to enable us to represent to ourselves those feelings and desires, that knowledge and thought, which belong to other living beings than ourselves.</p>
                <p>It is quite impossible to deny the reality and solidity of psychological science. As certain as we are that the cities, the houses, the rivers, the sun, and the sky do really exist, and are real objects, into the nature and properties of which we can inquire, so certain are we that every one of</p>
            </div1>
            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="duk.00730.005.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="left">1871.]</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top">PHILOSOPHY, PSYCHOLOGY, AND METAPHYSICS.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="right">395</fw>
                <p>mind? We cannot; in such a case it is hardly more difficult for the lower intellect to advance to the higher, than for the higher to retrace its steps, and, through imaginative sympathy, put itself in the position of the lower. Yet it is a real problem for us to do so; and the solution of it might have most important results. Again, the mental and intellectual condition of beasts is a subject of which it would be difficult to over estimate the interest. Those most conversant with beasts, most able to understand their feelings and capacities, have hitherto had too little of the scientific spirit. But that it is a most fruitful subject does not admit of question. In all these subjects, physical science can contribute much, in some cases essential, aid; but the subjects themselves are psychological.</p>
                <p>Further, just as there is a science which deals with the highest and most universal abstractions of the material universe, namely, mathematics; so there is a science which deals with the highest and most universal abstractions of mind, <span xml:id="s17" from="#s17" to="#s18" rend="wavyLine-left" hand="#h1"/>namely, logic. The material universe can be surveyed in many aspects; but in all its aspects it has one common property&#8212;it can be measured; and mathematics is the science of measurement. So, too, mind can be regarded in many aspects<anchor xml:id="s18"/> but one common property it always has&#8212;it reasons, consciously, or unconsciously;<span xml:id="s19" from="#s19" to="#s20" rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1"/> and logic is the science of reasoning.<anchor xml:id="s20"/> But yet, just as mathematics is not the deepest philosophy of the material universe&#8212;just as far more concrete theory, whether it be the atomic theory or any other, is required to lie at the rot of the great physical sciences, to be to them as a common origin, a common principle, and to bind them together&#8212;so loci is not<span xml:id="s21" from="#s21" to="#s22" rend="wavyLine-left" hand="#h1"/> the deepest philosophy of mind. Logic is concerned with the form of thought, as the Germans express it, not with its substance; it is a science of abstractions which may indeed be illustrated, but concrete instances, but does not primarily take any concrete phenomenon, or series of phenomena, as its subject. A more fundamental philosophy of mind is required. Now if the materialist view be true, that matter is the absolutely fundamental element, of which mind is merely  a function<anchor xml:id="s22"/>, then of course, the fundamental philosophy of mind is to be looked for in those atomic theories which are the deepest in<cb/><span xml:id="s23" from="#s23" to="#s24" rend="bracket-right" hand="#h1"/> all physical research, and all psychology must centre in these, and radiate from these. There are, however, reasons compelling man to believe spirit to be the deepest element in the universe; and hence a philosophy has to be sought which out indeed to amalgamate with the deepest philosophy of the material sciences, but out to underlie it, and be plainly the original of which that is the derivative. This deepest philosophy of the psychological sciences is metaphysics; and to the consideration of metaphysics we must now proceed.<anchor xml:id="s24"/></p>
                <p><span xml:id="s25" from="#s25" to="#s26" rend="bracket-right" hand="#h1"/>III. Metaphysics is the endeavor to demonstrate and bring clearly to light the spiritual unity of the world, not as contradictory of the material unity, but as underlying it, and being the source from which it proceeds.<anchor xml:id="s26"/></p>
                <p>The connections between metaphysics on the one side and philosophy and psychology respectively on the other side have already been indicated; but it may be worth while to repeat them. Philosophy is the endeavor to take a view of the world as a whole, with all its parts ranged in order of their genesis and development; and if, as I believe, in such an arrangement a spiritual force, a spiritual principle, is found to be the most primitive element, then philosophy will be found to centre round metaphysics. Psychology is the endeavor to know all we can about spiritual beings and spiritual faculties as exhibited in the world, without necessarily endeavoring to reduce our knowledge on these subjects to an organic unity. But if we do endeavor to bring out such an organic unity, and if such a unity is necessarily a spiritual unity, then the search after such an organic unity is metaphysics. Thus, while it is quite impossible to deny philosophy and psychology their place as rational and useful attempts, there is one hypothesis, and only one,b y holding we should deny the possibility of metaphysics&#8212;the hypothesis, namely, that matter is capable of being rationally taken as the origin of all things, and that spirit, in all its manifestations, is capable of being exhibited as a function of matter. I have given reasons for how believing this to be impossible; and it must now be shown how natural is the belief that spirit is the absolute first origin of things, and how perfectly it is re-</p>
            </div1>
            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="duk.00730.006.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="left">396</fw> 
                <fw type="header" place="top">PHILOSOPHY, PSYCHOLOGY, AND METAPHYSICS.</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="right">[April,</fw>
                <p>concilable with what we know of the laws of the physical universe. I must premise, however, that I do not promise the absolute demonstration, or the explanation of all the phenomena. A belief may be the only rational belief, and yet such as we cannot verify in detail.</p>
                <p>That we all "live, and move, and have our being" in God; that we are "children of God," and therefore brethren of each other&#8212;such are the most familiar expressions by which it has been endeavored to express the intrinsic unity of spiritual beings; and schemes of conduct have been laid down as the fit and natural result of the belief thus expressed. These schemes of conduct belong to religion, and into the subject of religion I cannot here enter; but the meaning of the belief itself it will be proper, as far as possible, to elucidate.</p>
                <p>If we regard, on the one hand, the phenomena of the external world, an don the other hand all those different personalities endued with passions, senses, faculties, that together make up what we understand by the spiritual world, these two classes of intelligible things move to a certain extent parallel to each other in such a way that the material phenomenon is the symbol, or so to speak, the shorthand register of the spiritual state. This parallelism, indeed, is not the manifest beyond certain limits. There are many thoughts, many emotions, that pass through our minds, which do not give, even for a moment, any token of their existence to the bystander who watches our bodily frame. Conversely, int eh external world, inorganic matter appears purely soulless. And even among organic living beings it is only animals that their outward frame give us any index of a spiritual state; and in most cases the index is a vague and imperfect one. Still, however imperfect, the parallelism is real. If we look at the broad types of character and faculty, each is attached to some definite outward characteristic, from which it is never dissociated. A powerful intellect is invariably united with a complex structure of the brain. If we analyzed the brain of a Newton, and then the brain of a Hottentot, we should be quite certain that the latter would have far fewer convolutions than the former. If we found an animal without eyes, we should assume at once that it could not see. The habitual feelings of men leave an unmistakeable stamp on their face, their mien, and bearing; even transient momentary feelings<cb/> have an equally distinct mark, unless where care is taken to suppress this mark, as is generally the case with civilized men. And it is to be observed that the more permanent is the feeling or faculty the more permanent is the outward index which denotes it. Thus the paleness of fear passes away with the fear, the blush of shame with the shame; but intellect, being of a more permanent nature, has a more permanent symbol in the brain, and so has the faculty of sight in the eyes, and the faculty of hearing in the ears.</p>
                <p>All of these are obvious facts. That to which I shall now proceed is the extension of the principle involved in these facts to regions where it is only possible to conjecture, and not to see clearly its operation. But the conjectures that will be brought froward are those, as I think, naturally suggested by a view of the universe as it is.</p>
                <p>I say then that this function of material bodies to be the expression of spiritual states and spiritual agencies, is no mere casual function, one out of many; that, on the contrary it is the one primitive function of the matter, its fundamental essence, to be the intermediate agency in the spiritual world, the means by which the parts of the living whole communicate with and affect each other; that body is strictly definable as the manifestation of spirit to spirit. The proposition conveyed in this sentence calls for considerable explanation; but before proceeding to this, attention may be directed to two distinct speculations&#8212;one philosophical, the other scientific&#8212; which tend to confirm the mediating function here assigned to matter and to the material world.</p>
                <p>It is well known in what difficulties Locke found himself involved in attempting to explain the meaning of the word Substance. The word itself is a scholastic word; but the sense of it is broadly popular; nor is there any difference to speak of between scholastic and the popular use of it. Philosophers or not, we all understand that there is a difference between the properties of a thing and the thing itself, or at any rate that at the first blush there appears to be such a difference. But philosophers, inasmuch as they seek to be accurate thinkers, cannot be con-</p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>