<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="duk.00025">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Literature of the Middle Ages</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
                <author xml:id="unk">Anonymous</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="jb">Joelle Byars</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2019</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>duk.00025</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>kprice@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Ed-Folsom@uiowa.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>bbarney2@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability ><p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain exceptions,
            public domain works may be freely copied or used in the creation of derivative works
            without permission, or authorization, of the former copyright owners.</p><p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and is governed
            by a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0).</p><p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners
            of the originals for this publication only.</p></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Literature of the Middle Ages</title>
                    <idno type="callno">MS 181</idno>
                    <date notBefore="1849-01-01" notAfter="1849-12-31">1849</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="duk">Trent Collection of Whitmaniana, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book &#38; Manuscript Library, Duke University</orgName>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from digital images of the original item.</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl type="base" xml:id="rd_453">
                    <author>Anonymous</author>
                    <title level="a">Literature of the Middle Ages</title>
                    <title level="j">The Westminster Review</title>
                    <date notBefore="1849-01-01" notAfter="1849-12-31">1849</date>
                    <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                    <biblScope type="vol">51</biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="issue"></biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="pp">181-191</biblScope>
                    <note type="project"/>
                </bibl>
                <bibl type="base" xml:id="rd_487">
                    <author>Anonymous</author>
                    <title level="a">Unknown</title>
                    <title level="j">New York Evening Express</title>
                    <date notBefore="1856-01-03" notAfter="1856-01-03">1856-01-03</date>
                    <pubPlace>Unknown</pubPlace>
                    <biblScope type="vol"></biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="issue"></biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="pp">4</biblScope>
                    <note type="project"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="h1" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h2" scribeRef="#unk" medium="typescript"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h3" scribeRef="#ww" medium="ink"/>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#jb" when="2019-11-19">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="marginalia">
        <body>
            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="duk.00025.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <note type="authorial" place="top" resp="#h1">Villemain's "Literature of the Middle ages" Westminster Review</note>
                <fw type="header" place="top left">1849.</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">Literature of the Middle Ages.</hi></fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">181</fw>
                    <p>posed upon him the necessity of learning their Roman name, or of inventing a barbarian appellation for them; while the attributes of war and dominion, from which the subject was practically excluded, were perpetuated in the language of the new masters of the soil.</p>
                <p>But, towards the end of the seventh century, during the Merovingian reigns, the rustic Latin of the south of France had become variously corrupted into a general form of that <hi rend="italic">romance</hi> which at one time extended round there Gulf of Lyons from Spain to Tuscany, while the north of France partook more of the Frankish, or Langue d'Oil; though many centuries were to elapse before it became fashioned to the French of Racine and Voltaire.</p>
                <p>M. Villemain pays a just tribute of respect to Raynouard, whose labours have so successfully indicated the birth (sown, indeed, in the corruption and decay of a nobler and more scientific one) of the modern southern tongues, much promoted by the mitigated feudality of the courts of Arles and Toulouse. Those parts had escaped the ravages of the wild men of the north for nearly two centuries. The courtesies of chivalry also began to soften some of the relations of life, but only some; forming a striking contrast with the cruelties sometimes exercised by the very same persons who acknowledged its authority, without being swayed by its principles. Indeed, the harshness was not peculiar to these periods, having survived to times not so very remote from our own. But, doubtless, the dramatic effect, the picturesque character of the middle ages, is enhanced from these inconsistencies and contrasts&#8212;from the opposition of the brilliant lights of knightly honour and devoir with the dark shadows of ambition, revenge, and crime. In this respect our modern times are far inferior; we afford ourselves no emotions, we permit ourselves no sacrifices (except those of ease and health, in pursuit of wealth); we ensure our lives, fortunes, persons, ships&#8212;everything, in short, except our own happiness; we stave off calamity we fear; we parry every misfortune we can imagine, by precautions which, though they do not bar all accidents, do effectually deprive them of that grand and tragic character which so powerfully affects the nobler sensations implanted in the heart of man. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">The more prominent men of the middle ages acted their part with an earnestness that impressed the stamp of their force on the century, the generation, or the country that produced them; different from ours, in which the sum of infinitesimal mediocrities of intelligence is found to outweigh <cb/>and overbear talent and mind in the gifted unit;</hi> how humiliating our self-conceit is it for us now to feel that every great genius must dilute the expression of his conceptions<note type="authorial" place="right" resp="#h1">? Why must he? Is he a "great" genius if he does?</note>  down to the level suited to the meaner capacity of his contemporaries!</p>
                <p>It was only when manhood and order resumed their lost place on the ruins of the Roman Empire, that we can trace the revival of that spirit which will perform and commemorate things worthy of posterity, and which will add to the written mind of a country that which is to bear witness to future generations of the sentiments that actuated a living one, and of the actions to which they gave rise. The former cultivation, the influence originating with Italy and Greece, had become torpid under the continual deposit of barbarism: but after a time the barbarians themselves became tinctured with humanity. Rude themselves, they felt there was something more savage than themselves bursting in upon them from the outer darkness, and threatening to envelope them in it, as they had the Romans. The Goths had to resist the Huns; the Franks to do battle with Saracens; and Christian Europe to this day gratefully acknowledge the event of Poitiers, in which the strong hand and stout heart of the founder of the Carlovingian greatness first rolled back the springtide of Moslem fanaticism: nor was it unnatural that, with the rising political vigour and military valour of this dynasty, uniting under its sway a people become confident in their skill, and penetrated with a conviction of their superior dignity and force, the literary aspiration should have endeavoured to record them in chronicle and song.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline" hand="#h3">Charlemagne himself, the stalwart emperor, united to the prowess of the ancient Germanic warrior, the head to command, and the spirit of order and arrangement</hi> <span xml:id="s1" from="#s1" to="#s2" rend="wavyLine-right" hand="#h3"/>which has handed him down as the founder of social order in Europe, even more than its conqueror. Always at war against brute force, imposing, tyrannically enough, his views of civilization on the hordes who adjoined his empire, it may be doubted whether, after all, his aggressions were unnecessary, or solely the result of ambition. Saracens and Saxons on either confine of his dominions, equally menaced the countries he guarded, for some generations. He<anchor xml:id="s2"/> may be excused, then, for anticipating, by his northern expeditions into the territories of the last, a possible invasion of his own. A similar cause carried him into Spain, and gave rise to the disaster long so famous in the poetry of Roncesvalles; nor can we wonder at the fancy which led the bards of</p>
            </div1>
            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="duk_ap_00124.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">182</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">Literature of the Middle Ages.</hi></fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top right">July,</fw>
                <p>that and succeeding time, combining religious feeling with admiration of courageous devotion, to imagine a mystical association between the martyrdom of the devoted knight, and the crucifixion of the Saviour. Roland, the single champion of Christendom, against the host of infidels from the solemn gorges of his Pyrenean Calvary, invokes the aid of the distant king; in vain sounds that wild horn of despair, whose unveiling echoes were destined never to reach the imperial ear. They were but the knell and death-note of its expiring champion.</p>
                <p>All these traditions which so powerfully lit up the imagination of those men of few but intense feelings, are not absolutely contemporaneous. Charlemagne's fame grew in after generations, partly from a comparison with the inferiority of the successors afforded by his family, and partly from the resumption of the victorious movement against the Mohammedan power, to which his exploits and those of his great father had given the first impulse. The great Charles seemed as he receded backwards into the midst of time, and the recollections of the past, to swell into colossal proportions and fame, as he became the centre of a great epic conception; popular belief investing him with a fabulous renown, beyond even that which, from his exploits and wisdom, is his own historical indefeasible right. Our love of the marvellous incessantly prompts us to grace traditions current amongst ourselves, with some celebrated name; and this instinct was doubly active throughout the lands which preserved the records of its Niebelungen, and among a people prone to indulge in legendary superstitions.</p>
                <p>The feudal dismemberment consequent on his demise, destroyed the comprehensive system of imperial unity established by <span xml:id="s3" from="#s3" to="#s4" rend="wavyLine-left" hand="#h3"/>Charlemagne. Nevertheless, during the security his long reign afforded to the interior of his empire, a certain degree of civilization had grown up with it, and some measure of social comfort, which remained after the severance of the political links which bound together his dominions. He, himself, was in some sort a deserter from the camp of barbarism, and becoming a convert to the Roman style and name, he was an apostate from that of his fathers.<anchor xml:id="s4"/></p>
                <p>It is remarked by Guizot, that the few books composed in those times were remarkable monuments of the richness and activity of the humankind; and though the classical authors will eternally survive the men who produced them, and the nations they describe, yet one finds in the middle <cb/>ages views as ample and deep, original questions examined with power of reasoning and vigour of thought, although without clearness or elegance. Between the senility of the departing tongue and the lisping infancy of the modern ones, mankind could not often find the fitting vehicle for the conveyance of their meaning.</p>
                <p>The long romance of 'Reynard the Fox,' in spite of its uncouth style, is an example of the invention, variety, and satire attained by the literary spirit of those times. The hero, Reynier, or Reynardus, who was given his name to the animal as well as the tale, is shown by M. St. Mc de Girardin, to have been a descendent of Charlemagne, and a great feudal prince in Lorraine, Lorraine, in the tenth century.<ref xml:id="ref1" target="#n1">*</ref> He is the friend of confident of Zwentebold, king of Lorraine, (the lion of the fable). The lion, the king of beasts, believes for a time that his faithful minister, the fox, has fallen a victim to his zeal in an adventure undertaken for the furtherance of the monarchical pastime. Hereupon great royal lamentation, a soliloquy; but it is that of a real prince after all&#8212;who is sorry that his servant has fallen in the execution of his duty; not that he regrets having employed the fox in a dangerous mission, but he praises him for his self-devotion. "He was quite right, was the faithful fox, in taking on himself the adventure; if he had not done so, I should now be where he is&#8212;I should be dead." The fox, however, had not deserved these lamentations on the part of his suzerain, who, after discovering his treachery, besieges him in his castle. (The duke Reynier was twice besieged at Durfos, on the Meuse, by Zwentebold). The lion unable to reduce the castle by force of arms, has recourse to the ecclesiastical authority; the audacious rhymester introduces as ass in the character of arch-priest; the ass excommunicates the fox, but the irreligious animal, as an incredulous as if he had kept company with the philosophers of the eighteenth century, only jests at the excommunication.</p>
                <p>Latin still continued to be the resort of diplomacy, law, and theology, and was susceptible of vigour and purity enough on those occasions. The insipid compositions of the fourth, fifth, and sixth centuries afford no criterion of the business-like power with which it was wielded on the fitting occasions by men who had a purpose to serve, or a great object in view, which called fort their ability and strength. Many a classical poet is now read at schools, grammatically</p>
                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
                <note xml:id="n1" target="#ref1" type="authorial" place="bottom right" anchored="true">* See St. Mc de Girardin's 'Notices sur l'Allemagne, R&#233;cit du Moyen Age,' Vol. ii. p. 170, <hi rend="italic">et sequ.</hi></note>          
            </div1>
            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="duk.00025.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <note type="authorial" place="top" resp="#h1">Troubadours&#8212;poets &amp; singers&#8212;South France&#8212;also Italy, Spain, Germany, Britain &amp;c. 11th, 12th, 13th, countries</note>
                <note type="authorial" place="top" resp="#h1">the troubadours of the middle ages</note>
                <fw type="header" place="top left">1849.</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">Literature of the Middle Ages.</hi></fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">183</fw>
                <p>construed, scanned, and parsed, without this laborious industry enabling the plodding student to seize the reality and spirit of the writer. The fancy Latin poems of the middle ages, when cultivated as a barren discipline of learning, resemble school-boy exercises; but the Latin, when resorted to by men for the accomplishment of adequate political purposes, worthily seconded their acquirements and even their passions. Speaking of it, Villemain observes that on these occasions it assumed an elevation and an energy quite singular.</p>
                <p>"Do you think when the men of action and council who surrounded the first Norman king in England, Lanfranc and others, expressed themselves in Latin, they did not carry into it all the fulness and vigour of their thought? I know not whether William the Conqueror dictated his letters himself, but assuredly it was no common secretary, no obscure parish clerk who translated them; for there is nothing in diplomatic eloquence more cogent, forcible, and original than his reply to Gregory VII., in which he promises him the tribute, and refuses him the homage he demanded for England."</p>
                <p>Europe was changing, had indeed become very different from the Europe of Charlemagne; but in order to hasten the evolution of her political destinies and complete the change for which events were silently preparing, there was wanting what had not arisen since the time of the first German emperor&#8212;great men who can sway and bind a whole nation’s energy and intellect to their views, and labour for their own end, "qui l'adoptent et le poussent, en leur disant ce que'lles croyent, en leur faisant faire ce qu'ils veuillent." In this the eleventh century, it gave an impulse though its leaders; for, says M. Villemain,</p>
                <p>"It is only as a sequel to great events, and under the influence of some superior genius, that the intellect of a whole nation grows. But I cannot assign the exact date of this&#8212;there are some revolutions in the spirit and the idiom of nations like those that take place in our own physical existence; we are not aware of what each day takes away from us; we believe ourselves to-day the same as yesterday, and yet with a succession of days, put one after another, we find ourselves one day quite a different thing; we have passed from youth to manhood, from maturity to old age. So it is with nations, they do not see themselves change, they do not feel that they descend, that their course is changed; all of a sudden they find themselves elsewhere."</p>
                <p>There were three men in particular, who impressed their seals upon this 11th century. A pope, a robber, and a king. Gregory VII., Roger Guiscard, and William of<cb/> England. Of these the Norman Guiscard is but a heroic adventurer, whose arms carve him out a kingdom in Sicily. Our William-the-Conqueror&#8212;his very name proclaims his glory&#8212;a genius truly commanding and political&#8212;a Charles V. of the 11th century. But the pope is incomparably the greatest of the three; he has nothing but the power of his own mind, aided by the belief of others, to subdue the whole world. And he all but succeeded&#8212;was very near establishing the federation of all Europe into a political family, of which the bishop of Rome should be the referee and moderator; and though in his hands this project failed, though he died in exile, and almost a prisoner, yet his ideas, more powerful than banishment, more enduring than life, remained behind. We do not mean the truth of the Catholic religion (though possibly it was purer than now), but the principle, the subordination of matter to mind, of brute force to intellect, which has extended itself for successive centuries in the train of Christianity, among various nations, and by the free adoption of willing converts; without violence like the progress of the Mahommedans in India, Africa, and Spain, or the Turks in Europe; and though the temporal power of the papacy be now gone, and its spiritual dominion lessened by the progress of rational Christianity, its influence is hardly even yet effete. Probably at first, an innate and indestructible love of liberty, which even in the most oppressed nations is never entirely trodden out, aided in the erection of the papal supremacy; for though it was no defence against temporal persecution of prince and potentate, it was a resource to the object of it to imagine some one on earth greater than the oppressor, some mysterious authority of whom the despot stood in awe.</p>
                <p><span xml:id="s5" from="#s5" to="#s6" rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h1"/>Powerful as the Church came to be under the guidance of such spirits as Gregory VII. and Innocent III., it was a necessary consequence that power should be abused: it was the vagrant minstrelsy of the troubadours that most effectually satirised the covetousness and luxury of her dissolute priesthood&#8212;sometimes "une malice profonde qui ferait peur &#225; des temps plus cultiv&#233;s." These were the founders of the southern poetry; not mere ballad-singers, as might be supposed, but knights and warriors, lords and chatelains, as well as wandering rhymesters. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">One is astonished at the vivacity and variety, the gaiety, and often the sarcasm of their rude effusion; it is not a little singular that wit should so prevail where force was in the ascendant,</hi> but the most warlike seigneurs were often<anchor xml:id="s6"/></p>
            </div1>
            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="duk.00025.003.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <note type="authorial" place="top" rend="circled" resp="#h1">fit for lords and ladies, w. saloons&#8212;</note>
                <note type="authorial" place="top" resp="#h1">The troubadours were "gentle"&#8212;knightly, reformed&#8212;the trouveres were in comparison fitter for the common people</note>
                <note type="authorial" place="top left" rend="circled" resp="#h1">(trouver &#8212;(troo-vee)&#8212;to find)</note>
                <note type="authorial" place="top left" resp="#h1">Trouveres</note>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">184</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">Literature of the Middle Ages.</hi></fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top right">July,</fw>
                <p>poets. The trouv&#232;res were different; less genteel and accomplished than their brethren, the troubadours; <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">they represented the unstamped press of our times, and were the precursors of 'Punch,' and the 'Charivari.' The troubadour was a gentleman, and lived with his compeers</hi> : <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">the trouv&#232;re was a ten-pounder, a pot-walloper, who, with his brother gossip, abused and ridiculed the authority or the institution which frightened while oppressed him,</hi> and which he detested, but with a secret and respectful hatred, the cunning of his story making amends for its want of refinement and poetic grace.</p>
                <p>One ought not, in speaking of the eleventh century, to omit mentioning the Cid Ruy Diaz, both from the influence his exploits exercised over the feelings of his countrymen, as well as the early poetry of the Peninsula. Pent within its narrow limits, his renown overshadows his native land; his career is almost the only thing in which interests us in that period of Spanish history, as it is the chief model to which the romance writers of his country have resorted for example. The type of Castilian honour delineated in the songs of the 'Romancero del Cid,' assumes a delicacy and loyalty which makes us forget the cotemporary barbarism. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">The Cid</hi> himself enjoys, in common with <note type="authorial" place="left" resp="#h1">(George Heriot)</note><hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">the celebrated Scanderbeg, the proud distinction of being known to the posterity of his countrymen by an appellation conferred on each by the awe of their mortal enemies&#8212;Turk and Sacacen.</hi></p>
                <p>The end of the twelfth and beginning of the thirteenth centuries were characterised by the greatness and ability of the men who appeared upon the stage, and the general progress of mind. One sees on the throne, in the army, in the church, men of strong individual powers and extraordinary energy. Think of a crusade bringing into the field <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">three such men as Federick Barbarossa, Richard C&#339;ur-de-Lion, and Philip Augustus;</hi> the last and least of whom was the victor at Bouvines. The first, though haughty and stern, was a historian,<ref xml:id="ref2" target="#n2">*</ref> as well as a ruler and a soldier; his firmness and constancy, in good evil fortune, as well as his talents, render him the most prominent ornament of the house Hohenstaufen, whose princes, to their honour, amidst all the tragic vicissitudes that accompanied their chequered career of above a century, never wanted devoted friends and followers to share their fortunes and their fate. Our own King Richard, of Lion-heart and the gaye science, was a troubadour:&#8212;</p>
                <milestone unit="undelcared" rend="horbar-full"/>
                <note xml:id="n2" target="#ref2" type="authorial" place="bottom left" anchored="true">* Barbarossa composed memoirs of his life.</note>
                <cb/>
                <p>"We cannot help feeling the charm. Place him in a more humane age, and where the accompaniments are less violent, and he would be, if not a just and gentle pince, a great man; who to the boldness of the Swedish Charles united more political genius and prudence. Always at war, always at a distance from his dominions, his name<ref xml:id="ref3" target="#n3">*</ref> yet fills the monuments of England."</p>
                <p>The prominent figures which M. Villemain presents as examples of the thirteenth century, are a brilliant company. Besides the Pope, Innocent III., in France alone three great kings&#8212;Philip Augustus, St. Louis, and Philip the Fair; of whom, he justly remarks, only one was a good man. In Spain, Ferdinand II. (the saint), and Alonzo the Wise, the titular Emperor of Germany&#8212;a royal alchemist, who imagined himself to have discovered the philosopher's stone. We might almost add a third, in the person of Sancho el Bravo, were it only to notice the singularity of three royal descents&#8212;a father, son, and grandson all of remarkable qualities and vigour, succeeding each other on the throne. Nor ought the Emperor Frederic II. to be omitted; a troubadour, like Richard, an <hi rend="italic">espirit fort</hi>as well as a <hi rend="italic">bel espirit</hi>. This imperial Crusader, who had fought for the faith against the Saracens, under the walls of Jerusalem, and then crowned within the holy city in spite of that faith (which had just then ex-communicated its champion), surrounded himself on his return to Palermo, with poets, astrologers, and philosophers, chosen mostly from among the infidels whom he had routed. The Popes accused him of writing the celebrated book, little known, if it were even ever seen, 'De Tribus Impostoribus.' A wit, a soldier, a statesman, and an author, he bore some resemblance in his society, adventures, opinions, and supposed works, to the other German prince of the same name, who appears after an interval of six hundred years.</p>
                <p>These were the Continental worthies. But in England it is otherwise. <note type="authorial" place="bottom" resp="#h1">&#9758;a great saying</note><hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">It is not the superiority of the princes that leads and forms opinions&#8212;it is their weakness and their incapacity.</hi> John Lackland, by his misfortunes and his shame, develops the genius of the English nation more than William the Conqueror, or Richard C&#339;ur-de-Lion, with all their glory&#8212;he gives the great character to England.</p>
                <p>Gibbon has been unjust as to the temporal and carnal motives of the Crusaders; he was by temperament disqualified from the</p>
                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
                <note xml:id="n3" target="#ref3" type="authorial" place="bottom right" anchored="true">* Legal memory begins in this time.</note>
            </div1>
            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="duk.00025.004.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <note type="authorial" place="top" resp="#h1">(serfdom and villenage)</note>
                <note type="authorial" place="top" resp="#h1"><hi rend="underline">Crusades</hi></note>
                <fw type="header" place="top left">1849.</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">Literature of the Middle Ages.</hi></fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">185</fw>
                <p><note type="authorial" place="left" resp="#h1"><hi rend="underline">Crusades</hi></note><span xml:id="s7" from="#s7" to="#s8" rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1"/>appreciation of their call. Many, no doubt, contemplated aggrandisement or plunder. But with the mass who bent their steps to the East, the simple desire to rescue the cradle of their belief from the invaders of the Holy Land, was a sufficient stimulus, according, as it did, with the warlike spirit of the age; while the combination of lofty religious enthusiasm with knightly prowess, lent to these enterprises a grandeur and force beyond that of ordinary vulgar warfare.<anchor xml:id="s8"/></p>
                <p>Man constantly proposes to himself some advantage to be gained over his fellow-men, by skill, industry, arms or craft, with the profession of God's service or the public weal on his lips. The motives of the more scheming Crusaders, Charles of Anjou, Bohemond the Norman, Conrad, and others, will bear as close an inspection as those of the chief spectaculars of present day, although wholly guiltless of such an enterprise. Yet the endeavour to manufacture for the whole world, is a sort of crusade against the industrious existence of every other country. The middle ages were more humane&#8212;they merely <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">imposed serfdom and villenage,</hi> while the manufacturing Christian exterminates his rival by starving him.</p>
                <p>Whatever were the mainsprings, the effects were <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">the first general European movement since Europe itself had been remodelled&#8212;a revival of the eternal struggle between our continent and that of Asia.</hi> The migratory spirit has survived to the present times, but it is only the affluent who travel. In those of which we speak, representatives of every order in society, from the highest downwards, assumed the cross. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">In their necessary absence, many fiefs changed hands; a new distribution of domains ensued</hi>; and even on the return of the travelled combatants, full of new ideas and experience, a change in the customs, if not the condition of society, gradually occurred.<hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">The solitude of many a lonely manor and castle became intolerable to the owner, who in the camp, in the Holy Land,</hi> had been accustomed to the conversation of kings and the minstrelsy of the troubadours. The greater barons surrounded themselves with a society often embracing the company of their smaller and dependant vassals&#8212;a first step towards refinement, since language, amid this less rude existence, tended to adapt itself to the increased requirements of courtesy and politeness. Some of the restored wanderers left memorials of their adventures. We owe to them in particular two of the earliest histories; each remarkable, not only as the testimony of eye-<cb/><span xml:id="s9" from="#s9" to="#s10" rend="wavyLine-right" hand="#h1"/>witnesses of extraordinary events, but as much so for their contribution to the forming of the French language.</p>
                <p>Geoffrey de Villehardouin begins the known French prose writers. This baron, marshal of Champagne, sets out with some of his neighbours from a tournament in the country, for the conquest of Constantinople (for so the expedition turned out). They installed an emperor there, forthwith repented them, retook it for themselves, repented of that too, and finally set up Baldwin. The chronicler himself received as his lot the city of Massinople, in Thessaly. Such was the venturous spirit of the times, there was no limit to their enterprise. "On partait alors pour Babylone, ou allait offrier son &#233;p&#233;e &#224; un roi de Thessalonique, on ne savait pas o&#249; &#233;tait Thessalonique, mais on ressemblait 20 ou 30 gentilhommes et on partait." Joinville belonged to the same order; a feudal baron, and friend of the great St. Louis; with a certain degree of worldliness and frivolity, he seems nevertheless to have been penetrated with <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">the simple grandeur of the character of his master.</hi> The seneschal of Champagne describes, with all the vigour of imagination and all the delightful freshness of ignorance, the strange scenes of the East, so full of action, and colour, and life (spite of the taciturnity and indolence of their inhabitants), to our western eyes. "Il les d&#233;crit comme H&#233;erodote; mieux que lui peut-&#234;tre, car H&#233;rodote &#233;tait d&#233;j&#224; savant, Joinville, Dieu merci, ne l'est pas du tout."</p>
                <p>Among the crusades, that against the Albigenses was truly hateful. Those against the Saracens were not devoid of a kind of chivalrous courtesy, which was entirely superseded by the brutal ferocity of Montford and his followers, the missionaries of Innocent III. The Count of Toulouse was forced, by the intolerant priesthood, to march against his own unoffending subjects. With the exception of some imperfect traditions which Protestant sympathy in this century<anchor xml:id="s10"/> has explored without substantiating, no witnesses on behalf of the accused were examined at the time, or even permitted to speak to posterity&#8212;all other testimony than that of the persecution was suppressed. "C'etaient les inquisiteurs qui s'etaient faits historiens," they wrote the sole account of the crime they punished. But retribution, though tardy, overtook them. "Le r&#233;cit des inquisiteurs fut comment&#233; uniquement plus tard par l'esprit philosophique;" that is, the persecutors were judged and sentenced as definitively by their enemies as the Albigenses had been by theirs. Doubtless the barbarity then unchained and insti-</p>
            </div1>
            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="duk.00025.005.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <note type="authorial" place="top" resp="#h1">Dante &#9759;</note>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">186</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">Literature of the Middle Ages.</hi></fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top right">July,</fw>
                <p>gated by the Church, powerfully aided the reactionary under-current of disaffection, independence, and dissent, which finally broke up the unity of the Christian religion. Even those who were engaged in these cruelties repented and doubted.</p>
                <p>Rome, however, was yet all-powerful in matters of faith. In temporal matters, the neighbouring states of the Peninsula were beginning to emerge into inconvenient importance. Pepin Charlemagne, when new and insecure masters of Italy, willingly countenanced the enfranchisement and increase of the great cities of the north, as a counterpoise to the yet smouldering Lombard element for which they had so recently substituted the Carlovingian fortunes; a larger proportion of nobles embraced an urban life, and sought protection within their walls, then was the case in countries where the feudal institutions were paramount&#8212;a circumstance probably not without share in elevating the character and imagination of the citizens. The freedom which they enjoyed was favourable to the development of the understanding. "Their struggles are schools of municipal independence." The sentiment of personal liberty, exemption from all domination but their own, was a compensation for privation and insecurity of other kinds. Having no feudal superior, no hereditary lord as patron, in times when the general opinion and feeling ascribed every man to some superior, as part of an endless chain of dependence and subordination, they were often fated for a time to become the property and prey of a master of their own choice. Villemain remarks that, with less eloquence, with a something still barbarous, the Italy of the middle ages with its vain, turbulent, generous, hardy existence, recalls classic Greece.<span xml:id="s11" from="#s11" to="#s12" rend="bracket-right" hand="#h1"/>Dante is at once the Homer and &#198;schylus of this newer period. Their rude liberties, growing up beneath the shadow of the sanguinary struggles between the priesthood and the empire, these were the images that presented themselves to his poetic vision, with all their accompaniments, which, in his marvellous creation, assumed such mysterious power. His conception affords at once the picture of the middle ages, the root and trunk of the Italian language, and the first modern example of a continuous and refined epoch; yet he was not alone, he was not even the poet of his time, in a country so prolific of genius, music, and verse. But the course of events, and the treatment he himself experienced at the hands of his party and his country, conspired to turn the current of his power into a particular channel. Born a Guelph, invested<cb/><anchor xml:id="s12"/> <span xml:id="s13" from="#s13" to="#s14" rend="bracket-right" hand="#h1"/>with a high office in his native city of Florence, he was driven forth by a caprice of popular feeling for the rest of his life; condemned, in his absence, to the fire, if he fell into their hands, he became a Ghibelin&#8212;a partisan of the emperor&#8212;not that he loved his native land less, but that he hated its oppressors more, under whatever democratic disguise they were concealed. He wished that the imperial sway should supersede the republican liberties, since they had become tyrannical and unjust. The great poet wandered up and down France and Italy in this hopeless pilgrimage, in which the composition of his immortal poem was at once his occupation, his solace, his glory and his revenge&#8212;his indignant and fierce appeal to posterity against contemporary oppression.</p>
                <p>"Many a transgressor sent to his account."</p>
                <p>"Long ere in Florence numbered with the dead."</p>
                <p>"Master of heaven, of purgatory, and of paradise&#8212;owning them by the right of genius&#8212;he could bestow situations in any of those upon friend or foe. That exile whom you had banished from Florence, he hardly knew where to lay his head, obliged, as he says, to go up and down another's stairs, and to experience how bitter tastes a stranger's bread&#8212;he was more powerful than you! From the midst of his flight and proscription, he thought, he wrote, he punished his enemies. There were three in particular who had persecuted him; he did not kill them&#8212;he left them alive at Florence; but in his verses he said they were dead, that their bodies had only the semblance of life, animated by demons. These terrible recitals made the Florentines avoid the approach of the three demoniacs; who, perhaps, themselves, were not sure that they were alive,&#8212;did not know of a certainty that they were not emanations from the bottomless pit, and that, after all, the poet was right."</p>
                <p>There was something unearthly in the reputation which Dante possessed even in his life-time. Alone in the world, far from kith and kin, a mystic terror attached to the name of one reputed to have intercourse with evil spirits: he heard himself held up by the gross but not illiterate vulgar as one descending into the Limbo, and returning thence at pleasure. "Yet the exile never lost sight of Florence. There would have been a feature wanting in his character, certainly in the dramatic interest his name inspires, had he less regretted his country." That country was ready to recall him, on paying (so the sordid traders who govern, insisted) a ransom for the offences of which he was unjustly accused. After fifteen years, it would have been sweet to return&#8212;but no in dishonour. "That is not my way to re-enter my country!"<anchor xml:id="s14"/></p>
            </div1>
            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="duk.00025.006.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <note type="authorial" place="top" resp="#h1">Petrarch Froissart&#8212;Boccaccio} all three contemporaries of Chaucer</note>
                <fw type="header" place="top left">1849.</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">Literature of the Middle Ages.</hi></fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">187</fw>
                <p>A very different man was Petrarch. Dante had been a soldier, a politician, a moralist. Petrarch was an ecclesiastic (at least he held a sincere rectory)&#8212;a squire of dames. Almost ashamed of writing Italian, in which alone his fame survives, and proud of his Latin compositions, now utterly forgotten and neglected, Petrarch, however, from the ferment which his poetical triumph occasioned in Rome, indirectly promoted a political revolution, which might have been more enduring. The Tribune Rienzi, his friend, animated with the prestige of antiquity, cherished a dram of Roman supremacy, a restoration of that power attained by the arms and the exertions of the ancient commonwealth. The splendour of the reminiscences attaching to the circuit of the Seven Hills, as it had done to Gregory VII.&#8212;Sovereignty,&#8212;religious or political&#8212;was the idea of those who trod upon the ashes of the Fabii and the Scipios. An aspiration after those grandeurs that had passed away, actuated the tribune in his harangues to the populace, "et dans ce sens il agitait le peurple savant et d&#233;guenill&#233; de Rome."</p>
                <p><note type="authorial" place="left" resp="#h1">Italian language</note><hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">Next to Dante, Boccacio was the greatest contributor to the formation of the Italian language. To the former it was indebted for nerve and dignity, to the latter for elegance, wit, and ease.</hi> In some respects Boccacio was the more useful: less lofty and grandiose, it became in his hands more manageable, while a vocabulary of ordinary life was stamped for current use by his authority. We do not speak of the morality of his tales; but he was, for the age in which he lived, hardly an indelicate writer, though his style and ideas were formed in the court of Johanna, in that Naples at once so sanguinary and so voluptuous.</p>
                <p>"Mary Stuart," says Villemain, "was not alone in the world; for in the fourteenth century, was born a woman, who, like her, was a queen, lovely, guilty, and unfortunate; who, wild with pleasure and frivolity, sported with grace in the midst of festive pomps; who suspected of having put to death a husband unworthy of her, perished herself by the hand which disputed her throne&#8212;never were two medials more worthy of being suspended side by side."</p>
                <p>Froissart was another priest. We owe more to some of these ecclesiastics for their contributions to history and literature, than for their examples in morality and religion, during these periods. Without much feeling for his vocation, he had the same strong love of chronicling military adventure, which has given to the present generation 'The Subaltern,' and the 'Recollections of the<cb/> Peninsula.' In his pages we become acquainted with the cream of the then existing society; kings, knights, ladies, protected and welcomed him throughout his whole life; he was the friend of our Black Prince, "the great man of the fourteenth century." Of the habits and existence of the lower orders at this time we know nothing from him; it is to his contemporary the elder Villani, that we must refer for notice of this sort. Villani, a shrewd Florentine merchant, always bargaining and trading as if New York had been his home; caring no more about battles, tournays, and fleets, save so far as they may might affect the market he resorted to, writes as he travels. It is quite refreshing, amid the din of arms all round him, to learn from the commercial traveller of the fourteenth century some of those statistical views which almost exclusively belong to our colder calculations of the nineteenth. With the feelings of chivalry, the "garde d'honneur de la f&#233;odalit&#233;," as M. Villemain happily terms it, Villani had nothing in common; he could not, in his civic simplicity, understand that enthusiasm which animated and embellished the arming of a knight after the ideas of those times, introducing a mixture of austere devotion and vagrant liberty which made the ceremony itself a religious initiation.</p>
                <p>Even the feudal institutions themselves were not without their brighter points. The vassal, though he was held in fealty and homage, might renounce that, or his country on surrendering up the fief or benefice which alone imposed upon him the corresponding duties and services. Their essence was the duty of man to man, his superior and chief, not that of a subject to his sovereign, or a citizen to his state. In modern times, we hold that no one can renounce his nationality, or acquire a right to bear arms against the land of his birth: the times we speak of were, in this respect, more tolerant and liberal. Villemain, comparing Froissart's account of the Black Prince's demeanour to King John when taken prisoner at Poitiers, with that given by Livy of the meeting, under the like circumstances, of Paulus Emilius and Perseus, justly observes that advantage is wholly on the side of the chronicler and our heroic Edward. The French academician delicately administers to the vanity of his countrymen, by reminding them that the victor was still the subject and liegeman of the sovereign whom he overcame.</p>
                <p>"C'est que le Prince de Galles, bien que vainqueur du roi Jean, se souvenait qu'il &#233;tait son vassal; ainsi du millieu de cette f&#233;odalit&#233; si</p>
            </div1>
            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="duk.00025.007.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <note type="authorial" place="top" resp="#h1">Feudality</note>
                <note type="authorial" place="top" resp="#h1">&#9759;</note>
                <note type="authoria" place="top" resp="#h1">Language</note>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">188</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">Literature of the Middle Ages.</hi></fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top right">July,</fw>
                <p>cruelle et si barbare, sortait une urbanit&#233; nouvelle. Le souvenir d'un certain devoir faisait que la vassal victorieux dans une bataille, servait &#224; table humblement son seigneur, vain&#231;u et prisonnier."</p>
                <p>A great statesman and philosopher has observed, too, that to this same feudality, heavy and oppressive as it looms to us through the haze of centuries, we are indebted indirectly for the first germs of liberty, contained in the acknowledged right of resistance to the superior when he transgressed the limits of his rights. Individual will has since been replaced by public law, personal judgement and caprice by the collective reason of the community. Political philosophers have sometimes dreamt of social compacts; their existence has always been problematical in the light in which they have been insisted upon by speculative writers, in order to support their theories of government. But the feudal compact, no matter how formed at first, really did exist in activity and vigour, and that sense of doing themselves a right, which impelled the landowners into the field at Runnymede&#8212;the right of claiming redress against the lord for injuries&#8212;has laid the foundation of modern liberties.</p>
                <p><span xml:id="s15" from="#s15" to="#s16" rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1"/>M. Guizot declares that "the first essays of poetry, the first intellectual pleasures that Europe tasted on emerging from barbarism, was under shelter of the wings of feudality. For this sort <note type="authorial" place="left" resp="#h1">&#9758;</note>of development of humanity, there must be some activity in the soul&#8212;in life, leisure, too&#8212;a hundred conditions, in fact, which could not occur in the sad, cold, hard lot of the common people. In France, England, Germany, it is with the feudal times that the first literary recollections, the earliest intellectual indulgences of Europe, are connected."<anchor xml:id="s16"/></p>
                <p>The Roman domination had borne comparatively less fruit in Britain, hardly commencing until the ruling state had so long passed its zenith that its vitality was impaired, and its power of imparting institutions and refinement on the decline; and while the remote governors of the British province were practically uncontrolled from Rome, the distance from the great city, and the inferiority of our climate, forbad any great influx of the more polished society, as into Gaul and Spain. The acquisition so long resisted by the Britons, led to an incomplete possession; and in the wane of military spirit, the empire began to rely on stone walls rather than the arms of its soldiers in the field&#8212;witness the huge works of Severus and Antoninus, merely to keep our a few bands of plunderers.</p>
                <p>After the C&#230;sarians, as they were termed, had finally evacuated the island, the<cb/> native British and Cymri stock was recruited from Danish and Saxon grafts, before the first invasion by <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">the Normans, from whom we mediately derive most of the words of Latin origin contained in our language.</hi></p>
                <p><span xml:id="s17" from="#s17" to="#s18" rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h1"/>The progress of our English was slower. From the want of any analogy between it and the dialects so long common to the south-west of Europe, we could derive no aid from the broad extent of surface over which romance or proven&#231;al was spoken. The Anglo-Saxon necessarily rested upon its own indigenous resources. Even then it was but the medium of the lower orders, since, for at least four generations after the Conquest, the governing society communicated only in French; the law proceedings were in that tongue, while prayer and diplomacy resorted to Latin.</p>
                <p>Our language struggled for existence; which it was something to maintain through two conquests, and against men whose settled policy and system it was to uproot it.<ref xml:id="ref4" target="#n4">*</ref> It partook of the national debasement, and<anchor xml:id="s18"/> sympathised with those who avenged the Saxon cause by outbreaks against the Norman yoke, but without any approach to the easier diction of the continent. The Robin-Hood ballads and metrical tales which belong to this date, exemplify the object and style of composition&#8212;<hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">popular enough with the yeoman and franklin, they were despised in hall and tower.</hi> The sympathy is all enlisted on the side of the Saxon deer stealer and outlaw, against organized oppression of Norman sheriff or bishop&#8212;the popular emphatic but unavailing protest against the enthralment of the stranger. The same feeling gives life to those rude rhymes of Scotland which recite the exploits of the Bruce and Wallace.</p>
                <p>Chaucer, whom we sent along with Froissart in the suit of Lionel Duke of Clarence on his bridal expedition to Italy, in 1386, then to make the acquaintance of Boccacio and Petrarch, was their inferior in style only, but not only, but not in invention and ideas. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">Gower his rival, Mandeville the contemporary traveller,</hi> <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">each wrote in Latin, French, and English,</hi> <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">perplexed between their desire of being appreciated by European learning, Norman fashion, and English nationality. The adoption of English for proceedings in courts of justice, in 1362, was</hi> an homage to the increasing power of the Commons, which was inconveniently felt by Edward</p>
                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
                <note type="authorial" xml:id="n4" target="#ref4" place="bottom right" anchored="true"><span xml:id="s19" from="#s19" to="#s20" rend="bracket-right" hand="#h1"/>* The Romans instituted schools for teaching the vanquished their idiom; and the determination of William the Conqueror to eradicate the native speech, is well known. It is fortunate that this successors were less preserving than himself.<anchor xml:id="s20"/></note>
                <note type="authorial" place="bottom right" resp="#h1">&#9757; Language</note>
            </div1>
            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="duk.00025.008.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <note type="authorial" place="top" resp="#h1">"With the close of the 15th Century, the middle-age period expires."</note>
                <note type="authorial" place="top left" resp="#h1">Architecture</note>
                <fw type="header" place="top left">1849.</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">Literature of the Middle Ages.</hi></fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">189</fw>
                <p>III. in his latter years. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">But the Norman-French was still strong in the court and the parliament.</hi> Half a century afterwards, while Henry V. was administering the kingdom of his father-in-law, the public acts intended to take effect in France, recorded in Rymer, are almost invariably in French; while the commissions, warrants, and proclamations directed to English Affairs, are indifferently in French or Latin. Henry the Fifth's will, made just before Agincourt (1415), is in Latin, but terminated with these remarkable words: "This is my last will, subscribed with my own hand&#8212;H. R. Jesu mercy, and grammercy Ladie Marie help!" The king's instructions to Tiptoft going to treat with the Emperor (1417) are in English; which he says he had, for secrecy, written with his own hand. Perhaps he adopted English for the same reason. Shakespeare's representation of his ignorance of French, while wooing the Princess Catherine, is a pure fiction. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">Our language remained unfashionable and clumsy as long as, with the possession of large French fiefs and territories, our kings maintained their pretensions to the throne of that country.</hi> And in admitting the inferiority of our own contemporary literature to that of the great Italians before mentioned, it must be remembered that the latter found a language, which, though not perfect, was commonly spoken by gentle and simple throughout the peninsula.</p>
                <p>We might almost claim Charles Duke of Orleans as a contributor to the English muses; more than one ditty having been composed in our language during his long captivity amongst us. Forced to surrender in the field at Agincourt, he joined the crowd of princes whom our renowned Henry V. had confined in his various prisons. His was Pomfret, which did not always (teste Richard II.) yield up its royal captives alive. The French prince solaced his detention of twenty-five years<ref xml:id="ref5" target="#n5">*</ref> with poetry; which induced Michelet, who evinces a kindly feeling to this family of Orleans, to term him the Beranger of that century.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">With the close of the fifteenth century,</hi><cb/></p>
                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
                <note xml:id="n5" target="#ref5" type="authorial" place="bottom left" anchored="true">* Rymer gives the indenture of his ransom, which evinces the tardy compassion of the son of the victor (Henry VI), 3rd November, 1440; reciting that "our dear cousin and captive, Charles Duke of Orleans, a tempore in quo sinistrante sibi fortun&#515; belli in campo de Agincourt.... Jam sunt 24 et amplius anni, captivitate miser&#515; infr&#224; nostrum regnum Angli&#230; sub custodi&#515; detentus..... velut infelix, alienus, elongatus ab amicis, exulque &#224; solo natali, steriliter et infructuos&#232; magora tempora vit&#230; su&#230; transegit, ade&#242; quod ad extremum depauperatus et adnichilatus, vix valeat attingere vel exiguam artem summ&#230; pro redemptione person&#230; su&#230;."</note>
                <p><span xml:id="s21" from="#s21" to="#s22" rend="bracket-right" hand="#h1"/><hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">the middle-age period expires.</hi> Political Europe assumes a new form by the absorption of great feudatories and the consolidation of inheritances into kingdoms; while its social composition was modified by the gradual advance of the monarchical authority, its religious identity was completely destroyed by the Protestant Reformation and its consequences.<anchor xml:id="s22"/></p>
                <p><hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">What we have gained by the more equal distribution of knowledge, wealth, and power, we have lost in brilliancy and colour; our busy but unimpressive modern times exhibit a prevalence of neutral tints</hi>; <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">the whole tone of our picture is tame, cold, compared with that in which all that most powerfully acts upon the nature of man was brought into salient relief&#8212;his faith and his apprehensions, his power and his frailty, his grandeur and his nothingness.</hi> The human career is more free from extremes, the oscillations are less violent; society, become more fluid, gently undulates, but escapes and abhors the convulsions which agitate the more energetic nature the proclaimed</p>
                <p><span xml:id="s23" from="#s23" to="#s24" rend="bracket-right" hand="#h1"/>It was almost a creed with mankind, that subjugation should be accepted without repining, on condition it proceeded from a heroic land. The opinion of the time, contemptuous of industry, was not dissatisfied when dominion and force were on the same side.<anchor xml:id="s24"/></p>
                <p><hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">We ought not to judge of their attainments</hi><note type="authorial" place="right" resp="#h1">&#9756;</note><hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">simply by the written memorials they have left behind</hi>:<hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">there are some monuments, equally the work of the intellect, which reach the heart through the medium of the imagination, which embody the recondite principles of constructive science with the outward conditions and forms of taste, and which please the eye at the same time that they satisfy the understanding.</hi> In estimating the intellectual claims of these ages to the regard of posterity, we are not to exclude all allusion to their architecture&#8212;a subject, it is true, not directly connected with letters, <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">but which,</hi><note type="authorial" place="right" resp="#h1">&#9756;</note><hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">like them, permits itself to be read and studied.</hi><hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">Whatever has survived the assault of men or the elements&#8212;castle, convent, church, or grange&#8212;all those stupendous edifices, from the midst of decay, still shine forth in that cold, proud beauty, which extorts from us a preference over their younger but less attractive rivals.</hi> In this respect those 600 or 700 years were truly original, inventive, and unmatched. For ten previous centuries, during the Roman republic and empire, men had continued to derive their models from the edifices coeval with Greek freedom and Ionian prosperity, preserving at last only some of the features,</p>
            </div1>
            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="duk.00025.009.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <note type="authorial" place="top" resp="#h1">middle-age architecture</note>
                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="vertbar-short-top"/>
                <note type="authorial" place="top" resp="#h1">modern poetry is "neutral tints"</note>
                <note type="authorial" place="top" resp="#h1">&#9759;</note>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">190</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">Literature of the Middle Ages.</hi></fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top right">July,</fw>
                <p>but without classic air and physiognomy.<span xml:id="s25" from="#s25" to="#s26" rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1"/>But with the middle ages came in a style more elevated in its character, purer in taste, more ingenious in the disposition of materials, and the creation of resource and effect, than any of the debased classical varieties which preceded it. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">The barbarian conceptions, whether Lombard, Gothic, or Norman, are infinitely superior to the remaining Gallo-Roman buildings, in which a confusion of details and hesitating outline destroy all effect save that of richness&#8212;a sure mark of the decline of genius and of the poverty of invention.</hi> On the other hand, each phase of medi&#230;val architecture has its own peculiar properties of arrangement and form. Saxon, Norman, English, and the varieties of Gothic, all akin to each other and yet distinct, respectively manifest a fitness and harmony that animates them with an eloquent expression throughout. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">The mind of a country speaks as plainly through such structures as it does through<anchor xml:id="s26"/> its writings;</hi> <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">nay, it is a kind of writing itself, more susceptible than parchment, more durable than papyrus, when the inert stone, the plastic clay, becomes conscious of the aspirations of the designer, impressed with the emblems of his hope, and typified with the symbols of his creed.</hi> <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">Comparing these with the after productions of the same art, we must admit the inferiority of the moderns.</hi> The examples which the<span xml:id="s27" from="#s27" to="#s28" rend="wavyLine-left" hand="#h1"/> Hanoverian dynasty has been call in to witness, have been deficient in point of taste and absolutely null in that of character. The Tudor possessed much of the latter, the Stuarts are recognizable, and even <note type="authorial" place="left" resp="#h1">&#9758;</note>William of Orange brought over a certain Dutch stateliness and breadth. But the last 150 years have deprived us even of that. We have deprived us even of that. We have now no style proper to this stage of our national existence and career; so little do we know our won mind on the subject, that we borrow equally from all&#8212;Grecian, Roman, Gothic, Italian, at one and this same time, almost in the same place. All these various examples dispute with each other in the halls of the Royal Academy. But we have nothing that marks our own epoch in architecture, except an extensive reliance on the merits of every former one. This age, so luxurious, religious, rich, and vain, will be utterly undistinguishable hereafter by any internal chronological evidence afforded by its erections, of the character of the architecture prevalent among its people.<anchor xml:id="s28"/></p>
                <p>All arts did not advance alike in the period we spoke of. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">Statuary and painting were stiff and cold, perhaps designedly and conventionally so</hi>, to be in unison with the<cb/> solemnity of the edifices of which they <span xml:id="s29" from="#s29" to="#s30" rend="bracket-right" hand="#h1"/>were the subordinate adjuncts. There is no want of expression and skill, though the pictures are wanting in action and grace. Besides their unrivalled perspective, their interiors (where the colours have been spared by time or fanaticism), enchant us now with the mellow richness of their tone, and with the skill with which hues so bold and brilliant have been balanced and softened by the introduction of contrasts and harmonies<anchor xml:id="s30"/></p>
                <p><hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">The cold timidity and puritanical asceticism of later days has reduced us to pale neutral tints, with no warmth of colour to welcome the stranger, no elevation of tone to inspire the worshipper.</hi> <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">When the architect of to-day ventures on the use of colour, he is obliged to resort to the examples of polychrome that remain to us from men whose obscure names have never reached us, whose precepts lie buried with them, but whose unsurpassed practice can only be reproduced by close and faithful imitation.</hi></p>
                <p>We ask pardon for this slight digression from a subject which we must now close, with the hope that the reader will do M. Villemain the justice to peruse the two <span xml:id="s31" from="#s31" to="#s32" rend="wavyLine-right" hand="#h1"/>volumes of which an imperfect outline has been given. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">If literature be, in his happy phrase, the instinctive consciousness of a nationality</hi>&#8212;if it was the representative and reflex of public opinion, and if language possesses for us any other value beyond its use in ministering to our commonest requirements&#8212;<lg>
                    <l>"Long may we love to catch the simple chime</l>
                    <l>Of minstrel harps and spell and fabling rhyme,</l>
                    <l>To view the festive rites, the knightly play,</l>
                    <l>That decked heroic Albion's elder day."</l>
                </lg>
                We may look back with an excusable pride at the few remaining memorials of the ideas of those who have so long gone before. These records are the title-deeds of our nation's fame. We may cherish, with a pardonable emotion, the written thoughts of the past, as an earnest that the future shall not be unworthy of it; since a country which has no retrospective efforts of this description which it surveys with satisfaction, has a little of promise to which it can look forward with confidence: there remains to it only the present&#8212;ease exempt from mental discipline&#8212;enjoyment devoid of elevated sentiment.</p>
                <p>Such does not suffice for the intellectual nature of man. Independent of the lessons of experience by which the events and feelings of bygone generations are rendered interesting to the living one, and the stock of</p>
            </div1>
            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="duk.00025.010.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <note type="authorial" place="top" resp="#h1">The English poet has reminiscences, and continually extols them,&#8212;the American poet has a future, and must extol it.&#8212;</note>
                <fw type="header" place="top left">1849.</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">Botany.</hi></fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">191</fw>
                <p>our practical knowledge is enriched from the pages of former times, it is not too much to assume that the mind is expanded, raised, and refreshed by partial abstraction from the pursuits, grave or frivolous, that engross its ordinary existence. On the contrary, we are invigorated by an occasional excursion into the domain of olden time; by some converse with <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">the strains that waked our fathers' patriotism, the songs that touched our mothers' breasts, the repositories of the wisdom, the fancy, the sorrows, or the daring of those distant forefathers,</hi> <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">who, if they did not perfect and fashion the land we live on, have bequeathed to us the elements of that national character which has so powerfully influenced its destiny and our own. <gap reason="covered" atLeast="1" unit="chars"/>ude as may have been the forms of expression to which their literature was condemned to resort, it is yet undeserving of <gap reason="covered" atLeast="1" unit="chars"/>ter neglect:</hi> nor need it be apprehended that an intellectual communism with the mental efforts of yore would inspire fancies more extravagant than the day-dreams of that more material communism which is undermining the foundations of social order in Europe.</p>
                <byline>L.</byline>
                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
                <p>PART. IV.&#8212;1. <hi rend="italic">The Plant: a Biography. In a Series of Popular Lectures.</hi> By M. J. Schleiden, M.D., Professor of Botany to the University of Jena. Translated by Arthur Henfrey, F.L.S., &amp;c. London: Bailli&#232;re, Regent-street. 1848.</p>
                <p><gap reason="covered" atLeast="1" unit="chars"/>&#8212;<hi rend="italic">The Poetry of Science, or Studies of the Physical Phenomena of Nature.</hi> By Robert Hunt. London: Reeve, Benham &amp; Reeve, King William-street, Strand. 1848.</p>
                <p><gap reason="covered" atLeast="1" unit="chars"/>&#8212;<hi rend="italic">A Century of Orchidaceous Plants;</hi> with Descriptions by Sir W. J. Hooker: and <hi rend="italic">An Introduction on their Culture and Management</hi>, by J. C. Lyons, Esq. London: Reeve, Benham &amp; Reeve. 1849.</p>
                <p><gap reason="covered" atLeast="1" unit="chars"/>&#8212;<hi rend="italic">A Manual of British Marine Alg&#230;, with twenty-seven Plates of Genera.</hi> By W. H. Harvey, M.D., M.R.I.A., &amp;c. Second Edition; in the Press. London: John Van Voorst, Paternoster-row.</p>
                <p><gap reason="covered" atLeast="1" unit="chars"/>&#8212;<hi rend="italic">The Sea-side Book; being an Introduction to the Natural History of the British Coasts.</hi> By W. H. Harvey, M.D., &amp;c. London: Van Voorst. 1849.</p>
                <p><gap reason="covered" atLeast="1" unit="chars"/>&#8212;<hi rend="italic">Phycologia Britannica; or, History of British Sea-Weeds, containing Coloured Figures, Generic and Specific Characters, Synonymes and Descriptions of all the Species of Alg&#230; inhabiting the shores of</hi></p>
                <ab>VOL. LI. 13</ab><cb/>
                <p><hi rend="italic">the British Islands.</hi> Three Volumes. By W. H. Harvey, M.D., &amp;c. London: Reeve, Benham &amp; Reeve. 1849.</p>
                <p>7.&#8212;<hi rend="italic">The Rhododendrons of Sikkim-Himalaya.</hi> By Joseph Dalton Hooker, M.D., &amp;c. With Drawings and Descriptions made on the spot. Edited by Sir W. J. Hooker, K.H., &amp;c. Second Edition. London: Reeve, Benham &amp; Reeve. 1849.</p>
                <note type="authorial" place="right" resp="#h3">&#9758; Insects.</note>
                <p><span xml:id="s33" from="#s33" to="#s34" rend="wavyLine-right" hand="#h3"/>IN the 'Westminster Review' for October, 1848, (No. XCVIII., page 108), we adduced<note type="authorial" place="right" resp="#h3">&#9756;</note> a few of the more striking examples of insect economy, by way of illustrating the claims to attention possessed by the members<anchor xml:id="s34"/> of an exceedingly interesting portion of the kingdom of nature; in the present paper we hope to show that the vegetable world is in no respect inferior to the animal, in the amount of pleasure it is capable of yielding to the enlightened investigator of the curious phenomena connected with the increase, distribution, and general habits of the organisms of which it composed.</p>
                <p>In one respect, indeed, plants posses a decided advantage over insects. Most persons have certain insect antipathies which it is all but impossible to eradicate. We, ourselves, must confess to a slight&#8212;a very slight&#8212;dislike of spiders; and among "the green myriads of the peopled grass" there are a few, whether creeping or flying, which are not to many individuals the objects of an unconquerable aversion. With plants, however, the case is widely different; they are almost universal favourites. The lady who would shriek in unfeigned terror at the unexpected appearance of a spider or an earwig, is sure to have certain floral pets, which she will cherish and tend with the fondest solicitude; the keen man of business, perpetually oscillating between his country-house and his counting-house, with scarcely a thought for anything beyond stocks and per-centages, may be seen entering town in the morning, with a flower, culled perchance from his own well-stored conservatory, jauntily worn in his button-hole; while the more humble member of the trading community, whose possession of the luxury of a garden is forbidden by his position in life, is fain to be content with the purchase of a blossom from the basket of some itinerant flower-vendor. Moreover, the various devices resorted to by numerous dwellers in "the stifling bosom of the town," those who
                <lg>
                    <l>"Never pass their brick-wall bounds,</l>
                    <l>To range the fields, and treat their lungs with air,"</l> 
                </lg>
                </p>
            </div1>
            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="duk_ap_00125.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">192</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">Botany.</hi></fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top right">July,</fw>
                <p>in order that they may gratify what Cowper styles "the burning instinct," are only so many proofs that the love of flowers is an inherent feeling, equally gratified by the "creeping herbs," dragging on a bare existence in the crazy box, the fragmentary pitcher, or the spoutless tea-pot, which forms the window-garden of the humble votary of Flora, and by the "buds and blossoms of a thousand hues," collected from all climes, and growing in the protecting walls of the well-regulated conservatory appended to the aristocratic mansion.</p>
                <p>In his pleasant book 'The Town,' Leigh Hunt has an apposite passage, quite confirmatory of the above remarks, upon a Londoner's love of flowers. He says,</p>
                <p>"A tree, or even a flower, put in a window in the streets of a great city (and the London citizens, to their credit, are fond of flowers), affects the eye something in the same way as the hand-organs, which bring unexpected music to the ear. They refresh the common-places of life, shed a harmony through the busy discord, an appeal to those first sources of emotion, which are associated with the remembrance of all that is young and innocent. They seem also to present to us a portion of the tranquility we thing we are labouring for, and the desire of which is felt as an earnest that we all shall realize it somewhere, either in this world or in the next. Above all, they render us more cheerful for the performance of present duties; and the smallest seed of this kind, dropt into the heart of man, is worth more, and may terminate in better fruit, than anybody but a great poet could tell us."&#8212;<hi rend="italic">The Town</hi>, i. 28.</p>
                <p>Although, in regard to species and individuals, plants are outnumbered by insects, yet do they by no means yield the palm in regard to the number and variety of interesting particulars connected with their mode of life, their choice of locality, their power of adaptation to external circumstances. All these are overlooked by the  man of whom Wordsworth says,
                <lg>
                    <l>"The primrose by the river's brim,</l>
                    <l>A yellow primrose is to him,</l>
                    <l>And it is nothing more;"</l>
                </lg>
                but how much more than a yellow primrose is that fair herald of spring to the scientific botanist&#8212;to him who delights to trace the progress of each herb and flower, from the earliest indication of the action of the vital principle up to the full development of the vegetable form and structure, in all their beauty and perfection! Such a one will recognise in the "yellow primrose" a wonderful apparatus of cells, and fibres, and vessels, each occupying its appropriate position, each performing its appointed duty, and all<cb/> harmoniously contributing to the well-being of the individual plant, and the perpetuation of the species. And from the primrose, his mental vision will range through the wide circle of vegetable life&#8212;from the "green mantle on the standing pool," to the lofty denizens of the tropical forest&#8212;and will connect the lowly flower "upon the river's brim" with the almost infinitely varied forms and conditions of vegetation so eloquently described in the following extract from Lindley's great work, the 'Vegetable Kingdom:'&#8212;</p>
                <p>"Wherever the eye is directed, it encounters an infinite multitude of the most dissimilar forms of vegetation. Some are cast ashore by the ocean in the form of leathery straps or thongs, or are collected into pelagic meadows of vast extent; other crawl over mines, and illuminate them with phosphorescent gleams. Rivers and tranquil waters teem with green filaments; mud throws up its gelatinous scum; the human lungs, ulcers, and sordes of all sorts, bring forth a living brood; timber crumbles to dust beneath insidious spawn; corn-crops change to fetid soot; all matter in decay is seen to teem with mouldy life; and those filaments, that scum-bred spawn and mould, alike acknowledge a vegetable origin. The bark of ancient trees is carpeted with velvet, their branches are hung with a grey-beard tapestry, and microscopical scales overspread their leaves; the face of rocks is stained with ancient colours, coeval with their own exposure to air; and those, too, are citizens of the great world of plants. Heaths and moors wave with a tough and wiry herbage; meadows are clothed with an emerald mantle, amidst which spring flowers of all hues and forms; bushes throw abroad their many-fashioned foliage; twiners scramble over and choke them; above all wave the arms of the ancient forest, and these, too, acknowledge the sovereignty of Flora. Their individual forms, too, change at every step. With every altered condition and circumstance new plants start up. The mountain side has its own races of vegetable inhabitants, and the valleys have theirs; the tribes of the sand, the granite, and the limestone, are all different; and the sun does not shine upon two degrees on the surface of this globe, the vegetation of which is identical: for every latitude has a Flora of its own. In short, the forms of seas, lakes, and rivers, islands and peninsulas, hills, valleys, plains and mountains, are not so diversified as that of the vegetation which adorns them."&#8212;<hi rend="italic">Vegetable Kingdom</hi>, Introduction, p. xxi.</p>
                <p>It will readily be conceived that the constitutional peculiarities of plants must be infinitely varied in order that they may both exist and flourish under circumstances so opposed, and in localities so numerous as those described in the foregoing extract; and such, in fact, is the case. But the vegetable kingdom, in an equal degree with the other "works of an Almighty hand," affords unnumbered proofs that throughout</p>
            </div1>   
            <add rend="pasteon" source="#rd_487">
           <q who="unknown" type="written"/>
                <floatingText rend="flippy">
                    <body>
                        <pb xml:id="leaf007r" facs="duk.00025.011.jpg" type="recto"/>
                        <p>The difference between the <gap reason="torn away" atLeast="1" unit="chars"/>of Paris<gap reason="torn away" atLeast="1" unit="chars"/> the press of our own country is so radical, that a few words upon the subject will not be out of place. That a country like France, which, in many respects, and particularly as regards Art and Learning, stands to-day at the head of the world, should be so deficient in journalism, is a fact which, to me, seems inexplicable. In typographical execution and general appearance, the best of Paris newspapers is inferior to the meanest New York journal. Indeed, I question whether the denizens of a American country village would not feel ashamed to own such poor affairs. The manner in which they are conducted is not much better. It is true that many men of high literary and political ability are attached in an editorial capacity to the various journals; but still their columns contain nothing but stupid puerilities about the war, a few ill written local items, a chapter or two of an insipid novel, (the nastier the better,) a long winded theatrical criticism and two or three telegraphic despatches of five or six lines each. Of editorial spirit and vigor they are, one and all, entirely destitute. Under the chains of a despotism which can, with a breath, destroy them, it is quite natural that they should be fawning, cringing set they are, but even a rigorous censorship does not <gap reason="torn away" atLeast="1" unit="chars"/>reclude a manly discussion of non-political topics. It is, however, vain to look for anything beyond the most ordinary commonplaces, in the editorial columns of the <hi rend="italic">Moniteur</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Constitutionnel</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Press Patrie</hi>, &amp;c. There is a total lack of enterprise and want of business tact observable in them all. Their telegraphic despatches, as I have said, do not amount to more than a "stick full," daily, and, indeed, I have known important intelligence, sent by telegraphic to private individuals and by them offered for publication to the newspapers, to be <hi rend="italic">refused admission</hi>, unless paid for at the rate of three francs per line. I am afraid the newspapers of Paris are rather behind the age.</p>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </add>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>