<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen
RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"
?>
<?oxygen
SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"
?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.07368">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Consuelo, vol. 1</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
                <author xml:id="cv">George Sand</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ano">Alejandro Omidsalar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mc">Matt Cohen</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>University of Texas at Austin</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>2015</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.07368</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>kprice@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Ed-Folsom@uiowa.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>bbarney2@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain exceptions, public domain works may be 
                        freely copied or used in the creation of derivative works without permission, or authorization, of the former copyright owners.</p>
                    <p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and is governed by a
                        <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                            Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License
                        </ref>
                        (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                    <p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted 
                        by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Consuelo</title>
                    <idno type="callno">PQ2400.A37 1848</idno>
                    <date notBefore="1847-01-01" notAfter="1892-03-26">1847 or later</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="bmr">Feinberg-Whitman Collection, Library of Congress</orgName>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from digital images of the original item.</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl type="base" xml:id="r1">
                    <author>George Sand</author>
                    <title level="a">Consuelo</title>
                    <date>1847</date>
                    <publisher>William H. Graham</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                    <biblScope type="pp">title page, vi, vii, 11, 13, 19-22, 24, 27, 34, 35, 50-53</biblScope>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="h1" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h2" scribeRef="#gs" medium="typescript"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h3" scribeRef="#ww" medium="ink"/>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2015-11-27" who="#ano">Transcribed; encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<text type="marginalia">
    <front>
        <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_mc_02592.jpg" type="recto"/>
        <titlePage>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h3">Walt Whitman</note>
            <docTitle>
                <titlePart>CONSUELO:</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline>BY<docAuthor>GEORGE SAND.</docAuthor></byline>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h2">IN THREE VOLUMES:
            VOL. 1</note>
            <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short"/>
            <byline>TRANSLATED BY 
            FRANCIS G. SHAW.</byline>
            <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short"/>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h2">Third Edition.</note>
            <docImprint>
                <pubPlace>NEW YORK:</pubPlace>
                <publisher>WILLIAM <gap reason="unspecified damage"/> GRAHAM, TRIBUNE BUILDINGS</publisher>
                <docDate>M DCCC XLVII</docDate>.
            </docImprint>
        </titlePage>
    </front>
    <body>
        <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_mc_00951.jpg" type="verso"/>
        <p>Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year 1846, by
        FRANCIS G. SHAW,
        the Clerk's Office of the District Court of Massachusetts.</p>
        <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short"/>
        <p>Stereotyped by
        GEORGE A. CURTIS;
        <hi rend="smallcaps">NEW ENGLAND TYPE AND STEREOTYPE FOUNDRY></hi></p>
        <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc_mc_02594.jpg" type="verso"/>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">vi</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top">CONSUELO.</fw>
        <p>book, out of any weak disgust for the experiences through which the 
            author may have had to work her way up to this serene and heavenly 
            <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="a1" from="a1" to="a2"/>
            elevation? Whoever does so is himself the loser. It is the way of 
            Providence, that loftiest character is reared not in the timid paths of 
            outward innocence alone; and that purest wisdom sometimes comes 
            from knowledge of both good and evil, that so it may speak the more 
            wisely, convincingly, inspiringly, to them that are fallen.<anchor xml:id="a2"/></p>
        <p>We shall take occasion hereafter to speak more at length of the 
            book and its author. At present we can only sum up its merits. 
            "Consuelo" is its name, and the name of the heroine&#8212;a Spanish 
            word, which means <hi rend="italic">Consolation</hi>. No word could better describe the 
            peculiar influence of the book. It is consoling to the depths of every 
            tried and weary soul. As surely as you read, you are in a clearer 
            and more loving mood. Every sentence seems to have proceeded 
            from a very rare union of Wisdom and Love; such serenity and such 
            mild warmth are from no other source. It throws around you the 
            sphere of an ideal person, a character so truly conceived, and so 
            thoroughly sustained, that almost you are persuaded it has bodily 
            existence, and that a " Consuelo" lives for <hi rend="italic">you</hi> too.</p>
        <p>Consuelo is a poor Spanish Gipsy girl; at first a gifted pupil in 
            one of the musical conservatories of Venice under old Porpora, the 
            master of Haydn; then the wonder of all Italy, of the courts of 
            Maria-Theresa, and of Frederic-the-Great, by her inspired singing 
            in theatre and church; then a countess; and always, from first to 
            last, sublime as an artist, a woman, and a child of God. In no work 
            of fiction do we find so high a character. It is gentleness grown 
            strong by purity; it is beauty perpetually renewed from the inward 
            living springs of beauty; it is genius sanctified by piety and justified 
            by use; it is the very height of liberty and frankness, yet its freest 
            motions rounded with the grace of reverence; it is innocence great 
            through all experiences, too great for vanity or fear, and humble in 
            its greatness; it is high, heavenly womanhood, a female incarnation 
            <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="b1" from="b1" to="b2"/>
            of the Godlike. Notable personages of history, monarchs, states-
            men, artists, philosophers, poets, spiritual mystics, coarser fanatics 
            and charlatans, shine in their truest colors in this book, <hi rend="underline">as they only<anchor xml:id="b2"/> 
            could do by the side of her.</hi></p>
        <p>Consuelo is an artist, a wondrous child of song; as loyal to nature, 
            as she is conscientious in art. In her inspirations, in her studies, in 
            her public performances, she is the ideal of that character. To her, 
            Music is the medium through which the soul may with all delicacy, 
            publish to the world its deepest, inmost life. To glorify music, to 
            proclaim its heavenly origin and power, its mystic sense, is her reli-</p>
        <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="loc_mc_02595.jpg" type="recto"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top">CONSUELO.</fw>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">vii</fw>
        <p>gious mission. mission. In it all thought of self is lost. Music is the meaning 
            of her life; music is the outpouring of all her soul to humanity, 
            her highest duty, her confession of faith, her acknowledgment of 
            God, her dedication of herself to holiest ends. Here again, amid so 
            many vain displays of heartless skill, the forms of art without the 
            soul, in operas and concerts and cathedral choirs, she is " Consuelo," 
            Consolation&#8212;a refreshing sunbeam of reality amid cold glittering 
            shams. It is perhaps the primary end of this novel, to hold up an 
            ideal of the artist's character, especially in music, which is <hi rend="italic">the</hi> art 
            of this age; and to show how genuine Art flows only from, and 
            leads always to, the moral; how all inspiration, alike of saint or 
            artist, must come from devotion to the "<hi rend="underline">first good, first fair.</hi>"</p>
        <p>It is because the author not only has an intellectual apprehension 
            of this idea, but actually feels and lives it, that her book itself is a 
            noble work of Art. The character of Consuelo inspires it all. Like 
            the "Voice, which first to light gave being," she pervades with a 
            quickening presence, shaping and harmonizing the whole book, 
            through all its more general arrangements, through all its shifting 
            scenes and interacting characters, down to the very choice of words, 
            and slightest turn of every sentence. The style, for graphic clearness, 
            warmth, and musical flow, is almost unrivalled.</p>
        <p>To expect all this in any English version would be too much. 
            But our translation is by one eminently qualified for the work, who 
            is both filled with enthusiasm for the beauty of the original, and who 
            deeply appreciates its spirit and purpose. The work with him is 
            truly one of love. We can with all confidence offer it to our readers 
            as a faithful, spirited and graceful version of a book, which needs 
            no other commendation but to be read.</p>
        <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc_mc_02596.jpg" type="recto"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top">CONSUELO.</fw>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">11</fw>
        <p>inevitable, had sometimes admitted to the course of musical 
            lessons, the children of poor artists, whose wandering life did 
            not permit a long residence at Venice. Of this class was the 
            little Consuelo, born in Spain, and arriving thence in Italy, by 
            the way of St. Petersburg, Constantinople, Mexico, or Archangel, 
            or by some other route even more direct, travelled by 
            the Bohemians alone.</p>
        <p>Bohemian, however, she was not, except by profession and 
            figure of speech; for by race she was neither Gypsy nor 
            Indian, nor Israelitish even, in any manner. She was of good 
            Spanish blood, no doubt Moorish in its origin, for she was 
            tolerably brown, and her whole person had a tranquillity which 
            announced nothing of the wandering races. Not that I wish 
            to speak ill of those races. If I had created the character of 
            Consuelo, I do not assert that I should not have made her 
            descend from Israel, or even from a more ancient race; but she 
            was formed from the rib of Ishmael, everything in her organization 
            declared it. I never saw her, for I am not yet a hundred 
            years old, but I have been told this, and cannot contradict it. 
            She had not the feverish petulance, interrupted by fits of a 
            pathetic languor, which distinguishes the <hi rend="italic">Zingarelle</hi>. She had 
            not the insinuating curiosity, and the obstinate mendicity of an 
            <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="c1" from="c1" to="c2"/>
            indigent <hi rend="italic">Ebbrea</hi>. She was as calm as the water of the lagunes, 
            and at the same time as active as the light gondolas which 
            incessantly furrow its surface.<anchor xml:id="c2"/></p>
        <p>As she grew very fast, and her mother was very poor, her 
            clothes were always too short by a year, which gave to her 
            long legs of fourteen, accustomed to show themselves in public, 
            a sort of savage grace and springing gait, the sight of which 
            caused both pleasure and pity. If her foot was small, she was 
            so badly shod that you could not be sure of it. On the other 
            hand, her figure, confined in a waist which had become too 
            small, and was bursting at every seam, was light and flexible 
            as a palm tree, but without form, without roundness, and 
            without any attractiveness. The poor girl thought nothing 
            of this, accustomed as she was to be called ape, monkey, and 
            gypsy, by the blonde, white and plump girls of the Adriatic.</p>
        <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="loc_mc_02597.jpg" type="recto"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top">CONSUELO.</fw>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">13</fw>
        <p>me, my dear master," cried he, " which of your pupils has 
            just sung the <hi rend="italic">Salve Regina</hi>?"</p>
        <p>"Why do you wish to know, count Zustiniani!" answered 
            the professor, leaving the church with him.</p>
        <p>"In order to compliment you," replied the patrician. "For 
            a long time I have attended, not only your vespers, but even 
            your lessons; for you know how much I am <hi rend="italic">dilettante</hi> of 
            sacred music. Well, this is the first time that I have heard 
            Pergolese's music sung in so perfect a manner; as regards 
            the voice, it is certainly the most beautiful I have ever met 
            with in my life."</p>
        <p>"By the Christ! I believe you!" returned the professor, 
            relishing a huge pinch of snuff with complaisance and dignity.</p>
        <p>"Then tell me the name of the celestial creature who has 
            thrown me into such ecstasies. Notwithstanding your 
            severities and your continual complaints, it may be said that 
            you have made your school one of the best in all Italy; your 
            choruses are excellent, and your solos very commendable; 
            but the music which you oblige them to execute is so grand, 
            so austere, that young girls can rarely cause all its beauties 
            to be felt&#8212;"</p>
        <p><span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="d1" from="d1" to="d2"/>
            "They do not cause them to be felt," said the professor 
            with sadness, "because they themselves never feel them!<anchor xml:id="d2"/>
            For fine, fresh and powerful voices and of«great compass, we 
            do not want, thank God! but for truly musical organizations, 
            alas! how rare and incomplete they are."</p>
        <p>"At least you have one that is admirably endowed; the 
            instrument is magnificent, the sentiment perfect, the knowledge 
            remarkable. Tell me her name."</p>
        <p>"It is true, then," said the professor, eluding the question, 
            "that she gave you pleasure?"</p>
        <p>"She seized me by the heart, she drew tears from my 
            eyes, and by means so simple, by effects so little labored, that 
            at first I could not understand how it was done. Then I 
            called to mind what you had so often told me, in teaching me 
            your divine art, my dear master; and for the first time I felt 
            how right you were<anchor xml:id="e1"/>.</p>
        <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="infralinear" target="e1">2</note> 
        <!-- Not sure why there is a 2 hovering beneath "were" on the last line, so I coded it as a note. -->
        <pb xml:id="leaf007v" facs="loc_mc_00952.jpg" type="verso"/>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">14</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top">CONSUELO.</fw>
        <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="f1" from="f1" to="f2"/>
        <p>"And what did I tell you?" asked the master again, with an air of triumph.</p>
        <p>"You used to tell me," answered the count, "that <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">the 
            grand, the true, the beautiful in art, was the simple."</hi></p><anchor xml:id="f2"/>
        <p>"I also told you that there was the brilliant, the difficult, 
            the skilful, and that there was often reason for remarking and 
            praising these qualities. Did I not?"</p>
        <p>"Without doubt; but between these secondary qualities 
            and the true manifestation of genius, there is an abyss, said 
            you. Well, my dear master! your songstress is alone on 
            one side, and all the rest are on the other."</p>
        <p>"It is true, and it is well said," observed the professor, 
            rubbing his hands.</p>
        <p>"Her name?" insisted the count.</p>
        <p>"What name?" asked the roguish professor.</p>
        <p>"Oh! <hi rend="italic">per Dio santo!</hi> that of the siren, or rather of the
        archangel whom I have just heard &#8212;"</p>
        <p>"And what do you wish to do with her name, my lord
        count?" replied Porpora, in a severe tone.</p>
        <p>"Sir professor, why do you wish to keep it a secret from
        me?"</p>
        <p>"I will tell you why, if you will first tell me, why you ask
        it with so much earnestness."</p>
        <p>"Is not the desire to know, to name, and to see the objects
        of our admiration, a natural and truly irresistible sentiment?"</p>
        <p>"Yes! But that is not your only motive! allow me, my 
            dear count, to contradict you. You are a great amateur and 
            good connoisseur in music, I know; but you are above all, 
            proprietor of the Saint Samuel theatre. You make it your 
            glory, even more than your interest, to draw thither the finest 
            talents and the most beautiful voices of all Italy. You know 
            that we give good lessons; that in our school alone are 
            severe studies prosecuted and great musicians formed. You 
            have already carried Corilla away from us; and as she will 
            probably be taken from you, at the first opportunity, by an 
            engagement with some other theatre, you come prowling 
            about our school, to'see if we have not formed some other</p>
        <pb xml:id="leaf008r" facs="loc_mc_02598.jpg" type="recto"/>
        <fw type="header" place="top">CONSUELO.</fw>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">19</fw>
        <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="g1" from="g1" to="g2"/>
        <p>"She, that dirty child? that lean black grasshopper? im-
            possible, maestro!"</p><anchor xml:id="g2"/>
        <p>"She herself, my lord count; would not she make a most 
            attractive prima donna?"</p>
        <p>The count stopped, returned, examined Consuelo again 
            from a little distance, then clasping his hands with a despair 
            that was truly comic;&#8212;</p>
        <p>"Just Heavens !" cried he, " how can you make such 
            mistakes, and pour the fire of genius into heads so roughly 
            wrought?"</p>
        <p>"Then you renounce your wicked project?" said the professor.</p>
        <p>"Certainly."</p>
        <p>"Do you promise me?" added Porpora.</p>
        <p>"Oh! I swear it to you," answered the count.</p>
        <pb xml:id="leaf008v" facs="loc_mc_02599.jpg" type="verso"/>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top">20</fw>
        <div1 type="chapter">
            <head>CHAPTER III</head>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Born</hi> under the sky of Italy, reared by chance like a bird 
                of the sea-shore, poor, orphan, abandoned, and yet happy in 
                the present, and sanguine for the future, like a love-child, 
                which he doubtless was; Anzoleto, that handsome boy of 
                nineteen, who passed all his days with the little Consuelo, in 
                the most complete liberty, upon the flag-stones of Venice, had 
                long since had, as may well be imagined, his first experiences 
                of love. Initiated into the easy pleasures, which had more 
                than once presented themselves to him, he would already 
                have been worn out and perhaps corrupted, had he lived in 
                our sombre climate, and if nature had endowed him with a 
                less rich organization. But, developed early in life, and 
                destined to a long and powerful manhood, he still had his 
                heart pure, and his senses restrained by the will. By chance 
                he had met with the little Spanish girl before the Madonettes, 
                singing canticles from pure devotion; and he, for the pleasure 
                of exercising his voice, had sung with her to the stars during 
                whole evenings. And then they had met upon the sands of 
                Lido, gathering shell-fish, he, for the purpose of eating, she, to 
                make chaplets and ornaments. And still again they had met 
                in the church, she praying to the good God with all her heart, 
                he looking at the beautiful ladies with all his eyes. And in 
                all these meetings, Consuelo had seemed to him so good, so 
                sweet, so obliging, so gay, that he had made himself her 
                friend, her inseparable companion, without knowing why or 
                wherefore. Anzoleto, as yet, knew nothing of love in its 
                higher forms. He felt friendship for Consuelo; and as he 
                <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="i1" from="i1" to="i2"/>
                was of a country and people where the passions rule more 
                than the attachments, he knew not how to give to this friend-<anchor xml:id="i2"/>
                ship any other name than that of love. Consuelo accepted 
                this manner of speaking, after she had made to Anzoleto the</p>
        <pb xml:id="leaf009r" facs="loc_mc_02600.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <fw type="header" place="top">CONSUELO.</fw>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">21</fw>
            <p>following observation: "If you call yourself my lover, it is 
                because you wish to marry me!" he had answered, " Most 
                certainly, if you are willing, we will be married together." 
                And thenceforth it was an understood thing. Perhaps Anzoleto 
                thought it a good joke, while Consuelo believed in it with 
                the best faith in the world. But it is certain that his young 
                heart already experienced those contradictory sentiments and 
                complicated emotions, which agitate and disjoin the existence 
                of men worn by dissipation.</p>
            <p>Abandoned to violent instincts, greedy of pleasures, loving 
                only that which conduced to his happiness, hating and flying 
                all that opposed his enjoyments, artist even to the bones, that 
                is, seeking and feeling life with a frightful intensity, he found 
                that his mistresses imposed upon him the sufferings and dangers 
                of passions which he himself did not feel profoundly. Still 
                he saw them from time to time, recalled as he was by his 
                desires, but soon repelled by satiety or disgust. And when 
                this strange child had thus expended without imagination and 
                without dignity the superabundance of his life, he felt the 
                necessity of a sweet society, and of a chaste and serene 
                expansion. He might already have said with Jean Jacques: 
                <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="j1" from="j1" to="j2"/>
                "So true it is that what attaches us most to women is less 
                libertinism than a certain delight in living near them." Then,<anchor xml:id="j2"/>
                without understanding the charm which attracted him towards 
                Consuelo, not having as yet even the sense of the beautiful, 
                and not knowing whether she was ugly or pretty; child himself 
                enough to be amused with her by plays beneath his age; 
                man enough, scrupulously to respect her fourteen years; he 
                led with her in public, upon the marbles, the tiles, and the 
                waves of Venice, a life as happy, as pure, as secret and 
                almost as poetic, as that of Paul and Virginia under the moss-
                covered trees of the desert. Though they had a liberty the 
                most absolute and the most dangerous, no family, no vigilant 
                and tender mothers to form them to virtue, no devoted servant 
                to search after them in the evening, and conduct them to the 
                fold, not even a dog to warn them of danger, they met with 
                no sort of accident. They sailed over the lagunes in an open</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf009v" facs="loc_mc_02601.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">22</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top">CONSUELO.</fw>
            <p>boat, at all hours and in all weathers, without oars and 
                without a pilot; they wandered over the marshes, without guide, 
                without compass, and without care of the rising tide; they 
                sang before the chapels raised under a vine at the corner of 
                the streets, without thinking of the late hour, and without 
                needing any bed till morning, other than the white flag-stone 
                still warm with the heat of the day. They stopped before the 
                theatre of Pulcinella, and followed with a passionate attention 
                the fantastic drama of the beautiful Corisanda, queen of 
                the Marionettes, without remembering the absence of breakfast, 
                and the little probability of supper. They gave themselves 
                up to the unbridled amusements of the carnival; having 
                for all disguise and all ornament, he, his vest turned inside 
                out, and she, a great bow of old ribbons above her ear. They 
                made sumptuous repasts upon the balustrade of a bridge, or 
                the steps of a palace, with fruits of the sea,&#42;<anchor xml:id="k1"/> leaves of raw
                <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="l1" from="l1" to="l2"/>
                fennel, or rinds of citron. In fine, they led a joyous and free 
                life, without more perilous caresses or amorous sentiments, 
                than would have been exchanged by two virtuous children of 
                one age and one sex. Days, years, passed by; Anzoleto had<anchor xml:id="l2"/> 
                other mistresses; Consuelo did not even know that there 
                could be another love than that of which she was the object. 
                She became a young woman without feeling herself obliged 
                to more reserve with her betrothed; and he saw her grow 
                and change, without experiencing any impatience, and without 
                desiring any alteration in this intimacy, without cloud, 
                without scruple, without mystery, and without remorse.</p>
            <p>Four years had already passed since professor Porpora 
                and count Zustiniani had presented to each other their <hi rend="italic">little 
                musicians</hi>, and since that time, the count had thought no 
                more of the young singer of sacred music; since that time 
                also the professor had equally forgotten the handsome Anzoleto, 
                inasmuch as he did not find him, after a first examination, 
                endowed with any of the qualities which he required in 
                a pupil; primarily, a nature of serious and patient intelligence,</p>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="bottom" target="k1">&#42; Divers kinds of shell-fish, very large and very cheap, of which the
            people of Venice are quite fond.</note>
            <pb xml:id="leaf010v" facs="loc_mc_02602.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">24</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top">CONSUELO.</fw>
            <p>It need not be asked if Anzoleto was affected internally; at 
                any rate it appeared but little; and hardly had his piercing eyes, 
                stealthily interrogating those of the ladies, divined that secret 
                approbation which is rarely refused to so handsome a young 
                man; hardly had the amateurs, surprised at such power of 
                tone, and such a facility of vocalization, caused favorable 
                murmurs to be heard around them, than joy and hope inundated 
                his whole being. Then also, for the first time in his life, 
                Anzoleto, until then vulgarly comprehended and vulgarly 
                taught, felt that he was not a vulgar man; transported by the 
                necessity and the feeling of triumph, he sang with an energy, 
                an originality, and a rapture which were remarkable. It is 
                true, his taste was not always pure, nor his execution faultless, 
                in all parts of the piece; but he always knew how to recover 
                himself by strokes of boldness, by flashes of intelligence, and 
                transports of enthusiasm. He missed the effects which the 
                composer had arranged, but he found others of which no one 
                had thought, neither the author who traced them, nor the 
                professor who interpreted them, nor any of the <hi rend="italic">virtuosi</hi> who 
                had rendered them. This boldness seized and carried with 
                him all the world. For one innovation they pardoned him 
                ten mistakes; for one individual sentiment, ten rebellions
                <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="m1" from="m1" to="m2"/>
                against method. So true is it, that in art, the least flash of 
                genius, the least soaring towards new conquests, exercises 
                more fascination upon men than all the resources and all the 
                lights of science within the limits of the known.<anchor xml:id="m2"/></p>
            <p>No one perhaps understood the causes, and no one escaped 
                the effects of this enthusiasm. Corilla had opened the meeting 
                by a grand air, finely sung and vigorously applauded; but the 
                success of the young debutant so completely effaced hers, 
                that she felt a movement of rage. But at the moment when 
                Anzoleto, covered with praises and caresses, returned to the 
                harpsichord where she was seated, he said, bending towards 
                her with a compound of submission and audacity: "And you, 
                queen of song, queen of beauty, have you not one look of 
                encouragement for the poor unfortunate, who fears and adores 
                you?"</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf011r" facs="loc_mc_02603.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <fw type="header" place="top">CONSUELO.</fw>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">27</fw>
            <p>between us? I know you not. Carry elsewhere your beautiful 
                smiles and your perfidious warblings."</p>
            <p>"See, he softens," said Corilla, seizing with one hand the 
                arm of the debutant, while the other continued toying with 
                the ample white cravat of the professor.&#8212;" Come here, <hi rend="italic">Zoto</hi>,&#42;<anchor xml:id="n1"/> 
                and bend your knee before the most learned professor of vocal 
                music in all Italy. Humble yourself, my child, and disarm
                <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="o1" from="o1" to="o2"/>
                his severity. One word from him, if you can obtain it, should 
                be more precious to you than all the trumpets of fame."<anchor xml:id="o2"/></p>
            <p>"You have been very severe with me, signor professor," 
                said Anzoleto, bending before him with a modesty that had 
                somewhat of mockery; "nevertheless my only desire for 
                four years has been to induce you to revoke so cruel a judgment; 
                and if I have not succeeded this evening, I doubt if I 
                shall have courage to re&#228;ppear before the public, bowed down 
                as I am with the weight of your anathema."</p>
            <p>"Boy," said the professor, rising with a vivacity and speaking 
                with a conviction which made him noble and grand, 
                instead of crooked and mean, as he ordinarily seemed, "leave 
                to the women honeyed and deceitful words. Never debase 
                yourself to the language of flattery, even before your superior, 
                much less before one whose judgment you inwardly disdain. 
                But an hour since, you were there in that corner, poor, 
                unknown, fearful; your whole future lot depended on a hair, 
                upon a sound of your throat, upon an instant of failure in your 
                powers, upon a caprice of your audience. One lucky chance, 
                one effort, one instant, has made you rich, celebrated, 
                insolent. The career is opened; you have only to pursue it so far 
                <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="p1" from="p1" to="p2"/>
                as your strength will support you. Listen then, for the first 
                time, and for the last perhaps, you are about to hear the truth.<anchor xml:id="p2"/>
                You are in a bad way, you sing badly, and you love bad 
                music. You know nothing, you have studied nothing 
                fundamentally. You have only practice and facility: you excite 
                yourself at will: you know how to coo and to warble, as do 
                those genteel and coquettish young ladies whom we pardon</p>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="bottom" target="m1">&#42; Contraction of <hi rend="italic">Anzoleto</hi>, which is the diminutive of <hi rend="italic">Angelo</hi>&#8212;<hi rend="italic">Anzolo</hi> in
            dialect.</note>
            <pb xml:id="leaf012v" facs="loc_mc_02604.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">34</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top">CONSUELO.</fw>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Corilla</hi>. And if I did love you.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Anz</hi>. I should despair entirely, because I must fall from 
                heaven into an abyss, and lose you, perhaps an hour after 
                having won you at the expense of all my future happiness.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Cor</hi>. And what makes you believe in such inconstancy on 
                my part?</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Anz</hi>. First my little merit, then all the ill that is spoken
            of you.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Cor</hi>. And who speaks ill of me?</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Anz</hi>. All the men, for all the men adore you.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Cor</hi>. And if I were fool enough to have an affection for
            you and to tell you so, you would repel me?&#8212;</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Anz</hi>. I don't know if I should have strength enough to
            fly; if I had, it is certain I would not see you again in all
            my life.</p>
            <p>"Well, said Corilla, "I wish to make the experiment 
            through curiosity. Anzoleto, I believe that I love you."</p>
            <p>"And I do not believe anything of it," answered he. "If 
                I remain, it is because I understand very well that you are 
                joking. At that play you cannot frighten me, and will 
                encourage me still less."</p>
            <p>"You wisk to make a trial of finesse, as I think."</p>
            <p>"Why not? I am not very formidable, as I give you the
            means of conquering me."</p>
            <p>"How so?"</p>
            <p>"That of chilling me with fear, and putting me to flight,
            by saying seriously what you just now said in jest."</p>
            <p>"You are a queer fellow! and I see that I must be very 
                cautious with you. You are one of those men who are not 
                satisfied with inhaling the perfume of a rose, but wish to 
                gather it and put it under glass. I should not have thought 
                you so bold or so free at your age."</p>
            <p>"And you despise me for that?"</p>
            <p>"On the contrary you please me even more. Good night,
            Anzoleto, we shall meet again."</p>
            <p>She held out her beautiful hand, which he kissed with</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf013r" facs="loc_mc_02605.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <fw type="header" place="top">CONSUELO.</fw>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">35</fw>
            <span rend="singleBracket-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="q1" from="q1" to="q2"/>
            <p>passion. "I have freed myself from that scrape, not so
            badly," thought he, as he ran along under the galleries<anchor xml:id="q2"/>
            which bordered the canaleto.</p>
            <p>As he despaired of having opened for him at this unseasonable 
                hour the poor lodging to which he usually retired, he 
                thought of stretching himself out on the first door step, to 
                enjoy that angelic repose which childhood and poverty alone 
                can know. But, for the first time in his life, he found no 
                flag-stone clean enough to lie down upon. Although the 
                pavement of Venice is cleaner and whiter than that of any 
                other place in the world, this bed, slightly dusty, was far 
                from agreeing with a complete black suit of the finest cloth 
                and the most elegant cut. And besides the propriety! The 
                same boatmen who in the morning carefully traversed the 
                steps of the landing place without touching the rags of the 
                young plebeian, would now insult his sleep, and perhaps 
                intentionally dirty the livery of his parasitical luxury, spread 
                out under their feet. What would they think of a sleeper in 
                the open air, in silk stockings, in fine linen, in wristbands 
                and neckbands of lace? At that moment Anzoleto regretted 
                <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="s1" from="s1" to="s2"/>
                his good cloak of brown and red woollen, well faded, well 
                worn, but still two inches thick, and proof against the 
                unhealthy fog which rises in the morning on the waters of<anchor xml:id="s2"/> 
                Venice. It was about the last of February; and though at 
                that season the sun is quite brilliant and warm in those 
                climates, the nights are still very cold. Then he thought 
                of going into some of the gondolas fastened to the bank, but 
                they were all locked up. At last he found one, the door of 
                which yielded before him; but on entering he struck against 
                the legs of the barcarole who had retired there to sleep, and 
                fell upon him. "By the devil's body," cried out a great 
                rough voice from the bottom of that cavern, " who are you, 
                and what do you want?"</p>
            <p>"Is that you, Zanetto?" answered Anzoleto, recognizing 
                the voice of the gondolier, who was usually quite kind to 
                him. "Let me lie down at your side, and get a nap under 
                cover of your cabanette."</p></div1>
            <pb xml:id="leaf014v" facs="loc_mc_02606.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top">50</fw>
            <div1 type="chapter">
                <head>CHAPTER VII.</head>
                <p>I<hi rend="smallcaps">t</hi> will appear to you very strange, but it is nevertheless 
                    very true, dear reader, that Anzoleto should never have had 
                    an opinion respecting the beauty or the ugliness of Consuelo. 
                    Consuelo lived so isolated, so unknown a life in Venice, that
                    no one had ever thought to ascertain, if, through this veil of 
                    forgetfulness and obscurity, intelligence and goodness had at 
                    length manifested themselves under an agreeable form, or 
                    under an insignificant one.</p>
                <p>Porpora, who had no sense remaining except for art, saw 
                    in her only the artist. Her neighbors in the <hi rend="italic">Corte Minelli</hi> 
                    saw her innocent love with Anzoleto without being scandalized.
                    <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="t1" from="t1" to="t2"/>
                    People are not ferocious on this point at Venice.<anchor xml:id="t2"/> <!-- This looks like a pencil mark to me, but I'll leave it up to your judgment. -->
                    They had sometimes prophesied to her that she would be 
                    unhappy with that boy, who had no position nor means of 
                    livelihood, and had advised her rather to seek an establishment 
                    with some honest and peaceable mechanic. But as 
                    she had always answered, that being without family or position 
                    herself, Anzoleto was perfectly fitted for her, and as for 
                    six years not a day had passed without their being seen 
                    together, never seeking for mystery and never quarreling, 
                    the neighbors had become accustomed to their free and 
                    indissoluble union. No one had ever thought of paying 
                    court to the <hi rend="italic">amica</hi> of Anzoleto. Was it solely on account 
                    of the engagement which they supposed she had formed, 
                    or was it on account of her wretchedness? or was it rather 
                    because her person had never exercised any attraction upon 
                    them? The last hypothesis is very probable.</p>
                <p>Still every one knows, that from twelve to fourteen, young 
                    girls are generally meagre, abashed, without harmony in 
                    their features, in their proportions, in their movements. 
                    Towards fifteen, they are <hi rend="italic">made over</hi>, to use a vulgar expres-</p>
                <pb xml:id="leaf015r" facs="loc_mc_02607.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top">CONSUELO.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">51</fw>
                <p>sion of the matrons; and she who just before seemed frightful, 
                    reappears, after this short labor of transformation, if not 
                    <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="u1" from="u1" to="u2"/>
                    handsome, at least agreeable. It has also been remarked, 
                    <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="v1" from="v1" to="v2"/>
                    that it is not advantageous for the future beauty of a little 
                    girl to be pretty too early. Consuelo having received like <anchor xml:id="u2"/><anchor xml:id="v2"/>
                    others the benefit of adolescence, people had ceased to say 
                    that she was ugly, and the fact is that she was no longer so. 
                    Only as she was neither dauphine nor infanta, she had no 
                    courtiers about her to proclaim that the royal offspring grew 
                    handsome day by day; and as she had not the support of 
                    tender friends, anxious for her future lot, no one took the 
                    trouble of saying to Anzoleto, "Your betrothed will not 
                    make you blush before the world." Anzoleto had heard her 
                    called ugly at an age when this reproach had to him neither 
                    meaning nor importance; and ever since people no longer 
                    said anything either good or bad about Consuelo's face, he 
                    had forgotten to think of it. His vanity had taken another 
                    flight. His dreams were of the theatre and of celebrity, 
                    he had no time to make a display of his conquests, and 
                    besides, the grosser part of curiosity which enters into the 
                    desires of youth was satisfied with him. I have said that at 
                    eighteen he had nothing more to learn. At twenty-two, he 
                    was almost blas&#233;; and at twenty-two as at eighteen, his 
                    attachment for Consuelo was as tranquil, spite of some 
                    chaste kisses, taken without trouble and given without 
                    shame, as it had been till then.</p>
                <p>In order not to be too much astonished at this calmness 
                    and this virtue on the part of a young man who certainly did 
                    not pretend to those qualities elsewhere, it must be observed 
                    that the great liberty in which our adolescents lived at the 
                    commencement of this history, had been modified, and little 
                    by little restrained with time. Consuelo was nearly sixteen, 
                    and still led a somewhat vagabond life, leaving the conservatory 
                    all alone, to repeat her lesson and eat her rice with 
                    Anzoleto, on the steps of the Piazetta, when her mother, 
                    worn out with fatigue, ceased to sing in the evening at the 
                    door of the caf&#233;s, with a guitar in her hand and a wooden</p>
                <pb xml:id="leaf016v" facs="loc_mc_02608.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">52</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top">CONSUELO.</fw>
                <p>bowl before her. The poor creature retired into one of the 
                    most miserable lofts of the <hi rend="italic">Corte Minelli</hi>, there tediously to 
                    end her wretched life upon a truckle bed. Then the good 
                    Consuelo, not wishing to leave her, changed entirely her
                    <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="w1" from="w1" to="w2"/>
                    manner of living. Except the hours in which the professor 
                    deigned to give her a lesson, she worked either with her 
                    needle or at counterpoint, always near the bed of that impe-
                    rious and despairing mother, who had cruelly maltreated her 
                    in childhood, and now presented to her the frightful spectacle 
                    of a death-bed without courage and without virtue.<anchor xml:id="w2"/></p>
                <p>Consuelo's filial piety and tranquil devotion were never 
                    inconsistent for a single moment. Joys of youth, liberty, 
                    wandering life, even love, all were sacrificed without regret
                    and without hesitation. Anzoleto complained bitterly, and 
                    seeing that his reproaches were useless, resolved to forget 
                    her, and divert himself; but this was impossible. Anzoleto 
                    was not so assiduous at labor as Consuelo; he took quickly 
                    and badly the bad lessons which his professor, to earn the 
                    salary promised by Zustiniani, gave him as badly and as 
                    quickly. This was very lucky for Anzoleto, in whom the 
                    prodigality of nature repaired as well as possible the lost 
                    time and the effects of bad teaching; but there resulted 
                    many hours of idleness, in which the friendly, cheerful 
                    society of Consuelo was horribly missed by him. He tried 
                    to throw himself into the passions of his age and class; he 
                    frequented the wine shops, and gambled away with blackguards 
                    the little gratuities which count Zustiniani bestowed 
                    upon him from time to time. This life pleased him for two 
                    or three weeks, at the end of which he found that his welfare, 
                    his health, and his voice were sensibly affected; that 
                    the <hi rend="italic">far-niente</hi> was not disorder, and that disorder was not 
                    his element. Preserved from evil passions by well understood 
                    love of self, he retired into solitude, and tried to study; 
                    but this solitude terrified him with sadness and difficulties. 
                    He then perceived that Consuelo was as necessary to his 
                    <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="x1" from="x1" to="x2"/>
                    talent as to his happiness. Studious and persevering, living 
                    in music as a bird in the air, or a fish in the sea; loving to<anchor xml:id="x2"/></p>
                <pb xml:id="leaf017r" facs="loc_mc_02609.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top">CONSUELO.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">53</fw>
                <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="y1" from="y1" to="y2"/>
                <p>overcome difficulties, without thinking more of the importance 
                    of her victory than would a child, but driven irresistibly to 
                    combat the obstacles and to penetrate the mysteries of art, by 
                    that invincible instinct which compels the germ of a plant to 
                    pierce the bosom of the earth, and to force its way towards 
                    daylight, Consuelo had one of those rare and happy organiza-<anchor xml:id="y2"/>
                    tions for which labor is a delight, a true repose, a necessary 
                    normal state, and for which inaction would be a fatigue, a 
                    wasting, a sickly state, if inaction were possible to such natures. 
                    But they do not know it; in an apparent idleness they 
                    <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="z1" from="z1" to="z2"/>
                    still labor; their revery is not vague, it is meditation. When 
                    <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="aa1" from="aa1" to="aa2"/>
                    we see them act, we think they are creating, while they are 
                    only manifesting a previous creation. You will say, dear<anchor xml:id="z2"/><anchor xml:id="aa2"/>
                    reader, that you have never known any of these exceptional 
                    organizations. I will answer, dearly beloved reader, that I 
                    have known only one, and perhaps I am older than you. 
                    Why can I not say, that I have analyzed on my own poor 
                    brain, the divine mystery of this intellectual activity! But 
                    alas! friend reader, it is neither you nor I who will study it 
                    upon ourselves.</p>
                <p>Consuelo worked always, in amusing herself always; she 
                    persevered for hours, to overcome, either by free and capricious 
                    song, or by musical reading, difficulties which would have 
                    repelled Anzoleto if left to himself; and, without any 
                    premeditated design, without any idea of emulation, she compelled 
                    him to follow her, to second her, to understand and to 
                    reply to her, sometimes in the midst of childish bursts of 
                    laughter, sometimes carried along with him by that poetic and 
                    creative <hi rend="italic">fantasia</hi>, which is experienced by the popular organizations 
                    of Spain and Italy.</p>
                <p>Imbued during many years with the genius of Consuelo, 
                    drinking it in at its fountain without understanding it, and 
                    appropriating without perceiving it, Anzoleto, otherwise kept 
                    back by his laziness, had become in music a strange compound 
                    of learning and ignorance, of inspiration and frivolity, of power 
                    and awkwardness, of boldness and weakness, which, at the 
                    last hearing, had<anchor xml:id="bb1"/> plunged Porpora into a labyrinth of medita-</p>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="infralinear" target="bb1">5&#42;</note>
                <pb xml:id="leaf018v" facs="loc_mc_00953.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">140</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top">CONSUELO.</fw>
                <p>Consuelo became pale with surprise. Notwithstanding her 
                    remarkable firmness, she had not had sufficient sang-froid to 
                    appreciate the difference between the applauses which she 
                    and her lover had received. There is in this kind of ovation, 
                    a trouble of which the most experienced artist cannot divest 
                    himself, and which often produces an illusion in some, 
                    sufficient to cause them to mistake the support of a clique for 
                    the clamors of success. But instead of exaggerating the 
                    delight of her audience, Consuelo had been terrified by so 
                    frightful a noise, had hardly understood it, and could not 
                    distinguish the preference awarded to her over Anzoleto. She 
                    scolded him ingenuously for his requirements of fortune; 
                    and seeing that she could not persuade him, nor conquer his 
                    sadness, she reproached him sweetly with being too greedy 
                    of glory, and with attaching too much value to the favor of the 
                    <span rend="doubleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="cc1" from="cc1" to="cc2"/>
                    world. "I have always told you," said she to him, "you 
                    prefer the results of art to art itself. When you do your best, 
                    when you feel that you have done well, it seems to me that a 
                    little more or less of approbation can neither add to nor 
                    diminish your inward satisfaction. Recollect what Porpora 
                    said to me the first time I sang at the Zustiniani palace: 
                    'Whoever is penetrated with a true love of his art can fear nothing'&#8212;"</p>
                <p>"You and your Porpora," interrupted Anzoleto, with<anchor xml:id="bb2"/>
                    temper, "can very easily satisfy yourselves with these fine 
                    maxims. Nothing is so easy as to philosophize on the evils 
                    of life, when you know only the goods. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">Porpora, although 
                    poor and oppressed, has an illustrious name.</hi> He has 
                    gathered so many laurels that his old head may whiten 
                    peaceably under their shade. You, who feel yourself invincible, 
                    are inaccessible to fear. At the first leap you raise 
                    yourself to the highest round of the ladder, and blame those 
                    who have no legs for their dizziness. That is not very 
                    charitable, Consuelo, but decidedly unjust. And besides, 
                    your argument is not applicable to me; you say that we 
                    should despise the approval of the public, when we have our 
                    own; but if I have it not, that inward testimony of having</p>
                <pb xml:id="leaf019v" facs="loc_mc_00954.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">142</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top">CONSUELO.</fw>
                <p>"I have lived long enough by your favor."</p>
                <p>"But it is not money that I refer to. If he does engage 
                    me at a small salary, that is of little consequence; but he will 
                    engage me for the second and third parts."</p>
                <p>"He has no other <hi rend="italic">primo uomo</hi> at hand. For a long while 
                    he has relied and depended upon you. Besides, he is all in 
                    your favor. You said he would be opposed to our marriage. 
                    Far from that, he seems to wish it, and often asks me when I 
                    shall invite him to my wedding."</p>
                <p>"Ah! indeed? That is very well! Many thanks, signor
                count."</p>
                <p>"What do you mean by that?"</p>
                <p>"Nothing. Only, Consuelo, you were very wrong not 
                    to hinder my debuts, until my faults, which you were so well 
                    acquainted with, were corrected by better studies. For you 
                    knew my faults, I repeat."</p>
                <p>"Have I wanted frankness? Have I not often warned 
                    you? But you have often told me that the public did not 
                    understand; and when I knew the success you had at the 
                    count's the first time you sang in his saloon, I thought&#8212;"</p>
                <p>"That the people of fashion knew no more than the
                vulgar public?"</p>
                <p>"I thought that your good qualities would be more striking 
                    than your faults; and it has been so, it seems to me, with one 
                    as well as with the other."</p>
                <p>"In fact," thought Anzoleto, " she says truly, and if I could 
                    put off my d&#233;buts&#8212;but then I run the risk of seeing a tenor 
                    called into my place who would not yield it to me."</p>
                <p>"Let us see," said he, after making several turns in the 
                chamber, "what are my faults?"</p>
                <p>"What I have told you very often; too much boldness, and 
                    not enough preparation; an energy more feverish than 
                    sustained; <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">dramatic effects, which are the work of the will, 
                    rather than of emotion.</hi> You were not penetrated by the 
                    sentiment of your part as a whole. You learnt it by fragments. Y
                    ou saw in it only a succession of pieces more or 
                    less brilliant. You did not seize either the gradation, or the</p>
                <pb xml:id="leaf020r" facs="loc_mc_00955.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top">CONSUELO.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">143</fw>
                <p>development, or the aggregate. <note type="authorial" resp="#h1">(</note>In the hurry to show your 
                    fine voice and the facility which you possess in certain 
                    respects, you exhibited the whole extent of your powers almost 
                    on your entrance upon the scene.<note type="authorial" resp="#h1">)</note> At the slightest opportunity, 
                    you searched for an effect, and all your effects were alike. 
                    At the end of the first act, they knew you and knew you by 
                    heart; but they did not know that that was all, and so 
                    expected something prodigious for the end. That something 
                    was not in you. Your emotion was expended, and your voice 
                    had no longer the same freshness. You felt this, you forced 
                    both the one and the other; the audience felt it likewise, and 
                    remained cold, to your great surprise, when you considered 
                    yourself most pathetic. The reason was that at the moment
                    <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="dd1" from="dd1" to="dd2"/>
                    they did not see <note type="authorial" resp="#h1">(</note>the artist 
                    inspired by passion, but the actor striving for success."<note type="authorial" resp="#h1">)</note></p><anchor xml:id="dd2"/>
                <p>"And how then do the others?" cried Anzoleto, stamping 
                    his foot. "Have I not heard them all, all who have been 
                    applauded at Venice during the last ten years? Did not old 
                    Stefanini scream when his voice failed him? And yet they 
                    applauded him with transport."</p>
                <p>"It is true, and I have not understood how the people could 
                    be deceived. Without doubt they recollected the time when 
                    he had more power, and did not wish to hurt his feelings in 
                    his old age."</p>
                <p>"And Corilla too, that idol whom you overthrew, did not 
                    she force her positions, did not she make efforts which were 
                    painful to see and to hear? Was she excited in good faith 
                    when they raised her to the skies?"</p>
                <p>"It was because I considered her methods factitious, her 
                    effects detestable, her playing as well as her singing void of 
                    taste and grandeur, that I presented myself so tranquilly upon 
                    the stage, persuaded, like you, that the public knew not much 
                    about it."</p>
                <p>"Ah!" said Anzoleto with a deep sigh, "there you put
                your finger upon my wound, poor Consuelo."</p>
                <p>"How is that, my well beloved?"</p>
                <p>"How is that, do you ask me? We deceived ourselves,</p>
                <pb xml:id="leaf021v" facs="loc_mc_00956.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">144</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top">CONSUELO.</fw>
                <p>Consuelo. The public does know. <hi rend="underline">The heart teaches what 
                    ignorance conceals.</hi> It is a great child, who needs amusement 
                    and emotion. It is contented with what they give it, 
                    but show it something better, and then it compares and understands. 
                    Corilla could charm it last week, although she sang 
                    false and wanted breath. You appear, and Corilla is lost; 
                    she is effaced, buried. Let her re&#228;ppear, and she would be 
                    hissed. If I had made my d&#233;but after her, I should have had 
                    a complete success, as I had at the count's, the first time I 
                    sang after her. But beside you, I was eclipsed. It ought to 
                    be so, and it always will be so. The public had a taste for 
                    tinsel. It mistook paste for precious stones; it was dazzled 
                    by it. You show it a fine diamond, and already it does not 
                    understand how it could have been so grossly deceived. It 
                    can no longer endure false diamonds, and holds them at their 
                    true value. This is my misfortune, Consuelo, to have been 
                    <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="ee1" from="ee1" to="ee2"/>
                    brought forward, Venetian glass-ware as I am, beside a 
                    pearl from the bottom of the ocean."</p>
                <p>Consuelo did not understand all the bitterness and truth <anchor xml:id="ee2"/>
                    contained in these observations. She placed them to the 
                    credit of the love of her betrothed, and answered to what she 
                    considered soft flatteries, only by smiles and caresses. She 
                    pretended that he would surpass her, if he would only take 
                    pains, and raised his courage by persuading him that nothing 
                    was easier than to sing like her. She had good faith in this, 
                    having never been retarded by any difficulty, and not knowing 
                    that labor itself is the first of obstacles for whomsoever 
                    has not the love of it united with perseverance.</p>
                <pb xml:id="leaf022r" facs="loc_mc_00957.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top">CONSUELO.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">153</fw>
                <p>instead of the cheat that he was; unfaithful, instead of ungrateful
                that he had always been."</p>
                <p>"What vanity, what envy?"</p>
                <p>"The vanity of surpassing all others, the vanity of surpassing you, rage at being surpassed by you."</p>
                <p>"Is that credible? Can a man be jealous of the advantages 
                    of a woman? Can a lover hate the success of her he 
                    loves? Then there are many things which I do not know, and 
                    which I cannot comprehend."</p>
                <p>"You never will comprehend them, but you will verify 
                    them every hour of your life. You will know that a man 
                    may be jealous of the advantages of a woman, when that man 
                    is an artist full of vanity; and that a lover may hate the 
                    success of her he loves, when the theatre is the atmosphere in 
                    which they live. The reason is, an actor is not a man, Consuelo, 
                    he is a woman. He lives only upon diseased vanity; 
                    he thinks only of satisfying his vanity; he works only to 
                    intoxicate himself with vanity. The beauty of a woman does 
                    him an injury. The talent of a woman effaces or disputes 
                    his own. A woman is his rival, or rather he is a woman's 
                    rival; he has all the littlenesses, all the caprices, all the exactions, 
                    all the ridiculousness of a coquette. Such is the character 
                    of most of the men attached to the theatre. There are 
                    grand exceptions; but they are so rare, so meritorious, that 
                    we ought to prostrate ourselves before them, and do them 
                    more honor than to the most learned men of science. 
                    Anzoleto is not an exception. Among the vain, he is one of the 
                    most vain; this is all the secret of his conduct."</p>
                <p>"But what an incomprehensible vengeance; what poor 
                    and inefficacious means! How can Corilla compensate him 
                    for his failure before the public? If he had frankly told me 
                    his sufferings,&#8212;(ah! there needed but one word for that,)&#8212;I 
                    should have understood him, perhaps; at any rate, I should 
                    have pitied him; I would have retired to make room for 
                    him."</p>
                <span rend="singleLine-right" xml:id="ff1" from="ff1" to="ff2"/>
                <p>"The characteristic of envious souls is to hate others in 
                    proportion to the happiness of which they deprive them.</p><anchor xml:id="ff2"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf023v" facs="loc_mc_00958.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">154</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top">CONSUELO.</fw>
                <span rend="singleLine-left" xml:id="gg1" from="gg1" to="gg2"/>
                <p>And the characteristic of love, alas! is it not to detest, in the 
                    beloved object, those pleasures which we do not furnish? 
                    While your lover abhors the public which covers you with 
                    glory, do you not hate the rival who intoxicates him with 
                    pleasure?"</p>
                <p>"You there say something which is very profound, my 
                    master, and upon which I wish to reflect."</p>
                <p>"It is something true. At the same time that Anzoleto
                hates you for your successes on the stage, you hate him for his
                pleasures in the boudoir of Corilla."</p><anchor xml:id="gg2"/>
                <p>"It is not so. I could not hate him, and you make me see 
                    that it would be mean and shameful to hate my rival. There 
                    remains then the pleasure with which she intoxicates him. 
                    and <!-- This is not a capitalization error. --> of which I cannot think without shuddering. But why? 
                    I know not. If it be an involuntary crime, then Anzoleto is 
                    not so guilty because he hates my triumph."</p>
                <p>"You are very ready to interpret matters so as to excuse 
                    his conduct and his sentiments. No ! Anzoleto is not innocent 
                    and respectable as you are. in suffering. He deceives, he 
                    humiliates you, while you strive to excuse him. Moreover, I 
                    do not wish to inspire you with hatred and resentment, but 
                    with calmness and indifference. The character of that man 
                    carries with it the actions of his life; never can you change 
                    him. Make up your mind and think of yourself."</p>
                <p>"Of myself! that is of myself alone? of myself without 
                    love and without hope?"</p>
                <p>"I have loved art for its own sake likewise; I have never 
                    separated in my thought those two inseparable things; my 
                    own life and that of Anzoleto. I do not see how there can 
                    remain any power in me to love anything, when the necessary 
                    half of my life shall be taken away."</p>
                <p>"Anzoleto was for you only an idea, and that idea gave 
                    you life. You will replace him by another idea, more grand, 
                    more pure, more vivifying. Your soul, your genius, your 
                    being in fine, will no longer be at the mercy of a fragile and</p>
                <pb xml:id="leaf024r" facs="loc_mc_00959.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top">CONSUELO.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">155</fw>
                <p>and deceitful form; you will contemplate the sublime ideal freed 
                    from this terrestrial veil; you will soar into heaven, and will 
                    live in a holy marriage with God himself."</p>
                <p>"Do you mean to say that I will become a religieuse, as
                you formerly advised me?"</p>
                <p>"No, you would thereby limit the exercise of your genius 
                    to one branch, and you must embrace all. Whatever you do, 
                    and wherever you are, on the stage as in the cloister, you 
                    may be a saint, a celestial virgin, the betrothed of the holy 
                    ideal."</p>
                <p>"What you say presents a sublime meaning, surrounded 
                    by mysterious figures. Let me retire, my master; I need time 
                    to recollect and to know myself."</p>
                <p>"You have said the word, Consuelo; you do need to know 
                    yourself. Hitherto you have not known your true self, in 
                    surrendering your soul and your future life to a being who is 
                    your inferior in every respect. You have not known your 
                    destiny, in not seeing that you were born without equal, and 
                    therefore without an associate possible in this world. You 
                    require solitude, absolute liberty. I wish for you, neither 
                    husband, nor lover, nor family, nor passions, nor ties of any 
                    kind. It is thus that I have always conceived your existence 
                    and comprehended your character. On the day that you give 
                    yourself to a mortal, you lose your divinity. Ah! if Mingotti 
                    and Molteni, my illustrious pupils, my powerful creations, 
                    had been willing to believe me, they would have lived without 
                    rivals on the earth. But woman is weak and curious; 
                    vanity blinds her, vain desires agitate her, caprice carries her 
                    away. What have they gained from the satisfaction of this 
                    restlessness? storms, fatigue, the loss or alteration of their 
                    genius. Will you not be more than they, Consuelo? will 
                    you not have an ambition superior to all the false goods of 
                    this life? Will you not wish to extinguish all the vain desires 
                    of your heart in order to seize the most beautiful crown which 
                    has ever been granted as a glory to genius?"</p>
                <p>Porpora spoke a long while, with an energy and an 
                    eloquence which I cannot translate. Consuelo listened to him,</p>
                <pb xml:id="leaf025v" facs="loc_mc_00960.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">156</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top">CONSUELO.</fw>
                <p>with her head bent and her eyes fixed upon the floor. When 
                    he had said all,&#8212;" My master," answered she, "you are
                    <span rend="singleLine-left" xml:id="hh1" from="hh1" to="hh2"/>
                    <span rend="singleLine-right" xml:id="ii1" from="ii1" to="ii2"/>
                    great, but I am not sufficiently so to comprehend you. It 
                    seems to me that you outrage human nature in proscribing 
                    her most noble passions. It seems to me that you stifle the 
                    instincts which God himself has given us, in order to make a 
                    sort of deification of a monstrous and antihuman selfishness.<anchor xml:id="hh2"/><anchor xml:id="ii2"/>
                    Perhaps I should understand you better if I were more of a 
                    Christian: I will strive to become so; that I can promise 
                    you."</p>
                <p>She retired, tranquil in appearance, but agitated in the 
                    depths of her heart. The great and austere artist accompanied 
                    her even to her home, continually indoctrinating, but not 
                    able to convince her. He did her much good nevertheless, 
                    by opening to her thought a vast field of profound and serious 
                    meditations, in which the crime of Anzoleto was buried as a 
                    particular fact, serving for a painful but solemn introduction 
                    to infinite reveries. She passed long hours in praying, weeping 
                    and reflecting; and then fell asleep with the consciousness 
                    of her virtue, and hope in a God willing to teach and to 
                    save.</p>
                <p>On the next day Porpora came to announce to her that 
                    there would be a rehearsal of Ipermnestra for Stefanini, who 
                    was to take Anzoleto's part. This latter was ill, kept his bed, 
                    and complained of a loss of voice. Consuelo's first movement 
                    was to run to his lodging for the purpose of nursing him. 
                    "Save yourself that trouble," said the professor; "he is 
                    perfectly well; the physician of the theatre has ascertained that, 
                    and he will go this evening to Corilla's without doubt. But 
                    count Zustiniani, who understands what all this means, and 
                    who consents without much regret that he should suspend his 
                    d&#233;buts, has forbidden the physician to unmask the pretence, 
                    and has requested the good Stefanini to return to the stage for 
                    a few days."</p>
                <p>"But my God, what does Anzoleto mean to do? Is he so
                much discouraged as to quit the stage?"</p>
                <p>"Yes, the stage of San Samuel. In a month he will leave</p>
                <pb xml:id="leaf026r" facs="loc_mc_00961.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top">CONSUELO.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">163</fw>
                <p>"To Vienna, whither Porpora has sent her to await his 
                    own coming. She cheated us all, the little mask. She was 
                    engaged for the imperial theatre, where Porpora is to 
                    produce his new opera."</p>
                <p>"Gone! gone without saying a word to me!" cried Anzoleto,
                rushing towards the door.</p>
                <p>"Oh! it will do you no good to hunt for her in Venice," 
                    said Corilla, with a malicious laugh and a look of triumph. 
                    "She embarked for Palestrina at the break of day, and is 
                    now far from here on the main land. Zustiniani, who 
                    thought himself beloved, and was deceived, is furious; he is 
                    in bed with a fever. But he sent Porpora to me a short 
                    time since, to ask me to sing this evening; and Stefanini, 
                    who is very tired of the stage, and is impatient to go and 
                    enjoy the pleasures of retreat in his chateau, is very desirous 
                    to have you resume your debuts. Therefore determine to 
                    reappear to-morrow in Ipermnestra. As for me, I am going 
                    to the rehearsal; they are waiting for me. You can, if you 
                    do not believe me, take a turn through the city, and convince 
                    yourself of the truth."</p>
                <p>"Ah! fury!" cried Anzoleto, "you have gained you<gap reason="illegible"></gap>
                point, but you tear my life from me." <hi rend="underline">And he fell in a
                <span rend="singleLine-left" xml:id="jj1" from="jj1" to="jj2"/>
                swoon upon the Persian carpet of the courtesan.</hi></p><anchor xml:id="jj2"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf027v" facs="loc_mc_00962.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">168</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top">CONSUELO.</fw>
                <p>the saloons, the more so because Corilla's jealousy increased 
                    the piquancy of the coquetry of which he was the object. 
                    Clorinda also developed her powers upon the stage, that is to 
                    say, her heavy beauty and the loose nonchalance of an 
                    unexampled stupidity, not without its attraction for a portion of the 
                    spectators. Zustiniani, somewhat to relieve his mind after 
                    his very deep disappointment, had made her his mistress, 
                    covered her with jewels, and pushed her in the first parts, 
                    hoping to make her succeed Corilla, who was definitively 
                    engaged at Paris for the coming season.</p>
                <p>Corilla saw without vexation this competition, from which 
                    she had nothing to fear, either at present or in the future; 
                    she even took a malicious pleasure in bringing out that coldly 
                    impudent incapacity, which recoiled before nothing. These 
                    two creatures lived therefore in good understanding and 
                    governed the administration imperiously. They put into the 
                    index every serious score, and revenged themselves upon 
                    Porpora by refusing his operas, to accept and bring forward 
                    those of his most unworthy rivals. They agreed together in 
                    injuring all who displeased them, in protecting all who humbled 
                    themselves before their power. During that season, 
                    thanks to them, the public applauded the works of the decline, 
                    and forgot that true and grand music had formerly prevailed 
                    in Venice.</p>
                <p>In the midst of his success and his prosperity, (for the 
                    count had given him a very advantageous engagement,) 
                    Anzoleto was overwhelmed with a profound disgust, and bent 
                    under the weight of a melancholy happiness. It was pitiful 
                    to see him drag himself to the rehearsals, hanging on the 
                    arm of the triumphant Corilla, pale, languishing, beautiful as 
                    an angel, ridiculous in foppishness, wearied like a man who 
                    is adored, crushed and destroyed under the laurels and myrtles 
                    <span rend="singleLine-left" xml:id="kk1" from="kk1" to="kk2"/>
                    <span rend="singleLine-left" xml:id="ll1" from="ll1" to="ll2"/>
                    he had so easily and so largely gathered. Even at the per-
                    formances, when upon the stage with his fiery mistress, he 
                    yielded to the necessity of protesting against her by his superb 
                    attitude and his impertinent languor. While she devoured<anchor xml:id="kk2"/><anchor xml:id="ll2"/> 
                    him with her eyes, he seemed, by his looks, to say to the</p>
                <pb xml:id="leaf028r" facs="loc_mc_00963.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top">CONSUELO.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">169</fw>
                <p>public: "Do not think that I respond to so much love. On 
                    the contrary, whoever will deliver me from it will do me a 
                    great service."</p>
                <p>The fact was, that Anzoleto, spoiled and corrupted by 
                    Corilla, turned against her the instincts of selfishness and 
                    ingratitude which she suggested to him against the whole 
                    world. There remained in his heart but one sentiment which 
                    was true and pure in its essence: the indestructible love 
                    which, in spite of his vices, he cherished for Consuelo. He 
                    could divert his attention from it, thanks to his natural frivolity; 
                    but he could not cure himself of it, and that love came 
                    back upon him like a remorse, like a torture, in the midst of 
                    his most culpable disorders. Unfaithful to Corilla, given to a 
                    thousand gallant intrigues, one day with Clorinda, to avenge 
                    himself in secret on the count, another with some illustrious 
                    beauty of high rank, and the third with the lowest of the 
                    figurantes; passing from the mysterious boudoir to insolent 
                    orgies, and from the furies of Corilla to the careless debaucheries 
                    of the table, it seemed as if he had assumed the task of 
                    stifling in himself all recollection of the past. <hi rend="underline">But in the 
                    midst of this disorder, a spectre seemed to dog his steps;</hi> and
                    <span rend="singleLine-right" xml:id="mm1" from="mm1" to="mm2"/>
                    deep drawn sighs escaped from his breast, when in the middle 
                    of the night, with the boisterous companions of his pleasures, 
                    he passed in his gondola along the dark buildings of the Corte<anchor xml:id="mm2"/> 
                    Minelli. Corilla, for a long time subdued by his bad treatment, 
                    and led, as are all mean souls, to love only in proportion 
                    to the contempt and outrages she received, began at last to be 
                    tired of this fatal passion. She had flattered herself that she 
                    could conquer and enchain that savage independence. She 
                    had worked for that end with a violent earnestness, and she 
                    had sacrificed everything to it. When she recognized the 
                    impossibility of ever succeeding, she began to hate him, and 
                    to search for distractions and revenge. One night, when 
                    Anzoleto was wandering in his gondola about Venice with 
                    Clorinda, he saw file off rapidly another gondola, whose 
                    extinguished lantern gave notice of some clandestine 
                    trendezvous. He paid little<anchor xml:id="nn1"/> attention to it; but Clorinda who, in her</p>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="infralinear" target="nn1">15</note> 
                <!-- Not sure why there is a 15 hovering beneath "little" on the last line, so I coded it as a note. -->
                <pb xml:id="leaf029r" facs="loc_mc_00964.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top">CONSUELO.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">251</fw>
                <p>'I speak to you of things divine and eternal,' replied he, after 
                    a little hesitation, 'and you recall to my mind the short 
                    moments which are fleeting, those puerile and ephemeral cares 
                    the record of which is almost effaced within me.'</p>
                <p>"'Speak, my son, speak!' returned count Christian; 'we 
                    must strive to know you this day.'</p>
                <p>"' You have never known me, father,' replied Albert, 'and 
                    you will not know me in what you call this life. But if you 
                    wish to know why I travelled, why I endured that unfaithful 
                    and careless guardian whom you had attached to my steps, 
                    like a greedy and lazy dog to the arm of a blind man, I will 
                    tell you in a few words. I had made you suffer enough. It 
                    was my duty to take away from you the sight of a son, rebel-
                    lious to your teachings and deaf to your remonstrances. I 
                    knew well that I should not be cured of what you called my 
                    insanity; but you needed both repose and hope: I consented 
                    to remove myself. You exacted from me the promise that I 
                    would not separate, without your consent, from the guide you 
                    had given me, and that I would allow myself to be conducted 
                    by him over the world. I wished to keep my promise. I 
                    wished also that he might sustain your hope and your confi-
                    dence, by rendering you an account of my gentleness and 
                    patience. I was gentle and patient. I closed my heart and 
                    my ears against him; he had the wit not even to think of 
                    opening them. He walked me, dressed me, and fed me like 
                    a child. I renounced life as I understood it; I accustomed 
                    myself to see misery, injustice and folly reign upon the earth. 
                    I have seen men and their institutions; indignation has given 
                    place to pity in my heart, for I have seen that the misfortunes
                    <span rend="singleLine-right" xml:id="oo1" from="oo1" to="oo2"/>
                    of the oppressed were less than those of their oppressors. In 
                    my childhood I loved only the victims: now I feel charity for 
                    the executioners, melancholy penitents, who endure in this 
                    generation the punishment of crimes which they have com-
                    mitted in former existences, and whom God condemns to be 
                    wicked, a suffering which is a thousand times more cruel than<anchor xml:id="oo2"/> 
                    that of being their innocent prey. This is why I now give 
                    alms only to relieve myself personally from the weight of</p>
            </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>