<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.07951">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Proverbial Philosophy: A Book of Thoughts and
                    Arguments, Originally treated.</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author xml:id="mft">Martin Farquhar Tupper</author>
                <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="slg">Samantha Gilmore</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2019</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.07951</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain
                        exceptions, public domain works may be freely copied or used in the creation
                        of derivative works without permission, or authorization, of the former
                        copyright owners.</p>
                    <p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and
                        is governed by a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"
                            >Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY
                        4.0).</p>
                    <p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted
                        by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Proverbial philosophy: a book of thoughts and arguments</title>
                    <idno type="callno"> PR5699.T5 A72</idno>
                    <date notBefore="1838">1838 or later</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="loc">The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt
                        Whitman, 1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</orgName>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from digital images of the original
                        item.</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl type="base">
                    <author>Martin Farquhar Tupper</author>
                    <title level="m">Proverbial Philosophy: A Book of Thoughts and Arguments,
                        Originally treated.</title>
                    <date>1838</date>
                    <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                    <note type="project"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="h1" scribeRef="#ww" medium="blue pencil"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h2" scribeRef="#mft" medium="type"/>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#slg" when="2019-10-14">Transcribed and encoded.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="marginalia">
        <front>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_sg.00035.jpg" type="recto"/>

            <titlePage>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="top-right">W.W. '75</note>

                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart type="main"><handShift new="#h2"/>Proverbial Philosophy:</titlePart>
                </docTitle>

                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart type="sub">A Book of<lb/>THOUGHTS AND ARGUMENTS,<lb/>Originally
                        Treated</titlePart>
                </docTitle>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

                <byline>BY <docAuthor>MARTIN FARQUHAR TUPPER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Esq.
                        M.A.</hi></docAuthor></byline>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

                <docImprint><pubPlace>London:</pubPlace> JOSEPH RICKERYBY, SHERBOURN LANE,<lb/>KING
                    WILLIAM STREET, CITY. <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
                    <docDate when="1847">MDCCCXXXVIII</docDate>.</docImprint>
            </titlePage>
        </front>



        <body>
            <div1>


                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_sg.00037.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top">25</fw>

                <head>Of Compensation.</head>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="s1" from="#s1" to="#s2"/><hi
                            rend="smallcaps">EQUAL</hi> is the government of heaven in allotting
                        pleasures among men,pleasures among men,</l>
                    <l>And just the eternal law, that hath wedded happiness to virtue.</l>
                    <l>For verily on all things else broodeth disappointment with care,</l>
                    <l>That childish man may be taught the shallowness of earthly enjoyment<anchor
                            xml:id="s2"/></l>
                    <l>Wherefore, ye that have enough, envy ye the rich man his abundance?</l>
                    <l>Wherefore, daughters of affluence, covet ye the cottager's content?</l>
                    <l>Take the good with the evil, for ye are all pensioners of God,</l>
                    <l>And none may choose or refuse the cup His wisdom mixeth.</l>
                    <l>The poor man rejoiceth at his toil, and his daily bread is sweet to him;</l>
                    <l>Content with present good, he looketh not for evil to the future:</l>
                </lg>
                <fw type="sig" place="bottom-right">C</fw>

            </div1>


            <div1>

                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc_sg.00039.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top">33</fw>

                <head>Of Indirect Influences.</head>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><hi rend="smallcaps">FACE</hi> thy foe in the field, and perchance thou wilt
                        meet thy master,</l>
                    <l>For the sword is chained to his wrist, and his armour buckled for the
                        battle;</l>
                    <l>But find him when he looketh not for thee, aim between the joints of his
                        harness,</l>
                    <l>And the crest of his pride will be humbled, his cruelty will bite the
                        dust.</l>
                    <l>Beard not a lion in his den, but fashion the secret pitfall,</l>
                    <l>So shalt thou conquer the strong, thyself triumphing in weakness.</l>
                    <l>The hurricane rageth fiercely, and the promontory standeth in its might,</l>
                    <l>Breasting the artillery of heaven, as darts glance from the crocodile:</l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled" hand="#h1">But the small continual creeping of silent footsteps of
                            the sea</hi></l>
                </lg>



                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc_sg.00040.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-left">34</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top">Of Indirect Influences.</fw>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><hi rend="circled" hand="#h1">Mineth the wall of adamant, and stealthily compasseth its
                            ruin.</hi></l>
                    <l>The weakness of accident is strong, where the strength of design is weak:</l>
                    <l>And a casual analogy convinceth, where a mind beareth not argument.</l>
                    <l>Will not a man listen? be silent; and prove thy maxim by example:</l>
                    <l>Never fear thou losest not thy hold, though thy mouth doth not render a
                        reason.</l>
                    <l>Contend not in wisdom with a fool, for thy sense maketh much of his
                        conceit;</l>
                    <l>And some errors never would have thriven, had it not been for learned
                        refutation.</l>
                    <l>Yea, much evil hath been caused by an honest wrestler for truth,</l>
                    <l>And much of unconscious good, by the man that hated wisdom:</l>
                    <l>For the intellect judgeth shrewdly, and if thou overstep thy argument,</l>
                    <l>Or seem not consistent with thyself, or fail in thy direct purpose,</l>
                    <l>The mind that went along with thee, shall stop and return without thee,</l>
                    <l>And thou shalt have raised a foe, where thou mightest have won a friend.</l>
                </lg>

            </div1>


            <div1>

                <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="loc_sg.00042.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-left">40</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top">Of Memory.</fw>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Beams of the Sun, streams from the River, branches of the might Tree,</l>
                    <l>Some bearing fruit, some bearing leaves, and some diseased and
                        barren,&#8212;</l>
                    <l>Some for the feast, some for the floor, and some,&#8212;how many,&#8212;for
                        the fire?</l>
                    <l>Memory may be but a power of coming to the treasury of fact,</l>
                    <l>A momentary self-desertion, an absence in spirit from the now,</l>
                    <l>An actual coursing hither and thither, by the mind, slipped from its
                        leash,</l>
                    <l>A life, as in the mystery of dreams, spent within the limits of a moment.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><hi rend="smallcaps">A BRUTISH</hi> man knoweth not this, neither can a fool
                        comprehend it,</l>
                    <l>But there be secrets of the memory, deep, wondrous, and fearful.</l>
                    <l>Were I at Petra, could I not declare, My soul hath been here before me?</l>
                    <l>Am I strange to the columned halls, the calm dead grandeur of Palmyra</l>
                    <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="s3" from="#s3" to="#s4"/>
                    <l>Know I not thy mount, O Carmel! Have I not voyaged on the Danube,</l>
                    <l>Nor seen the glare of Arctic snows,&#8212;nor the black tents of the
                        Tartar?</l>
                    <l>Is it then a dream, that I remember the face of them of old</l>

                    <note hand="#h1" place="bottom-right">accepted</note>
                    <anchor xml:id="s4"/>
                </lg>


                <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="loc_sg.00043.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top">Of Memory.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-right">41</fw>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="s5" from="#s5" to="#s6"/>
                    <l>While wandering in the prove with Plato, and listening to Zeno in the
                        porch?</l>
                    <l>Paul have I seen, and Pythagoras,&#8212;an the Stagyrite hath spoken me
                        friendly,</l>
                    <l>And His meek eye looked also upon me, standing with Peter in the palace.</l>
                    <l>Athens and Rome, Persepolis and Sparta, am I not a freeman of you all?</l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s6"/>
                    <l>And chiefly can my yearning heart forget thee, O Jerusalem?&#8212;</l>
                    <l>For the strong magic of conception, mingled with the fumes of memory,</l>
                    <l>Giveth me a life in all past time, yea, and addeth substance to the
                        future.</l>
                    <l>Be ye my judges, imaginative minds, full-fledged to soar into the sun,</l>
                    <l>Whose grosser natural thoughts the chemistry of wisdom hath sublimed,</l>
                    <l>Have ye not confessed to a feeling, a consciousness strange and vague,</l>
                    <l>That ye have gone this way before, and walk again your daily life,</l>
                    <l>Tracking an old routine, and on some foreign strand,</l>
                    <l>Where bodily ye never were before, finding your own footsteps?</l>
                    <l>Hath not at times some recent friend looked out an old familiar,</l>
                    <l>Some newest circumstance or place teemed as with ancient memories?</l>
                    <l>A startling sudden flash lighteth up all for an instant,</l>
                </lg>
                <fw type="sig" place="bottom-right">D</fw>

            
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="loc_sg.00046.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <fw type="header" place="top">Of Memory.</fw>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top-right">43</fw>
            
            <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
            
            <lg type="stanza">
                <span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="s7" from="#s7" to="#s8"/>
                <l><hi rend="smallcaps">TO</hi> be pained for a minute, to fear for an hour, to hope for a week: how long and weary!</l>
                <l>But to remember forescore years, is to look back upon a day.</l>
                <anchor xml:id="s8"/><note place="right" type="authorial" resp="#h1" target="#s7">&#8592;</note>
                <l>An avenue seemeth to lengthen in the eyes of the wayfaring man,</l>
                <l>But let him turn, those stationed elms crowd up within a yard:</l>
                <l>Pace the lamp-lit streets of some sleeping city,</l>
                <l>The multitude of cressets shall seem one, in the false picture of perspective;</l>
                <l>Even so, in sweet treachery, dealeth the aged himself,</l>
                <l>He gazeth on the green hill-tops, while the marshes beneath are hidden;</l>
                <l>And the partial telescope of memory pierceth the blank between,</l>
                <l>To look with lingering love at the fair star of childhood.</l>
                <l>Life is as the current spark on the miner's wheel of flints;</l>
                <l>Whiles it spinneth, there is light; stop it, all is darkness.</l>
                <l>There is but the flitting moment, wherein to hope or to enjoy,</l>
                <l>But in the calendar of memory, that moment is all time.</l>
            </lg>
                
                <fw type="sig" place="bottom-right">D 2</fw>
                
            </div1>
            
            
            
            <div1>

                <pb xml:id="leaf007r" facs="loc_sg.00048.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top">Of Experience.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-right">73</fw>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>For youth suspecteth nought, till manhood, bitterly learned,</l>
                    <l>Mistrusteth all, overleaping the mark; and age correcteth his excess.</l>
                    <l>Suspicion is the scaffold unto faith, a temporary needful eyesore</l>
                    <l>By which the strong man's dwelling is slowly builded up behind:</l>
                    <l>But soon as the top-stone hath been set to the well-proved goodly
                        pyramid,</l>
                    <l>The scaffold is torn down, and well-timed trust taketh its long leave of
                        suspicion.</l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled" hand="#h1">A thousand volumes in a thousand tongues, enshrines the
                            lessons of Experience,</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled" hand="#h1">Yet a man shall read them all, and go forth none the
                            wiser:</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled" hand="#h1">For a self-love lendeth him a glass, to <choice>
                                <orig>colour</orig>
                                <reg>color</reg>
                            </choice> all he connecth,</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled" hand="#h1">Lest in the features of another, he find his own
                            complexion.</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled" hand="#h1">But thou, student of Wisdom, feed on the marrow of the
                            matter;</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled" hand="#h1">If thou wilt suspect, let it be thyself: if thou wilt
                            expect, let it not be gladness.</hi></l>
                </lg>

                <fw type="sig" place="bottom-right">F</fw>

            </div1>
            
            
            
            <div1>
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf008r" facs="loc_sg.00065.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top">Of estimating Character.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-right">75</fw>
                
                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
                
                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Judge not of things by their events: neither of character by providence;</l>
                    <l>And count not a man more evil, because he is more unfortunate.</l>
                    <l>For blessings of a better covenant lie not in the sunshine of prosperity;</l>
                    <l>But pain and chastisement the rather show the wise Father's love.</l>
                </lg>
                
                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><hi rend="smallcaps">BEHOLD</hi> that daughter of the world: she is full of gaiety and gladness;</l>
                    <l>The diadem of rank is on her brow, uncounted wealth is in her coffers.</l>
                    <l><span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="s9" from="#s9" to="#s10"/>
                        <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="s11" from="#s11" to="#s12"/>She tricketh out her beauty like Jezebel, and is welcome in the court of kings;</l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s10"/>
                    <anchor xml:id="s12"/>
                    <l>She is queen of the fools of fashion, and ruleth the revels of luxury.</l>
                    <l>And though she sitteth not as Tamar, nor standeth in the ways as Rahab,</l>
                    <l>Yet in the secret of her chamber, she shrinketh not from dalliance and guilt.</l>
                    <l>She careth not if there be a God, or a soul, or a time of retribution,</l>
                    <l>Pleasure is the idol of her heart: she thirsteth for no purer heaven.</l>
                    <l>And she laugheth with light good <choice>
                        <orig>humour</orig>
                        <reg>humor</reg>
                    </choice>, and all men praise her gentleness;</l>
                </lg>
                
                <fw type="sig" place="bottom-right">F 2</fw>
                
            </div1>
                    


            <div1>

                <pb xml:id="leaf009r" facs="loc_sg.00051.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top">Of Revelation.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-right">113</fw>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>The element of all things are the same, though nature hath mixed them with a
                        difference,</l>
                    <l>And Learning delighteth to discover the affinity of seeming opposites:</l>
                    <l>So out of great things and small, draweth he the secrets of the universe,</l>
                    <l>And argueth the cycles of the stars, from a pebble flung by a child.</l>
                    <l>It is pleasant to note all plants, from the rush to the spreading cedar,</l>
                    <l>From the giant king of palms,(13) to the lichen that staineth its stem;</l>
                    <l>To watch the workings of instinct, that grosser reason of brutes,&#8212;</l>
                    <l>The river-horse browsing in the jungle, the plover screaming on the moor,</l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled" hand="#h1">The dog at his master's feet, and the walrus anchored to the iceberg;</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled" hand="#h1">To trace the consummate skill that hath modelled the anatomy of insects,</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled" hand="#h1">Small fowls that sun their wings on the petals of wild flowers;</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled" hand="#h1">To learn a use in the beetle, and more than a beauty in the butterfly;</hi></l>
                    <l>To <choice>
                            <orig>recognise</orig>
                            <reg>recognize</reg>
                        </choice> affections in a moth, and look with admiration on a spider.</l>
                    <l>It is glorious to gaze upon the firmament, and see from far the mansions of
                        the blest,</l>
                </lg>

            </div1>



            <div1>

                <pb xml:id="leaf010r" facs="loc_sg.00053.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top">121</fw>

                <head>Of a Trinity.</head>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><hi rend="smallcaps">DESPISEST</hi> thou, shrewd reckoner, the God of a good
                        man's worship?</l>
                    <l>And shall thy calculating folly gainsay the unity of three?</l>
                    <l>Look now abroad, I pray thee, for analogy holdeth in all things,</l>
                    <l>And the Maker hath stamped his image on every creature of his hand:</l>
                    <l>Show me the matter, or the spirit, that is not three in one,</l>
                    <l>And I will show thee a marvel&#8212;a being which He hath not created.</l>
                    <l>Thyself hast within thyself body and life and reason;</l>
                    <l>Matter and breath and instinct unite in all beasts of the field:</l>
                    <l>Substance, coherence, and weight fashion of the fabric of the earth;</l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled" hand="#h1">The will, the doing, and the deed combine to frame a
                            fact:</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled" hand="#h1">The stem, the leaf, and the flower; beginning, middle, and
                            end;</hi></l>
                </lg>

            </div1>



            <div1>

                <pb xml:id="leaf011r" facs="loc_sg.00055.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top">137</fw>

                <head>Of Reading.</head>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><hi rend="smallcaps">ONE</hi> drachma for a good book, and a thousand talents
                        for a true friend:&#8212;</l>
                    <l>So standeth the market, where scarce is ever costly.</l>
                    <l>Yea, were the diamonds of Golconda common as shingles on the shore,</l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled" hand="#h1">A ripe apple would ransom kings before a shining
                            stone:</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled" hand="#h1">And so, were a wholesome book as rare as an honest
                            friend,</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled" hand="#h1">To choose the book be mine: the friend let another
                            take.</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled" hand="#h1">For altered looks and jealousies and fears have none
                            entrance there;</hi></l>
                    <l>The silent volume listeneth well, and speaketh when thou listest.</l>
                    <l>It praiseth thy good without envy; it chideth thine evil without malice;</l>
                    <l>Is is to thee thy waiting slave, and thine unbending teacher.</l>
                    <l>Need to <choice>
                            <orig>humour</orig>
                            <reg>humor</reg>
                        </choice> no caprice, need to bear with no infirmity;</l>
                </lg>

                <fw type="sig" place="bottom-right">K</fw>



                <pb xml:id="leaf012r" facs="loc_sg.00057.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top">Of Reading.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-left">139</fw>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Trees yielding all fruits, whose leaves are for the healing of the
                        nations;</l>
                    <l>Groves of knowledge, where all my eat, nor fear a flaming sword;</l>
                    <l>Gentle comrades, kind advisers; friends, comforts, treasures;</l>
                    <l>Helps, governments, diversities of tongues; who can weigh your worth?</l>
                    <l>To walk no longer with the just; to be driven from the porch of science;</l>
                    <l>to bid long adieu to those intimate ones, poets, philosophers, and
                        teachers;</l>
                    <l>To see no record of the sympathies which bind thee in communion with the
                        good;</l>
                    <l>To be thrust from the feet of Him, who spake as never man spake;</l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled" hand="#h1">To have no avenue to heaven but the dim aisle of
                            superstition,</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled" hand="#h1">To live as an Esquimaux, in lethargy; to die as the Mohawk
                            in ignorance;</hi></l>
                    <l>O what were life, but a blank? what were death, but a terror?</l>
                    <l>What were man, but a burden to himself? what were mind, but misery?</l>
                    <l>Yea, let another Omar burn the full library of knowledge,</l>
                    <l>And the broad world may perish in the flames, offered on the ashes of its
                        wisdom!</l>
                </lg>

                <fw type="sig" place="bottom-right">K 2</fw>

            </div1>


            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf013v" facs="loc_sg.00060.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-left">150</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top">Of Wealth.</fw>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><choice>
                            <orig>labour</orig>
                            <reg>labor</reg>
                        </choice>, with care, for the man of law, responsible in his gains:</l>
                    <l><choice>
                            <orig>labour</orig>
                            <reg>labor</reg>
                        </choice>, with envy and annoyance, where strangers will thee wealth:</l>
                    <l><choice>
                            <orig>labour</orig>
                            <reg>labor</reg>
                        </choice>, with indolence and gloom, where wealth falleth from a father:</l>
                    <l><choice>
                            <orig>labour</orig>
                            <reg>labor</reg>
                        </choice> unto all, whether aching thews, or aching head, or
                        spirit&#8212;</l>
                    <l>The curse on the sons of men, in all their states is <choice>
                            <orig>labour</orig>
                            <reg>labor</reg>
                        </choice>.</l>
                    <l>Nevertheless, to the diligent, <choice>
                            <orig>labour</orig>
                            <reg>labor</reg>
                        </choice> bringeth blessing:</l>
                    <l>The thought of duty sweeteneth toil, and travail is as pleasure;</l>
                    <l>And time spent in doing hath a comfort that is not for the idle,</l>
                    <l>The cures is transmuted into joy, by the dear alchemy of Mercy.</l>
                    <span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="s13" from="#s13" to="#s14"/>
                    <l>Wealth hath never given happiness, but often hastened misery:</l>
                    <l>Enough hath never caused misery, but often quickened happiness.</l>
                    <l>Enough is less than thy thought, O pampered creature of society;</l>
                    <l>And he that hath more than enough, is a thief of the rights of his
                        brother.</l>

                    <note hand="#h1" place="bottom-right">wealth</note>
                    <anchor xml:id="s14"/>
                </lg>


            </div1>



            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf014r" facs="loc_sg.00061.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top">Of Invention.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-right">153</fw>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="s15" from="#s15" to="#s16"/><span
                            rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="s17" from="#s17" to="#s16"/>And
                        anon the cold smooth stone is warm with feathery grass,</l>
                    <l>And the light sporules of the fern are dropt by the passing wind;</l>
                    <l>The wood-pidgeon, on swift wing, leaveth its crop-full of grain;</l>
                    <l>The squirrel's jealous care planteth the fir-cone and the filbert.</l>
                    <l>Years pass, and the sterile rock is rank with tangled herbage;</l>
                    <l>And the tall pine and hazel-thicket shade the rambling school-boy.</l>
                    <l>Shall the rock boast of its fertility? shall it lift the head in pride?</l>
                    <l>Shall the mind of man be vain of the harvest of its thoughts?</l>
                    <l>The savage is that rock; and a million chances from without,</l>
                    <l>By little and little acting on the mind, heapeth the hot-bed of society:</l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s16"/>
                    <l>And the soul, fed and fattened on the thoughts and things around it,</l>
                    <l>Groweth to perfection, full of fruit, the fruit of foreign seeds.</l>
                    <l>For we learn upon a hint, we find upon a clue,</l>
                    <l>We yield an hundred-fold; but the great sower is Analogy.</l>
                    <l>There must be an acrid sloe before a luscious peach;</l>
                    <l>By culture man may do all things, short of the miracle&#8212;Creation.</l>
                    <l>The soil may be rich, and the mind may be active, but neither yield
                        unsown;</l>
                    <l>The eye cannot make light, nor the mind make spirit:</l>
                    <l>Therefore it is wise in man to name all novelty, invention;</l>
                </lg>

                <fw type="sig" place="bottom-right">L</fw>

            </div1>
            
            
            
            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf015v" facs="loc_sg.00064.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-left">186</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top">Of Marriage.</fw>
                
                
                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
                
                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>But of those God may give thee of her, that they reproach thee not for their being:</l>
                    <l>See that he hath given her health, lest thou lose her early and weep:</l>
                    <l>See that she springeth of a wholesome stock, that thy little ones perish not before thee:</l>
                    <l>For many a fair skin hath covered a mining disease,</l>
                    <l>And many a laughing cheek been bright with the glare of madness.</l> 
                </lg>
                
                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><hi rend="circled" hand="#h1"><hi rend="smallcaps">MARK</hi>the converse of thou lovest; that it be simple and sincere;</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled" hand="#h1">For an artful or false woman shall set thy pillow with thorns.</hi></l>
                    <l>Observe her deportman with others, when she thinketh not that thou art nigh,</l>
                    <l>For with thee will the blushes of love conceal the true <choice>
                        <orig>colour</orig>
                        <reg>color</reg>
                    </choice> of her mind.</l>
                    <l>Hath she learning? is it good, so that modesty go with it:</l>
                    <l>Hath she wisdom? is it precious, but beware that thou exceed;</l>
                    <l>For woman must be subject, and the true mastery is of the mind.</l>
                    <l>Be joined to tine equal in rank, or the foot of pride shall kick at thee;</l>
                    <l>And look not only for riches, lest though be mated with misery.</l>
                    <l>Marry not without means; for so shouldst though tempt Providence;</l>
                </lg>
            </div1>



        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
