<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="mid.00011">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Indian Epic Poetry</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
                <author xml:id="unk">unknown</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="lmg">Lauren Grewe</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="slg">Samantha Gilmore</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>University of Texas at Austin</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>mid.00011</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>kprice@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Ed-Folsom@uiowa.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>bbarney2@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain
                        exceptions, public domain works may be freely copied or used in the creation
                        of derivative works without permission, or authorization, of the former
                        copyright owners.</p>
                    <p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and
                        is governed by a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"
                            >Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY
                        4.0).</p>
                    <p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted
                        by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Thoreau and Others on Indian Poetry and Indian Drama</title>
                    <idno type="callno">MS-121</idno>
                    <date notBefore="1848-10-01" notAfter="1892-05-26">After October 1, 1848</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="mid">Middlebury College Library, Special Collections, Rare
                        Books and Manuscripts</orgName>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from our digital image of original.</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl type="base" xml:id="r1">
                    <author>Unknown author</author>
                    <title level="a">Indian Epic Poetry</title>
                    <title level="j">Westminster Review</title>
                    <date when="1848">October 1848</date>
                    <publisher>Leonard Scott &amp; Co.</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="h1" scribeRef="#unk" medium="typescript"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h2" scribeRef="#ww" medium="brown-ink"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h3" scribeRef="#ww" medium="black-ink"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h4" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h5" scribeRef="#ww" medium="blue-pencil"/>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#slg" when="2019-10-08">proofed</change>
            <change who="#lmg" when="2012-07-19">transcribed and encoded.</change>
            <change who="#lmg" when="2014-02-04">checked.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="marginalia">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="mid.00011.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <head type="main-authorial"><handShift new="#h2"/>Indian Epic Poetry</head>
            <fw type="date" place="top left"><handShift new="#h1"/>1848.</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top" rend="italic">Indian Epic Poetry.</fw>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">17</fw>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h3" rend="circled">Who was Vei<unclear reason="illegible"
                    cert="high" resp="#slg">a</unclear>s?</note>
            <cb/>
            <del rend="hashmark" hand="#h4"><p><handShift new="#h1"/>"Read over your compositions,
                    and wherever you meet with a passage which you think is <hi rend="italic"
                        >particularly</hi> fine, strike it out," the quality of the works would have
                    been certainly benefited, though the quantity would have been reduced in a much
                    higher proportion. </p>
                <p>But the premier had, no doubt, Aristotle's recipe in his eye: "The greatest thing
                    of all is to be <hi rend="italic">powerful in metaphor,</hi> for this alone
                    cannot be acquired from another, but is the mark of original genius; for to
                    metaphorize <hi rend="italic">well</hi>, is to discern in different objects that
                    which is similar."</p>
                <p>The noble premier is <hi rend="italic">powerful</hi> enough in
                    metaphor,&#8212;strong as Sampson, to his own undoing. He has fallen into the
                    error of adopting a canon for his own guidance, which is addressed to "original
                    genius." Nor are there any counterbalancing qualities to weigh down this
                    besetting sin. There is no originality of thought, no vigorous reasoning, no
                    evidence even of industrious research. We have neither new facts and materials,
                    nor happy illustrations of old ones. The noble writer's works are "objectless;"
                    we rise from their perusal with no fresh information of any kind, and are at a
                    loss to understand why the premier should have rushed into print.</p>
                <p>We have expressed our opinions on the several works in the order in which they
                    were published. It is unnecessary, therefore, to add to our criticism on their
                    several merits. We regret that we cannot, upon the whole, sum up in Lord John
                    Russell's favour; that we cannot favour his pretensions to literary rank, even
                    in the smallest degree. The noble lord <hi rend="italic">may</hi> call, it is
                    true, eleven witnesses, 4to. 8vo., and 12mo., to support his pretensions; but,
                    if well-advised, he will rather trust to the merciful consideration of the
                    court, than rely upon their testimony: for the said witnesses, though decent
                    enough in their exterior clothing, when made to disclose their evidence, will
                    infallibly damage the noble defendant's cause, and for ever strip him of all <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">LITERARY CHARACTER.</hi></p>
                <ab>S.</ab></del>

            <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

            <p>A<hi rend="smallcaps">RT</hi>. II.&#8212;1. <hi rend="italic">Bαλα βαρατα η συντομη
                    ιηζ Μαζαβαςδιας, μεταγλωττιοα παςα Δημητςιου Ταλδνου, Αθηναιου.</hi> Athens.
                1847.</p>
            <p>2. R<hi rend="smallcaps">AMAYANA</hi>&#8212;<hi rend="italic">testo Sanscrito secondo
                    i Codici Manoscritti della Scuola Gaudana, per Gaspare Gorresio.</hi> V<hi
                    rend="smallcaps">ols</hi>. I., II., III. <hi rend="italic">Parigi.</hi>
                1843-4-5.</p>

            <p>W<hi rend="smallcaps">E</hi> little think, while we read of the glories of Grecian
                and Roman history, that during <fw type="sig" place="bottom">VOL. L. 2</fw><cb/>
                those very centuries which they seem so to have monopolized, the sun still witnessed
                other empires in other parts of the earth, whose histories were full of interest in
                those days, and not without importance even in our own time. Contemporaneous with
                these romance-lands of European antiquity, flourished the great empires of Persia
                and India; and however little their orbits intersected, each has indeed a "magic
                circle," of awful import and reality to the human hearts which beat within its
                round. Each had its own heroes and its chivalrous deeds; each had its own laws and
                institutions, and its generations of minds to be trained and influenced thereby.
                Thus the two worlds of ancient life fulfil their destiny side by side: rarely do
                they visibly intermingle to the historian's eye; however they may have mutually
                influenced one another by the silent interchanges of hospitality and commerce, in
                the private life of their people. The expeditions of Darius and Xerxes fell on
                Greece as violently, but as transiently, as a storm; and Alexander's invasion of
                India scarcely reached the banks of the Ganges even as a <hi rend="italic"
                    >rumour</hi>. But unimportant as these <choice>
                    <orig>enterprizes</orig>
                    <reg>enterprises</reg>
                </choice> may have been, and however transitory were their effects, at our distance
                of time they assume an interest utterly apart from their historical value. Such
                events as these form the few glimpses which we now get of the old condition of that
                part of the world. Long successions of mighty kings had reigned in different parts
                of India before Alexander thought of conquering Porus; but it is only of Porus that
                European history tells us any news: Alexander, as it were, threw for us a torch into
                the blank darkness; but he only revealed what existed there before, and we catch a
                momentary glimpse of a monarch and his court sitting in that hall of time in solemn
                state, and then the scene vanishes again from our eyes into blank darkness as
                before. All that the Greeks have left us concerning India, only amounts to such a
                transient view as this; nor could we indeed expect that it should be otherwise; and
                modern writers have wasted their wonder to little purpose respecting it. For a hasty
                inroad of foreign conquerors could only collect a few observations on the people on
                their way; and these would naturally relate to the more prominent peculiarities, and
                the deeper traits of the nation's life and character would remain far hidden from
                their sight. Thus they may have preserved for us a few facts of interest, which
                modern scholars have verified in their Sanscrit researches; but the greater part of
                their details are trivial, and not unfrequently quite erroneous.</p>

            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="mid.00011.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">18</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top" rend="italic">Indian Epic Poetry.</fw>
            <fw type="date" place="top right">Oct.</fw>
            <cb/>
            <p>India has, however, a literature of her own, in which the Greeks are as little
                thought of as she is in theirs; and the <hi rend="italic">discovery</hi> of Sanscrit
                (for such it may well be called), has opened an almost inexhaustible region for the
                scholar’s investigation. In this ancient literature we have the growth of a language
                in all its stages of development. In the Vedas, or sacred books, we have it in all
                its roughness and unpolished rudeness, abounding with archaisms and irregularities,
                which present strange resemblances with the old tongues of Europe; in the heroic
                poems of a succeeding age, we find it when it had undergone no little elaboration
                and improvement, for, as Emerson says, "language is an edifice, to which every
                forcible individual contributes a stone;" and in the dramatic poems (some of which
                were contemporary with Augustus and Virgil), and in the later epics which followed,
                we have it in all that extreme elaboration which precedes decline, when the weapon,
                by dint of overpolish, grows too keen and of too fine an edge for the daily
                requirements of life. There is also in the dramas a continual intermixture of
                Pracrit, a dialect which sprang out of Sanscrit, just as Italian and Spanish out of
                Latin,&#8212;this being the language of the female characters, while Sanscrit is
                confined to the men.</p>
            <p>Now all this had been going on in that very period which we are apt to think served
                only to ripen Greece and Rome. While Greek was passing from the Homeric dialect to
                the Attic of Thucydides and Plato, and thence falling into balanced antitheses and
                sophistries; and while Latin was slowly escaping from its Oscan nurse, and shaping
                its sound from the <hi rend="italic">arvales fratres</hi> to fit words to be set to
                the heroic music of Ennius, and passing from thence to the hands of Virgil, who
                added to it that grace which inevitably precedes and ushers in declining vigor:
                while all this was passing, India was witnessing the rise and decline of as noble a
                speech as these, with a literature entirely her own, exemplifying in itself all
                those changes which scholars love to trace in the classical languages of Europe. The
                same principles may be observed working alike in each; the gradual decline of the
                old epic spirit, with the heroic speech which rose from it like the breath of
                action, and the fading away of what was once glorious and true into a common-place,
                which becomes vapid and then false, with the barrenness of thought which inevitably
                blights a literature, if we cling to the old forms of the past, when the life that
                once animated them has passed into others, according to nature’s
                metempsychosis;&#8212;all this is exemplified in <cb/> the poets of ancient India as
                much as in those of Greece or Rome. For heroic poetry only belongs to heroic times,
                and when those times are passed men must leave the old subjects and turn to others
                which are new. It was for want of this that in Athens Marathon became the staple for
                every sophist and declaimer; and in the same way, in the latter days of Roman
                literature, every poet tried his hand at a new epic on the old mythology. But in the
                times of the later C&#231;sars and their successors, all faith in the mythic ages
                was gone; tyranny and corrupted civilization had hardened men’s hearts against the
                beautiful, and such poetry was no longer possible. But alas! the form always
                continues long after the soul has migrated elsewhere, and men fancy, at every new
                creation of art, that it is the only genuine kind, and they fly in pursuit of the
                novelty; forgetful that nature’s horn (as in the fairy tale) hangs alike for all,
                although it is the only true knight who can make it sound. Thus everything which
                once was beautiful becomes, by-and-by, false and deformed,&#8212;<span
                    rend="bracket-right" hand="#h4" xml:id="s1" from="#s1" to="#s2"/><hi
                    rend="underline" hand="#h4">the artist is always <span rend="bracket-right"
                        hand="#h4" xml:id="s3" from="#s3" to="#s4"/>succeeded by the imitator, who
                    fancies that imitation is creation.</hi> Meanwhile <hi rend="underline"
                    hand="#h4">poetry</hi> comes and goes</p>
            <lg type="linegroup">
                <l>"And flies like a bird from tree to tree,"</l>
            </lg>
            <p><hi rend="underline" hand="#h4">making no subject her</hi> continual resting <hi
                    rend="underline" hand="#h4">place, but alig</hi>hting on all in their turns; <hi
                    rend="underline" hand="#h4">and thus Troy</hi>, and Marathon, and Tiber, <hi
                    rend="underline" hand="#h4">and Hindost</hi>an alike become beautiful to all <hi
                    rend="underline" hand="#h4">mankind,</hi> when she hallows them; but only<anchor
                    xml:id="s4"/><span rend="bracket-right" xml:id="s5" hand="#h4" from="#s5"
                    to="#s6"/>
                <hi rend="underline" hand="#h4">while <hi rend="italic">she</hi> is there do they
                    charm, and if a<anchor xml:id="s2"/>
                    <hi rend="underline" hand="#h4">profane foot</hi> approaches she is
                        gone&#8212;per<hi rend="underline" hand="#h4">haps to t</hi>he fern at the
                    tree's foot, or to <hi rend="underline" hand="#h4">yonder peasant's</hi> cottage
                    on the hill!</hi></p>
            <anchor xml:id="s6"/>
            <p>The earliest specimens of Hindu literature, the Vedas, date from an almost unknown
                antiquity, and the language in which they are written is a sufficient; voucher for
                their authenticity. Their whole style bears marks of belonging to the earliest ages
                of Sanscrit, when its original asperities were yet unsoftened, and its
                irregularities unreduced to rules and order; and when we compare it with that of the
                epic poems of the succeeding ages, it is like passing from Chaucer to Pope in our
                own literature. Until lately, the Vedas have received but little attention from
                Sanscrit scholars, and only parts of them have hitherto been published; but editions
                of all are, we believe, now in preparation, and these will doubtless throw an
                immense light on Hindu antiquities. </p>
            <p>It is only by going back to these ancient beginnings of Hindu thought, that we can
                ever hope to understand the various ideas <pb xml:id="leaf002r"
                    facs="mid.000111.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h3" place="top">The Ramayana is the most ancient
                    having one separate distinct thread</note>
                <fw type="date" place="top left">1848.</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top" rend="italic">Indian Epic Poetry.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">19</fw>
                <cb/>and customs which have influenced every generation of that people, from before
                Troy to the present day; and without this even our knowledge of the language can
                only be imperfect, and many of the links which connect it with the old languages of
                Europe must remain unknown. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h4">The Vedas are <span
                        rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h4" xml:id="s7" from="#s7" to="#s8"/>four in
                    number,</hi> the Rich, Yajush, Saman, and Atharvana, and <hi rend="underline"
                    hand="#h4">consist chiefly of hymns and prayers to the various deities;</hi> and
                doubtless it was these which Calanus sang in the presence of Alexander’s army, when
                he was borne to the funeral pyre, “crowned after the Indian manner, and singing in
                the Indian tongue; and the Indians said that these were ancient songs in the praise
                of the Gods.”&#8212;(Arrian vii.) Mr. Colebroke has settled the date of the Yajush
                Veda by proving, in one of his essays, that the place given to the solstitial
                points, in a calendar<anchor xml:id="s8"/>
                <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h4" xml:id="s9" from="#s9" to="#s10"/>appended
                to it (which represents their position at the time of its being composed), is really
                that in which those points were situated in the fourteenth century before our era;
                and there are many parts of the Vedas which must belong to even a much higher
                antiquity. The mythological systems of later times are here found (when they occur
                at all) only in the germ, and a simple monotheism reigns throughout, widely
                different from the belief which we find in the heroic poems.<anchor xml:id="s10"
                    /><span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h4" xml:id="s11" from="#s11" to="#s12"/>
                <hi rend="underline" hand="#h4">At the same time the Vedas abound with splendid
                    passages of poetry, and many a wonderful glimpse of primeval truth</hi> occurs
                in the midst of their obscure invocations. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h4">These
                    are, as it were, the primeval rocks of the world of Hindu thought, and on these
                    all the other <hi rend="italic">strata</hi> rest; and in these we still can hold
                    converse with those mighty sages, who lived and thought in those remote
                    centuries before history,</hi> and have yet left such traces of their existence,
                even on the degenerate Hindus of the present day.</p>
            <p>But the age of the Vedas passed, and<anchor xml:id="s12"/> each century brought its
                series of changes. The priests, who in the earliest times were the sole repositories
                of the nation’s knowledge, began to lose their monopoly, as the military class,
                called <hi rend="italic">Kshatriyas</hi>, became more powerful and independent.
                These were, as their name intimates, the soldiers-possessors of the soil; and these
                bold barons probably held their lands under a feudal tenure to the king, as their
                nominal head, something like the arriere-ban of the old Germanic empire. Many
                things, in the course of Hindu literature, preserve some vague remembrance of the
                contest which naturally arose between the priests and the Kshatriyas, as these
                latter gradually became their rivals in intelligence and power; although all this
                lies in the background of the <cb/> past, at the era of the heroic poems. Between
                their era and that of the Vedas lay the stormy scene of these quarrels, which, if we
                may trust the uncertain rumors of tradition, at last became a deadly feud, in<note
                    type="authorial" resp="#h4" place="right">Vedas, there are <hi rend="underline"
                        >four:</hi> One was written 1400 B.C. others anterior</note> which the
                Brahmins obtained the victory. But at the time when mythic history commences, all
                this battle is over, and it is only alluded to in that casual way in which such old
                chronicles refer to things of past interest to their hearers. One of the <hi
                    rend="italic">avataras</hi>, or incarnations of Vishnu, represents him as coming
                to the aid of the Brahmins, against the persecutions of their rivals, under the form
                of Rama Jamadagnya, who slew all the Kshatriyas, and filled five lakes with their
                blood; and under this wild legend how much of human passion and crime may not lie
                quietly inurned! But all the especial details of this struggle lie far beyond the
                memory of history, in those remote regions of the past which, as Plutarch says, men
                people with prodigies and fables, just as geographers describe those countries which
                are unknown to them, as only tracts of sand, or frozen seas, or inaccessible
                mountains! Passing by these times, we arrive at that period when mythic history
                commences, and when the great events are no longer lost, but are made the subjects
                of the songs of the bards, and thus become <hi rend="italic">national</hi> memories. </p>

            <p>In these early times the bards are the historians, and the only annals are the family
                traditions of the nobles. From the earliest times, India seems to have been divided
                into numerous kingdoms, which were continually at war with one another; and each,
                having its ruling dynasty, had likewise its own traditions and heroes. This is the
                state in which Alexander found India, at the time of his invasion; and the same is
                Herodotus’ description (in Thalia, 98), "that there were many different tribes of
                the Indians, nor did they all speak one language;" and such too it appears in the
                heroic poems. A vague memory of a universal monarchy seems to linger here and there,
                but probably on no real foundation; or if ever it existed, it was merely a nominal
                supremacy over independent chiefs, who soon shook off even <span
                    rend="bracket-right" hand="#h4" xml:id="s13" from="#s13" to="#s14"/>the name of
                servitude.</p>

            <p>Two heroic poems remain to us of this period, the Ramayana and the Mahabharata, and
                in these lies all that we can ever know of India's early history. Of these the
                Ramayana is the most ancient, and doubtless the most genuine, as it has one main
                action running through it, which is seldom interrupted by any very long
                interpolations. But with the Mahabharata the case is widely different, as the main
                subject of the poem is almost<anchor xml:id="s14"/>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="mid.00011.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <note type="authorial" place="top" resp="#h4">Two most ancient Indian
                    poems,&#8212;the <hi rend="underline">Ramayana</hi>, of almost unknown
                    antiquity, one continued thread of action full of mixed episodes and
                    legends.</note>
                <note type="authorial" place="top left" resp="#h4">the <hi rend="underline"
                        >Mahabharata,</hi>
                </note>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">20</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top" rend="italic">Indian Epic Poetry.</fw>
                <fw type="date" place="top right">Oct.</fw>
                <cb/><span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h4" xml:id="s15" from="#s15" to="#s16"/>buried
                under an accumulation of all kinds of legends, which are inserted at every possible
                opportunity. The very bulk of the poem, which fills four closely-printed quarto
                volumes, and extends to nearly 200,000 lines, sufficiently proves that we have here
                no single epic, but rather a cycle of all the mythic lore of ancient India; and thus
                the Ramayana itself appears in one place abridged as an episode. However skilfully
                the heterogeneous elements are generally connected, and fitted into the main action,
                a great diversity of style prevails in various parts of the work, and occasionally
                the interpolations are self-evident. Thus a completely separate poem on mystical
                philosophy is put <note type="authorial" resp="#h4" place="left" rend="vertical"
                    corresp="#s15">Mahabharata</note>into the mouth of the incarnate Krishna, and
                addressed by him to the hero of the poem, just as two hostile armies are on the
                point of engaging; while, in another part, a dying hero dictates to his friends a
                whole canto on the duties of society! Again, long legends are continually being
                introduced on the slightest opening for them; and in the earlier books we have
                complete mythological histories of the universe, from Brahma's first waking, all
                inserted without any necessity, <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h4" xml:id="s17"
                    from="#s17" to="#s18"/>and completely stopping all progress <anchor xml:id="s16"
                /> in the epic action. Yet, however these may destroy the unity of the poem, they
                greatly add to its value; for thus the Mahabharata becomes a storehouse of almost
                inexhaustible mythic materials. At present it has been only superficially examined,
                but its immense extent offers subjects for all kinds of studies, and presents as
                wide a field as either Grecian or Roman antiquities. Some future scholar must deal
                with these traditions <anchor xml:id="s18"/>as Muller has with those of the
                Peloponnesus; and the invasion of the Brahminical tribes, and the history of their
                war with the aboriginals, may then perhaps stand out as clearly as the descent of
                the Heraclidæ and the Dorians. Hints and casual details respecting these events are
                scattered continually in both these poems, and they have only to be collected and
                arranged by <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h4" xml:id="s19" from="#s19"
                    to="#s20"/>"the cunning head," and one can hardly say what discoveries may not
                reward the labor. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h4">One common family of languages,
                    springing from one common though unknown stock, reaches from India (with
                    occasional interruptions) to England, and has been spoken by earth's
                    noblest</hi> races. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h4">The Arabians and Hebrews are
                    the only great nations who have not spoken dialects of this speech; India,
                    Persia, Greece, Rome, Sclavonia, and Scandinavia, and all the modern races which
                    have sprung from these, use common roots in the conversation of every day; and
                    it i</hi>s the Indo-teutonic tongues <hi rend="underline" hand="#h4">which are
                    identified</hi> with all European civilization. <anchor xml:id="s20"/><cb/>
                <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h4" xml:id="s21" from="#s21" to="#s22"/>Emerson has
                well called language "fossil poetry;" and thus, however strange it may seem to us,
                the words which fall thoughtlessly from our lips in the daily avocations of life,
                are no idle sounds, but magic symbols, which preserve for ever the first migrations
                of the race, and whose antiquity makes Greece and Rome appear but of
                    yesterday!<anchor xml:id="s22"/></p>
            <p>Yet although these epics have undergone great alterations since the times of their
                composers, underneath all the subsequent additions the original elements are still
                preserved; and careful criticism might perhaps separate the interpolations, and
                present the more genuine parts as a whole by themselves. The task, however, would be
                difficult, and perhaps as impracticable as it has proved in the Homeric poems. <hi
                    rend="underline" hand="#h4">For many ages it is certain that the works existed
                    only by oral tradition, and each rhapsodist added and altered at his pleasure,
                    or to suit the taste or vanity of the princely families whom he served.</hi> The
                measure of the poems, moreover, is of a somewhat fatal facility, and many
                rhapsodists would naturally be ambitious of mingling their own songs with those of
                their bards; and the habit of repetition would at once supply them with a vocabulary
                of epic phrases to suit their purpose. Whole chapters, in both poems, thus betray
                their origin by their barrenness of thought and laborious mimicry of the epic
                spirit, which, in the case of the old poets, had spontaneously burst out from the
                heart's fulness, like the free song of a child. But when the Indian <hi
                    rend="italic">Pisistratus</hi> arose, who collected these separate songs and
                reduced them to their present shape, the genuine and spurious were alike included,
                and no Hindu critic ever appears to have attempted to discriminate between them.
                    <span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h4" xml:id="s23" from="#s23" to="#s24"/>With
                regard to the Ramayana, it seems to have undergone two distinct revisions, one in
                Benares and the other in Bengal, and as the two were accomplished without any
                relation or reference to each other, they naturally present many variations in their
                texts. The same thoughts and events are generally preserved in both, but the words
                and order of the verses continually differ, as would naturally be the case where the
                revisions were made from the oral traditions of two different schools of
                rhapsodists, from each of which the poem had been undergoing a long series of
                alterations such as those we have suggested above.<ref target="#note2" xml:id="ref1"
                    >*</ref><anchor xml:id="s24"/></p>
            <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
            <note xml:id="note2" type="footnote" target="#ref1" anchored="true">*See Gorresio's
                preface to the first vol. of his edition of the Ramayana, where he argues the point
                with much ingenuity, though he sometimes mingles sophistry with his
                reasoning.</note>

            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="mid.00011.005.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h4" place="top right">Ramayana, by the poet Valmiki</note>
            <fw type="date" place="top left">1848.</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top" rend="italic">Indian Epic Poetry.</fw>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">21</fw>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h4" place="top right">Probably Valmiki and Homer were
                contemporaries&#8212;perhaps V. was the earlier of the two</note>

            <cb/>
            <p>We now proceed to give some account of the epics in themselves, <hi rend="italic">as
                    epics</hi>, or rather (since the term “epic” has become a dull, meaningless
                party-word, only associated with 'Blair’s Lectures,' and such unreadable
                criticisms), as the exponents and <hi rend="italic">audible voices</hi> of the
                spirit of their nation in its heroic age. In this respect, they have even a European
                interest; because, until they were discovered, the Homeric poems were without a
                parallel in the history of literature, and we had no means of comparing them with
                others of the same class, because other nations (if they ever possessed such) had
                    <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h4" xml:id="s25" from="#s25" to="#s26"/>lost
                all record of them in the lapse of time. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h4">These
                    Indian poems, however, in their <hi rend="italic">exterior form</hi>, are an
                    exact parallel; they occupy precisely the same place in the national heart, and
                    they equally stand alone in their class, separated by silent centuries from all
                    imitators</hi> or rivals, and springing <hi rend="underline" hand="#h4"
                    >apparently,</hi> like Minerva, in full maturity <hi rend="underline" hand="#h4"
                    >from their</hi> authors’ minds, with no record of any predecessors or
                    masters.<anchor xml:id="s26"/>
                <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h4" xml:id="s29" from="#s29" to="#s30"/><span
                    rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h4" xml:id="s27" from="#27" to="#s28"/>The subject
                of the Ramayana is the descent or <hi rend="italic">avatara</hi> of Vishnu, in human
                form, to save the world from Ravana, one of those demon-princes, who, in Hindu
                mythology, so often tyrannized over the world, and even extended their sway over the
                lower deities of the visible heaven.<anchor xml:id="s28"/> By dint of continued
                penances which in the Hindu religion are invested with a power over the gods, that
                reminds us of the Greek idea of fate, which enveloped even Jove in its toils),
                Ravana had obtained a promise from Brahma that no mortal being should destroy him;
                and on obtaining this boon, he throws off his disguise of asceticism, and from his
                island home, Lanka, or Ceylon, he spreads his despotism over all India, oppressing
                all the virtuous and defending all the impious through his dominions. At the
                commencement of the epic, we are introduced to the Hindu Olympus, and we find the
                gods assembled in solemn debate on the impending destruction of all faith and
                holiness in the world. Brahma's boon had given invincible power to the tyrant, and
                heaven is filled with dismay, until Vishnu, the preserver, comes forward, and
                resolves to assume a human form and thus overcome the enemy.<anchor xml:id="s30"
                /></p>
            <p>The scene then changes to earth, where Dasaratha, king of Oude (or Ayodhya, as it is
                called in the epic), after a life spent in deeds of virtue, finds his years drawing
                to a close without any heir to defend his old age or succeed to his crown. A holy
                    <hi rend="italic">Rishi</hi> or saint, reveals to him that he shall obtain his
                desires, on performing the <hi rend="italic">Aswamedha</hi>, or sacrifice of a
                horse, which occupies such a pre-eminent place in the Hindu religious <cb/>
                <span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h4" xml:id="s31" from="#s31" to="#s33"/>rites. The
                sacrifice is accordingly performed, and with the promised result. Dasaratha’s three
                wives become the mothers of four sons, all participating in the divine nature of
                Vishnu; but Rama, the eldest, is Vishnu himself. He is brought up at his father’s
                court, and educated by wise Brahmins; and while yet a youth, a great Rishi, named
                Viswamitra takes him away to his hermitage, to defend it against the attack of some
                demons who molested the sacrifices. Rama, on his arrival, overcomes them, and he
                next wins the hand of Sit&#0224;, the daughter of Janaca, by bending a bow which
                defied all her other suitors. He then returns to his father’s court, and is about to
                be appointed successor to the throne, when the mother of Bharata, one of his
                brothers, supplants him by an intrigue, and procures his banishment for fourteen
                years. Sit&#0224;, and his brother Lakshmana, share his exile; and we have next a
                long account of their wanderings, and we get many a pleasant glimpse of quiet
                hermitages, which they visited on their way,&#8212;such as doubtless<note
                    type="authorial" resp="#h4" place="right" rend="vertical">Ramayana
                    &#9756;</note> abounded from the earliest ages in Hindostan, to offer their
                shelter to those contemplative minds which fled from the tumults of their times. It
                was in one of these hermitages<ref target="#note3">*</ref> that Alexander found the
                Gymnosophists, when, in reply to his inquiries, they only stamped on the ground, as
                a silent admonition to the conqueror of his mortality. At length the three royal
                exiles settle on the banks of the Godaveri, in the forest of Dandaka, which spread
                over a vast portion of the Deccan. Here Rama and his brother spend their time in
                hunting wild beasts and driving away the demons; and in one adventure they mutilated
                the demon-sister of Ravana himself. The tyrant, on hearing of the outrage, resolves
                to avenge himself, and he comes to Rama's cottage and carries off Sit&#0224;, in her
                husband's absence, to his island palace. Rama and his brother search in vain on
                their return, and they wander over the peninsula without finding any trace of her.
                At last, in their wanderings, they meet with a tribe of satyrs or apes, and Rama
                restores Sugriva their king to his throne, of which he had been deprived by his
                brother Bali; and in gratitude, Sugriva sends out a host of his subjects to search
                for Sit&#0224;. After long and fruitless travel, one named Hanumat discovers her
                abode: he crosses the strait, and at last sees her and speaks with her, and then
                returns with the glad tidings to Rama, who proceeds with an army of apes to the
                southernmost point<anchor xml:id="s33"/>
                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
                <note type="footnote" place="bottom" xml:id="note3">Eν λειμωνι, ΐναπερ άντοΐς
                    διατρίβαι.&#8212;Arrian vii.</note>
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="mid.00011.006.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <note type="authorial" place="top" resp="#h4">
                    <list>
                        <item>The Athenian <add rend="insertion" place="supralinear"
                                >historical</add> "pet" was Theseus</item>
                        <item>The
                            Dorian&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;Hercules</item>
                        <item>The Hindostaner<add rend="unmarked" place="supralinear"
                                >Brahminic</add>&#8212;Rama</item>
                        <item>The French&#8212;Napoleon</item>

                        <cb/>

                        <item>Who was the Roman?</item>
                        <item>Scandinavian?</item>
                        <item>Briton?<add rend="unmarked" place="inline" hand="#h3">&#8212;</add>
                            Arthur <add rend="unmarked" place="inline" hand="#h3"><unclear
                                    cert="medium" resp="#slg" reason="illegible"
                                >Alfred</unclear>?</add></item>
                    </list></note><anchor xml:id="s35"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top left"><handShift new="#h1"/>22</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top" rend="italic">Indian Epic Poetry.</fw>
                <fw type="date" place="top right">Oct.</fw>
                <span rend="bracket-left" hand="h4" xml:id="s63" from="#s63" to="#s64"/><cb/>of
                India: and the <choice>
                    <orig>Hindoo</orig>
                    <reg>Hindu</reg>
                </choice> sailor will yet point out to the traveller the remains of <hi
                    rend="italic">Rama's Bridge</hi>, built with rocks, which the apes threw into
                the sea; as a range of rocks does run into the sea, in high broken masses, above
                Cape Comorin, and is apparently met by a corresponding line from the coast of
                Ceylon, while between them lie impassable sandbanks, as if in old days a neck of
                land had connected the island with the continent. Rama passes with his army over
                this Titanic bridge, and after a fierce conflict, he kills Ravana, disperses his
                forces, and rescues Sit&#0224; from her imprisonment. The word of Brahma himself
                pronounces that she is pure, in spite of all Ravana's solicitations and threats; and
                Rama returns with his wife to Ayodhya, and receives the kingdom from his brother,
                who resigns it to him as the lawful possessor.</p>
            <anchor xml:id="s64"/>
            <p>Such is a brief sketch of the story; but of course each of these events branches out
                into numerous episodes. Under its wild fable there doubtless lies an historical
                basis; and modern scholars have conjectured that the subject is the introduction of
                the Brahminical religion into the peninsula, the aboriginal inhabitants being
                distorted by the mist of tradition into demons, and the apes representing some wild
                but more friendly tribe. But, hitherto, the poem has not been <hi rend="italic"
                    >critically</hi> studied; only half of it has as yet been published: and a
                fatality appears to attend all attempts to edit the whole. Three editions have
                successively appeared; the first by Carey and Marshman, the second by Schlegel, and
                the last by Gorresio; but the two former only reached to the close of the second
                canto, and the third (which was published under royal auspices at Paris, and nearly
                completed the fourth canto), appears to be now abruptly terminated; and the <note
                    type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="left-margin">Alexander invaded India 327
                    B.C.</note>poet Valmiki must wait for some more fortunate editor, or more quiet
                times. Perhaps, when the whole poem is printed, and facilities are furnished for its
                study, Sanscrit scholars may unravel the threads of truth which run through its web
                of fiction; and many questions of deep interest will rise to <span rend="singleLine"
                    hand="#h4" xml:id="s61" from="#s61" to="#s62"/>attract their attention. Two, in
                particular, will invite them&#8212;the sources of the legends, and the age of the
                poem itself. Are the legends which are here preserved to us, the creations of
                Valmiki's imagination, from whose soul, to use Schlegel's words, poetry
                involuntarily burst out "like a fountain from the living rock;" or are they derived
                from other sources (of greater or less antiquity), and incorporated in after times
                with his poem?<anchor xml:id="s62"/> At present, such questions as these are
                premature; but one important element suggests itself, which has hitherto <cb/> been
                but little examined, viz., how far are the legends of a <hi rend="italic"
                    >Kshatriya</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Brahminic</hi> origin? Our own impression
                is, that the poem, in its original state, was rather an heroic song or series of
                songs, of the Kshatriya tribe, and that in later times the Brahmins revised them,
                and added the numerous passages which inculcate their tenets and uphold their
                authority. Many of the old Kshatriya legends can still be distinctly traced; and
                thus, in the first book, we have a battle between Rama (who is completely a
                Kshatriya, and doubtless was once the favourite hero of the tribe, like the Dorian
                Hercules, or Athenian Theseus) and Rama Jamadagnya, the Brahminic hero, whom we have
                spoken of above; and the Kshatriya champion drives <choice><sic>hi</sic><corr>his</corr></choice> rival from India and deprives him of all his power. Again, we have
                another legend, which describes how a Kshatriya, named Viswamitra, by dint of
                austerities, became one of the Brahmins, in spite of their utmost opposition. At
                present these and other legends of a similar kind, lie buried under a mass of
                interpolations and Brahminical alterations; but some future critic will reduce these
                heterogeneous elements into order, and separate the ancient and genuine from that
                which has been superadded to it, to suit the pretensions or the vanity of later
                times.</p>
            <p>In a similar way, we are ignorant of the date of the poem, or rather of the era to
                which its older parts belong. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h4">Probably Valmiki and
                    Homer were contemporaries; perhaps the Hindu was the earlier of the two, and
                    sang his song while that Ilion was a reality, which to Homer rose in the
                    background of two or three generations.</hi> Our limits forbid us to enter into
                any detailed proof, nor indeed could any be quite satisfactory; the best arguments
                for its age are found in the poem itself, and the habits and manners which it
                describes. <span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h4" xml:id="s37" from="#s37" to="#s38"
                />Thus, the burning of widows on the funeral piles of their husbands, which the
                Greeks describe as an old custom, when Alexander invaded India, B.C. 327, is utterly
                unknown in the Ramayana; and one fact like this speaks<anchor xml:id="s38"/>
                volumes. In such poems as the Ramayana and the Iliad, we instinctively feel that
                they belong to the earlier world: we enter them as we enter a house in
                Pompeii&#8212;the colours may still seem fresh, and no mark of decay remind us of
                their age; but we feel that they belong not to <hi rend="italic">us</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">ours</hi>, and a gulf of ages lies between us and our objects!</p>
            <p>We now proceed to give a few extracts, for our readers to judge of Valmiki's merits
                as a <hi rend="italic">poet</hi>; and those of them who may wish to cultivate a
                further acquaintance with his <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="mid.00011.007.jpg"
                    type="recto"/>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h4" place="top">The style of a great poem must flow on
                    "unhasting and unresting."</note>
                <fw type="date" place="top left">1848.</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top" rend="italic">Indian Epic Poetry.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">23</fw>
                <cb/>poem (without the labour of studying it in the original), we would refer to
                Schlegel's <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h4" xml:id="s39" from="#s39"
                    to="#s40"/>felicitous Latin translation of the first book, &#8212;a work, which
                is now equally stopped with his publication of the text itself. Valmiki's style, as
                might be expected, greatly resembles that of Homer; <hi rend="underline" hand="#h4"
                    >each flows on in that "unhasting and unresting" continuity, <span
                        rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h4" xml:id="s41" from="#s41" to="#s42"/>which
                    only belongs to the heroic age of a <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h4"
                        xml:id="s43" from="#s43" to="#s44"/>literature; in later times men lose the
                    old <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h4" xml:id="s45" from="#s45" to="#s46"
                    />openheartedness and confidence, and fence themselves with suspicion and
                    caution; and<anchor xml:id="s40"/> in a similar way their poetry loses its
                    freeness and ease, and stoops to the niceties of syntax, or the art of the
                    rhetorician.</hi></p>
            <anchor xml:id="s42"/>
            <anchor xml:id="s44"/>
            <anchor xml:id="s46"/>
            <p>In comparing Valmiki with Homer, let us not be misunderstood as placing them on a
                level with each other; in poetical merit the Ramayana is as far inferior to the
                Iliad, as the national character of the Hindu to that of the Greek; but apart from
                their poetry, and looking more at its outward dress and decorations, its language
                and subjects and mythology, no one can deny that there exists a strong family
                likeness between them. The same freeness of expression characterizes each; the words
                flow carelessly from the poet's lips, as the natural voice of his emotions; and the
                open fullness of his heart faithfully mirrors itself in his song. In each, too, we
                find the same repetition of favourite phrases and images; <hi rend="italic">τον δ'
                    υπαμειβομενοζ</hi> hardly occurs more frequently than <hi rend="italic">srulwá
                    tad vachanam teshá</hi>; and both poets abound with that vivid fellow-feeling
                with nature, which so strongly characterizes the half-civilized age of an heroic
                people. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h4">The <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h4"
                        xml:id="s49" from="#s49" to="#s50"/><span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h4"
                        xml:id="s47" from="#s47" to="#s48"/>gigantic peaks of the Himalayas are ever
                    present to Valmiki's mind, as Ida and Olympus to Homer's;</hi> and <hi
                    rend="underline" hand="#h4">his poem reflects a <span rend="bracket-left"
                        hand="#h4" xml:id="s51" from="#s51" to="#s52"/>thousand influences from his
                    country's vast scales of geography and scenery.</hi><anchor xml:id="s48"/> It is
                to this perhaps, that we may trace his huge creations and mythology; nurtured amidst
                those wild scenes, his imagination dwells on<anchor xml:id="s50"/><anchor
                    xml:id="s52"/><cb/>
                <span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h4" xml:id="s53" from="#s53" to="#s54"/>the
                gigantic and superhuman; and Homer's Jupiter sinks into insignificance beside his
                Vishnu and Siva, just as Homer's mountains are but hillocks beneath the tremendous
                heights of the Dhwawalaghiri range!</p>
            <p>Our first extract shall be the sections describing the capture of Sitá by Ravana, the
                demon-king of Ceylon, which forms a grand episode in the Ramayana, and is, in fact,
                the <hi rend="italic">nodus</hi> where the plot begins to thicken.</p>
            <p>Rama has been banished from his father's court, and dwells with his wife Sitá and his
                brother Lakshmana, in the forest-wilds of the Deccan. Here, in the course of one of
                their adventures, the two brothers mutilate Suparnaka, the sister of Ravana, and the
                demon-monarch resolves on revenge. He accordingly takes one of his followers, and
                they repair to the forest where Rama lives. Here his follower transforms himself
                into a golden deer, and lures Rama from the cottage in its pursuit, who leaves his
                brother Lakshmana behind, to guard Sitá, with strict injunctions to stay with her
                until his return. He then follows the deer, and after a long chase (which is
                described with all the charms of poetry by the Hindu bard), he transfixes it with an
                arrow, and the demon expires with a loud cry, "<hi rend="italic">O Lakshmana, save
                    me!</hi>" This cry is only a stratagem to lure away Lakshmana from the cottage,
                in order that Sit&#0224; may be left as Ravana's prey; and the feint succeeds.
                Sit&#0224;, in agony, conjures Lakhmana to fly to his brother's aid; at first he is
                reluctant to leave her; but at last she overrules his misgivings, and prevails upon
                him, by her entreaties and reproaches, to set out. It is here that our extract
                commences, which we present in a <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h4"
                    xml:id="s55" from="#s55" to="#s56"/>rhymed dress, <hi rend="underline"
                    hand="#h4">of the same measure as the original;</hi> the only alterations we
                have made being occasional omissions, where the details would only have added to the
                    length<anchor xml:id="s56"/> of the extract without increasing its spirit.</p>
            <cb/>
            <lg type="linegroup" n="I." rend="centered">
                <l>"Lakshmana, grieved at Sit&#0224;'s words, no longer undecided stood,</l>
                <l>But hied him forth in Rama's search, and left her in the lonely wood.</l>
                <l>With many a dark presentiment fast gathering round, and unknown fear,</l>
                <l>In the deep forest-paths he roved, like one who roves he wists not where.</l>
                <l>And now that thus the golden deer had lured the brothers both away,</l>
                <l>Ravana deemed within himself the hour was come to seize his prey.</l>
                <l>There he beheld the dame forlorn, left in that cottage all alone,</l>
                <l>As upon earth is left a gloom, when meet eclipsed the sun and moon:</l>
                <l>And while upon her form he gazed, so fair in such a dreary spot,</l>
                <l>Thus to himself the tyrant spoke, as he surveyed the lonely cot: </l>
                <l>'While she is left with husband none, with brother none to hear her cries,</l>
                <l>Why longer stay? the time is come to claim and seize my rightful prize.'</l>
                <l>Thus having pondered in his heart, Ravana left his hiding-place,</l>
                <l>And walked where Sit&#0224; sorrowing sat; clothed in a wandering beggar's
                    dress,</l>
                <l>Threadbare and red his garment was, th' ascetic's tuft of hair he wore,</l>
                <l>And the three sticks and waterpot in his accursed hand he bore.</l>
            </lg>
            <!-- <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="mid.00011.007a.jpg" type="verso"/>
                    <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">24</fw>
                    <fw type="header" place="top" rend="italic">Indian Epic Poetry.</fw>
                    <fw type="date" place="top right">Oct.</fw>
                    <l>As he drew near, the lofty trees, that over Janasthana grow,</l>
                        <l>And every twining creeper-plant which hangs and climbs from bough 
                        to bough,</l>
                    <l>And every bird and every beast stood motionless with silent dread,</l>
                        <l>Nor dared the summer wind to breathe, nor shake a leaflet overhead.</l>
                        <l>Over Godavery's bright waves a shiver darkened as he passed,</l>
                        <l>And bird and beast in terror fled, as on he came in evil haste,</l>
                        <l>With his black heart and beggar's garb, disguised and hidden as he was,</l>
                        <l>Like a dark well, whose unseen brink is overgrown with waving grass.</l>
                        <l>Hard by the cottage-door he stood, and gazed upon his victim fair,</l>
                        <l>As there she sat in woful plight, lost in a maze of grief and fear,</l>
                        <l>Reft of her husband, and with gloom o'ershadowed like a moonless sky,</l>
                        <l>Weeping alone in silent woe, and musing o'er that unknown cry.</l>
                        <l>On her he gazed, and that fair face seemed ever fairer and more 
                        bright;</l>
                    <l>And his stern eye, awhile absorbed, lingered as loth to lose the sight.</l>
                        <l>Fierce passion woke within his heart, until at length, with softened air,</l> 
                        <l>He thus addressed her as she sat, shining, a golden statue there:</l>
                        <l>'Oh thou, that shinest like a tree with summer blossoms overspread,</l>
                        <l>Wearing that woven kusa robe, and lotus garland on thy head,</l>
                        <l>Why art thou dwelling here alone, here in this dreary forest's shade,</l>
                        <l>Where range at will all beasts of prey, and demons prowl in every 
                        glade?</l>
                    <l>Wilt thou not leave thy cottage home, and roam the world, which stretches wide;</l>
                        <l>See the fair cities which men build, and all their gardens, and their pride?</l>
                        <l>Why longer, fair one, dwell'st thou here, feeding on roots and sylvan fare,</l>
                        <l>When thou might'st dwell in palaces, and earth's most costly jewels wear?</l>
                        <l>Fearest thou not the forest gloom, which darkens round on every side?</l>
                    <l>Who art thou, say, and whose and whence, and wherefore dost thou here abide?'</l>
                    <l>When first these words of Ravana broke upon sorrowing Sit&#225;'s ear,</l>
                        <l>She started up, and lost herself in wonderment and doubt and fear;</l>
                        <l>But soon her gentle loving heart threw oft' suspicion and surmise,</l>
                        <l>And slept again in confidence, lulled by the mendicant's disguise.</l>
                        <l>'Hail, holy Brahmin!' she exclaimed; and, in her guileless purity,</l>
                        <l>She gave a welcome to her guest with courteous hospitality.</l>
                        <l>Water she brought to wash his feet, and food to satisfy his need,</l>
                        <l>Full little dreaming in her heart what fearful guest she had received.</l></lg>
            <lg type="stanza" n="II." rend="centered"><l>Then having pondered on his words, after a pause she made reply,</l> 
                <l>And in her guileless confidence, unbosomed all her history;</l>
                <l>How Rama won her for his bride, and brought her to his father's home,</l>
                <l>And how another's jealousy had cast them forth, the woods to roam;</l>
                <l>All her full heart she opened then, and all her husband's praise she spoke,</l>
                <l>And long she lingered o'er the tale, and all the memories which it woke;</l>
                <l>'And thou too, Brahmin,' she exclaimed, 'thy name and lineage wilt 
                thou say?</l>
                <l>And wherefore thou hast left thy land, in pathless Dandaka to stray?</l> 
                <l>Ere long my husband will return&#8212;to him are holy wanderers dear,</l>
                <l>And fair the welcome which he gives, whene'er their pathway leads 
                them here.'</l>
                <l>Then answered her the demon-king, 'My name and lineage thou shalt hear,</l>
                    <l>And wherefore in this guise I come, and wander in this forest drear.</l>
                    <l>Thee, Sit&#225;, am I come to see,&#8212;I, at whose name heaven's armies flee;</l>
                    <l>The demon monarch of the earth, I, Ravana, am come to thee!</l>
                    <l>I come to woo thee for my queen; in Lanka stands my palace home,</l>
                    <l>High on a mountain's forehead built, while round it breaks the ocean's 
                    foam.</l>
                <l>There like dark clouds my demons stand, my mandates through the earth to bear;</l>
                    <l>There shalt thou worshipped be like me, and all my world-dominion share.'</l>
                    <l>In sudden wrath outburst she then, the wife of Raghu's princely son,</l>
                <l>And gushed indignant from her lips the answer to that evil one ;</l>
                <l>'<hi rend="italic">Me</hi> wouldst thou woo to be thy queen, or dazzle with thine empire's shine?</l>
                    <l>And didst thou dream that Rama's wife could stoop to such a prayer as thine?</l>
                    <l><hi rend="italic">I</hi>, who can look on Rama's face, and know that there my husband stands,</l>
                <l>My Rama, whose high chivalry is blazoned through a hundred lands!</l>
                <l>What! shall the jackal think to tempt the lioness to mate with him?</l>
                <l>Or did the king of Lanka's isle build upon such an idle dream?</l>
                    <l>He who would enter Rama's home, and think to tear his wife away,</l>
                    <l>Might beard the lion in its den, and rob its hunger of its prey;</l> 
                    <l>Or safer far her new-born cubs from the fierce tigress might he wrest,</l>
                    <l>Or in his garment wrap the flame, and fold and nurse it to his breast!'</l>
                    <l>Stung to the heart by Sit&#225;'s words, in silence Ravana folds his hands,</l>
                    <l>And at that lonely cottage door a mendicant no longer stands;</l>
                    <l>'Tis but a moment, and behold! bursting from out the assumed disguise,</l>
                    <l>Before her towers the demon-king, with his black brow and glaring eyes,</l></lg> -->

            <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="mid.00011.008.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">26</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top" rend="italic">Indian Epic Poetry.</fw>
            <fw type="date" place="top right">Oct.</fw>

            <lg type="stanza" rend="centered">
                <l>And with the shoals of fishes and tortoises, and with the troops of
                    porpoises,</l>
                <l>As they flashed falling, and fallen, the earth gleamed on every side.</l>
                <l>The godlike Rishis, and Gandarvas, and the Genii, and the heavenly hosts,</l>
                <l>All stood gazing on the river, as it rushed down from heaven upon the earth.</l>
                <l>There, too, stood the gods themselves, with their city-equalling chariots,</l>
                <l>And some upon horses and elephants, while others came flying through the air.</l>
                <l>With the meeting hosts of heaven, and the splendour of their ornaments,</l>
                <l>The cloudless air shone as having an hundred suns;</l>
                <l>And with the troops of porpoises, and snakes, and the fishes in their falling
                    play,</l>
                <l>The sky seemed coruscating as with flung lightnings;</l>
                <l>And with the white foam of the waters spreading in a thousand directions,</l>
                <l>And with the flocks of waterfowl, the air seemed filled as with autumnal
                    clouds.</l>
                <l>Here the waters rushed swiftly, there they wandered in mazy paths,</l>
                <l>Here they opened into an expanse, there they flowed softly with idle ripples;</l>
                <l>And there, with a fiercer current, wave repelled by wave</l>
                <l>Flashed as it rose aloft, and then again sank upon the ground.</l>
                <l>Thus, falling from Sancara's peaks, falling down to the earth,</l>
                <l>Shone the bright waters of Ganga, pure from all spot or stain."</l>
            </lg>

            <cb/>
            <p>Surely it was a true <hi rend="italic">poet's</hi> imagination, which could paint
                this scene upon the blank canvas of the past. Ganga's sacred river, which
                continually rises before Valmiki's mind, here seems almost to flow into his song,
                and mingle the eternal roll of her waters with its language! Well may we repeat, on
                rising from the perusal of such passages as these, Schlegel's version of the proud
                prophecy, which Brahma addresses to Valmiki in the opening of the poem,</p>

            <lg type="stanza" rend="italic">
                <l>Dum stabunt montes, campis dura flumina current,</l>
                <l>Usque tuum toto carmen celebrabitur orbe!"</l>
            </lg>

            <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h4" xml:id="s57" from="#s57" to="#s58"/>
            <p>We now proceed to give some account of the other epic poem which is preserved to us,
                and which, as we have shown above, is rather a cycle of poems, than one continued
                poem in itself. Tradition reports that the author's name was Vyasa, but as this
                appellation would signify the "arranger" or "disposer," it is probably only an
                etymological myth to imply that at some unknown period this collection of ancient
                poems was <hi rend="italic">arranged</hi> into its present form; and it is a
                somewhat singular coincidence that<anchor xml:id="s58"/> Homer's name has been
                analyzed into the same signification (δμου and δοω), and thus corresponds precisely
                with the Sanscrit Vyasa. Of course, from this very fact, it is obvious that we know
                nothing of the age of the <hi rend="italic">Mahabharata</hi>, except from internal
                evidence; and at present this has been but little investigated. Many of the poems of
                which it is composed betray evident marks of a later origin; while others, on the
                contrary would refer us back to the earliest times; and there is as great a
                difference in the poetical merit as in the style. The earlier poems are probably
                contemporary with the Ramayana, but the greater part of it must be assigned to the
                following ages, and the poem, perhaps, only assumed its present shape a few
                centuries before our era. At the time, however, when it was thus arranged, <cb/> the
                songs themselves had become national memories; and the poets of that day were
                contented to draw the subjects of their works from its vast storehouse of legendary
                materials, instead of inventing for themselves. Thus the groundwork of Calidasa's
                play, Sacontala (which is well known by Sir W. Jones's translation), is taken from
                an episode in the first book of the Mahabharata, just as the Greek dramatists drew
                their subjects from the old world of the Homeric and Cyclic poems.</p>
            <p>The <hi rend="italic">Balabharata</hi>, or Romaic book, which stands at the head of
                our article, is a translation into modern Greek of a Sanscrit epitome of the
                Mahabharata ; and though the epitome, in itself, is but a poor shadow of the
                original, how much of extrinsic interest is added to it by the place where it is
                published! Surely the appearance of such a book in Athens must be an era in modern
                Greek literature, and we hail the augury. If the minds of modern Greeks are
                beginning to turn to the old Indian world, whence their first ancestors probably
                derived so much,&#8212;may we not hope, that a second growth of the same influence
                may spring up? <hi rend="italic">Ex Oriente Lux,</hi> (as the motto of the Oriental
                Translation Society tells us, with its beautiful vignette); and perhaps the light
                which rose in old ages in India, and flung its beams through unknown media upon
                Egypt and Greece, in their heroic times, may cast a reflection upon Greece even in
                her degeneracy, and wake something of that lost spirit, which once was her glory,
                and has rendered her history one of the brightest pages in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >fasti</hi> of what man has done!</p>
            <p>The present work is translated by Demetrius Galanus, an Athenian, and it is prefaced
                by some prolegomena, which are intended to introduce its Romaic readers to Sanscrit
                literature; and contain many interesting remarks, especially where the <pb
                    xml:id="leaf006r" facs="mid.00011.009.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h4" place="top">Vyasa, poet of the Mahabharata</note>
                <fw type="date" place="top left">1848</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top" rend="italic">Indian Epic Poetry.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">27</fw>
                <cb/>author compares the Indian epics with the Homeric poems of his own country. The
                translation is in that <hi rend="italic">half</hi> ancient Greek, which seems now
                the most fashionable form of Romaic; and at the foot of every page are many really
                valuable notes to illustrate Hindu mythology, as well as the difficulties of the
                context. The work is dedicated to King Otho, and is published at the expense of
                Joannes Duma. If the present volume succeeds, we may probably have some further
                translations by the same author; and in the present dearth of writers and thinkers
                in Greece, such a series could hardly fail of producing a marked influence on the
                minds of their readers, and perhaps might waken up some ambition to imitate or
                surpass them!</p>
            <p>We now return to the Mahabharata, the subject of which is the long civil war between
                the sons of two brothers, Pandu and Dhritarashtra, for the throne of India. The
                elder brother, Pandu, is a leper, and thereby incapable of succeeding to the throne;
                but his claims descend to his five children&#8212;Yudishthira, Bhima, Arjuna,
                Nakula, and Sahadeva, who are the heroes of the poem. Their uncle, Dhritarashtra, is
                blind, but his numerous family of sons exercise the regal power in his name; and the
                eldest of these, Duryodhana, is distinguished for his hostility to his cousins, who
                are brought up at their uncle's court after their father's death. The young princes
                are continually quarrelling, even in their boyhood, and many instances of their
                rivalry are related; but as they grow up, this spirit becomes still more manifest.
                At last Dhritarashtra is persuaded to divide his empire equally between his sons and
                his nephews; and for some time the rivalry seemed over; until at last, one day, at a
                great festival, Yudishthira engages at play with Duryodhana, and with that
                inveterate passion for gambling, which has always characterized the Hindus, stakes
                his kingdom, his brothers and himself, and loses. It is at last agreed that he and
                his brothers shall resign their kingdom, and pass twelve years in banishment; and
                the long account of their adventures in their forest life is one of the most
                interesting parts of the poem. Many episodes occur here, and several stories are
                related to the brothers; amongst others, that of Nala, which has been so well
                translated by Milman, and that of Savitri, which has been translated into German by
                Bopp. At the close of their term of banishment, both parties prepare for war; and
                all the various kings of India and the surrounding countries join one or the other,
                as allies. Krishna (who is an incarnation of Vishnu, like Rama in the Ramayana),
                takes the side of the <cb/> Pandavas, and by his counsel and personal aid, greatly
                contributes to their success. The war is fierce and bloody, and many chieftains fall
                on both sides; but at last Duryodhana is killed by Bhima, and Yudishthira gains the
                long-contested throne. The conclusion of the poem will be given hereafter.</p>
            <p>The characters of the five brothers in the Mahabharata are drawn with an
                individuality which is very unusual in oriental poetry. They each have their
                distinguished traits, which are often painted with much discrimination and even
                delicacy of touch in the lighter shades; and yet there evidently runs a family
                likeness through them all. To the European reader, Arjuna, the third brother, is the
                most interesting, and approaches the nearest to our ideal of chivalry: many of his
                exploits remind us of Arthur's knights, or Charlemagne's paladins; and it is he who
                wins Draupadi as his wife, in a tournament, where her father had offered her hand as
                the conqueror's prize. With the Hindus, however, Yudishthira, the eldest, is the
                favorite: his cold, passionless heroism is with them the <hi rend="italic">beau
                    ideal</hi> of humanity; and he moves through the poem in a calm majesty of
                self-possession, as if far above all the weaknesses of man, while the sorrows and
                joys which chequer his life</p>
            <lg type="stanza">
                <l>"Viennent toujours glisser sur son être insensible,</l>
                <l>Comme des gouttes d'eau sur un marbre poli!"</l>
            </lg>
            <p>The sons of Dhritarashtra are, on the contrary, little distinguished from one
                another; their individual traits are lost in their intensity of hatred towards their
                rivals; and their misfortunes and fall excite no regret. These are the evil genii of
                the story; and indeed, under the whole poem, there runs a wild, half-unconscious
                belief (which only occasionally breaks out in a tangible shape), that the whole war
                is only a visible bas-relief sculpture of the old war between the evil principle and
                the gods. They have descended to wage their war in mortal form upon earth; but the
                causes of their jealousies lie deep in the abyss of the past; and "war in heaven"
                was the secret which Nature read in the colossal cypher of the Pandavas and
                Dhartarashtras. To the contemplative Hindu the old strife bore this mournful
                meaning; just as Stasimus, the cyclic poet, says of the siege of Ilion,</p>
            
            <lg type="stanza">
                <l><hi rend="italic">"Ην δτε μνρία φύλα κατά χθόνα πλαζόμεν’ άνδρών</hi></l>
                <l><hi rend="italic">…Bαθνστέρνσυ πλάτος άιης.</hi></l>
                <l><hi rend="italic">Zευς δέ ίδων έλέησε, καί έν πυκινάις πραπίδεσσι</hi></l>
                <l><hi rend="italic">σύνθετο κσνφίσσαι έλέησε, καί έν πυκινάις πραπίδεσσι</hi></l>
                <l><hi rend="italic">ούνθετο κονφίσσι άνδρών παμβώτορα γάιαν</hi></l>
                <l><hi rend="italic">ριπίσσας πολέμον μεγάλην έριν Ιλιάκοιο,</hi></l>
                <l><hi rend="italic">όφρα κενώσειεν θανάτω βάρος όί δ ένί Τροίη</hi></l>
                <l><hi rend="italic">ήρωες κτείνοντο’ Διός δ έτελέιετο βόνλη."</hi></l>
            </lg>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="mid.00011.010.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">28</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top" rend="italic">Indian Epic Poetry</fw>
            <fw type="date" place="top right">Oct.</fw>
            <cb/>
            <p>But amongst the cruel opponents of the Pandavas, there is one round whom the author
                of the Mahabharata throws all the charms of his poetry; and several of the most
                touching episodes relate to his history. Karna was the half-brother of the Pandavas,
                being the son of their mother Pritha, before her marriage with Pandu; he was exposed
                on the banks of the Jumna, and found by the charioteer of king Sura, who brings him
                up as his own child. Being of course ignorant of his real parentage, he joins the
                party of the sons of Dhritarashtra, and vows to kill Arjuna. On the eve of one of
                the great battles, he is recognized by his mother, who goes to the camp and reveals
                herself, and implores him to leave Duryodhana and join his brothers in their
                rightful cause. But the dictates of honour were imperative; he had vowed fidelity to
                his party, and although he knew from omens and prophecies and his own presentiments
                that his present friends were fated to fall, and himself to perish with them, Karna
                sorrowfully but firmly abides by his plighted word. With this <cb/> self-devotion
                and fidelity, Kama rises a true hero from amidst his evil associates; the heroic
                character which has always some affinity with self denial and endurance, flings the
                same halo round the Hindu chief as round the son of Peleus in Grecian story, and an
                epic dignity envelopes every event of his history.</p>
            <p>From among the countless legends and <choice><sic>episcodes</sic><corr>episodes</corr></choice> of the Mahabharata, it is difficult to
                make a selection of quotations, so many favorite passages rise to remembrance that
                the mind feels quite bewildered with the variety which offers itself. We give but a
                few of the pieces which suggest themselves, and we doubt not our readers will admire
                their novelty as well as their beauty.</p>
            <p>Here is a description of Draupadi, left alone in the cottage of the Pandavas, while
                they are all absent in pursuit of game in the forest wilds. A king passes by with
                his retinue; and one could almost think it was Spenser's fancy which drew the
                following picture.</p>
            <lg type="stanza">
                <l>"There he beheld the glorious wife of the Pandava,</l>
                <l>Standing at her cottage door in the lonely wood;</l>
                <l>Shining in her beauty, and wearing the loveliest form,</l>
                <l>And lighting up the forest glade, as the lightning a dark blue cloud."</l>
            </lg>
            <cb/>
            <p>Here, too, is another of a similar kind. A tournament is about to take place, and the
                poet has finely described all the noise and tumult of the spectators; when suddenly
                <cb/>the Brahmin enters the arena, and the poet's art seems to hush the mind of the
                reader, as his appearance hushed the din of the crowd.</p>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h4" target="#lg1">&#9758;</note>
            <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h4" from="#lg1" to="#s65"/>
            <lg xml:id="lg1" type="stanza">
                <l>"With the noise of the musical instruments, and the eager voices of the
                    spectators,</l>
                <l>The din of the assembly rose up like the roaring of the sea;</l>
                <l>When lo! wearing his white raiment, and the white sacrificial cord,</l>
                <l>With his snow-white hair and his silvery beard, and the white garland round his
                    head,</l>
                <l>Into the midst of the arena slowly walked
                    the Brahmin with his son,</l>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h5" place="left" target="#hi1">?moon</note>
                <l>Like the <hi rend="underline" hand="#h5" xml:id="hi1">sun</hi> with the planet Mars in a
                    cloudless sky!<anchor xml:id="s65"></anchor></l>
            </lg>
            <cb/>
            <p>To understand the full meaning of many of these outbursts of poetry, we must enter
                into some of the Hindu superstitions and feelings; and thus to appreciate the beauty
                of the following, we must allow ourselves to feel something of the Hindu's awe for
                <cb/> those vast periods of time which heaven's dial-plate measures out in his
                mythology: the Yugas and Brahma's years, which sink our generations into mere
                moments. Such lines as these will then seem like trumpet blasts,&#8212;where he
                describes a fierce <hi rend="italic">melée</hi>,&#8212;</p>
            <lg type="stanza">
                <l>"Like two stormy-waved oceans, <hi rend="italic">tossed by the winds of a Yuga's
                        end."</hi></l>
            </lg>
            <cb/>
            <p>How completely also does the following carry us away to the old times, before modern
                discoveries had mapped out every coast <cb/> in the world, when the world's end was
                still a terror to the seaman, and unknown monsters gambolled in the sea:&#8212;</p>
            <lg type="stanza">
                <l>"Like a gem-laden ship at the end of the ocean, wrecked on a Leviathan's
                    back."</l>
            </lg>
            <cb/>
            <p>One of the most beautiful stories of the Mahabharata is that of Savitri, which for
                depth of pathos surpasses even Admetus and Alcestis. We have only room for a brief
                sketch of it, but it well deserves to be translated entire. The plan of the story is
                <cb/> simple enough, but the filling up of its details displays the poet's master
                hand. Savitri, the daughter of King Aswapatri, is in love with Satyavat, the son of
                an old blind hermit, who was once a king, but has long lost his throne. A holy <hi
                    rend="italic">Rishi</hi> warns her of 
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf007r" facs="mid.00011.011.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="date" place="top left">1848</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top" rend="italic">Indian Epic Poetry.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">29</fw>
                <cb/>the fated sorrow of the marriage, for Satyavat is doomed to die young, and only
                one <cb/> more year remains of his life. Savitri, however, has made her choice.</p>
            <lg type="stanza">
                <l>"Let his years be few or many, high or humble be his lot,</l>
                <l><hi rend="italic">Him</hi> my inmost heart has chosen, and again it chooses
                    not."</l>
            </lg>
            <p>The lovers are therefore married, and the first few months of their forest life glide
                only too swiftly away, and gloom gathers over the wife's mind as the fatal term
                approaches. Day after day she spends in prayers and penances to avert, if possible,
                the unalterable sentence; but her heart hides its sad secret in itself, and to her
                <cb/> husband she seems as cheerful as before. At length the morning dawns which
                closed the year; and Satyavat rises to go to the forest, to cleave wood. Savitri
                entreats that she may go with him, and at last he consents, little thinking of the
                sad meaning which lay under her words.</p>
            <lg type="stanza">
                <l>"Having thus obtained his leave, to the wood she followed him,</l>
                <l>With an aching heart within her, but a smile upon her face.</l>
                <l>On she wandered with her husband, through the pleasant painted woods,</l>
                <l>And beheld their flocks of peacocks sporting in the happy spring,</l>
                <l>And with joy he pointed out the flowering trees which o'er them hung,</l>
                <l>And the stately flowing rivers, gleaming through the forest paths;</l>
                <l>But from these her eyes in sorrow ever to her husband turned,</l>
                <l>Ever as the Rishi's sentence came to memory rushing back;</l>
                <l>Ever as they roamed together, to the Rishi's prophecy</l>
                <l>Turned her thoughts with dark foreboding, and her heart seemed cleft in
                    twain."</l>
            </lg>
            <cb/>
            <p>At length they reach the spot, and Satyavat begins his task, when he suddenly
                complains of a pain in his head, and Savitri knows that the hour has come. She takes
                his head on her bosom, and there he falls asleep, and she watches over him until she
                sees standing beside them a dark figure, whom she knows by her heart's instincts to
                be Yama, the king of death. He seizes <cb/> the body, and binds his fatal band
                around it, and has begun to drag it away, when Savitri follows him, and implores him
                not to leave her behind. Yama, in pity for her anguish, grants her a boon of
                anything except her husband's life, and she chooses that her old father-in-law may
                receive his sight. Yama exclaims&#8212;</p>
            <lg type="stanza">
                <l>"Noble one, I grant thy wish; as thou hast said, so shall it be;</l>
                <l>Long and weary is the way; return, return, and sorrow not."</l>
            </lg>
            <cb/>
            <p>Still she lingers, and again Yama grants her a second boon with the same limitation;
                but still the bereaved wife lingers. A long conversation then follows between them;
                <cb/> and at last love conquers death! Yama again grants her a boon, and Savitri
                exclaims&#8212;</p>
            <lg type="stanza">
                <l>"Mighty lord, the boon thou grantest cometh as a real boon;</l>
                <l>No exception <hi rend="italic">now</hi> debars me, as thine other boons
                    debarred;</l>
                <l>Give my husband back to me; grant me my boon, and let him live;</l>
                <l>What is joy, or wealth, or fortune, if my husband be not there?"</l>
            </lg>
            <cb/>
            <p>Yama then departs, and Satyavat wakes back again into life.</p>
            <p>We have no space for the beautiful conversation which follows between the husband and
                wife; where she hides the dark secret from him, and only urges him to hasten home,
                as it is now quite night. They accordingly return to the hermitage, and Satyavat
                finds his father no longer blind; and the hermits all ask him the reason for the
                unexpected restoration of the old man's sight. Satyavat is as much astonished as the
                rest; and then Savitri opens her full heart and reveals the whole story.</p>
            <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h5" xml:id="s59" from="#s59" to="#s60"/>
            <p>Our last extract from the Mahabharata <note type="authorial" resp="#h5" place="left"
                corresp="#s59">&#9757;</note><cb/> shall be the closing scene of the poem; and here
                the heroic poetry of India attains its full! We know of no episode, even in the
                Homeric poems, which can surpass its mournful grandeur, or raise a more solemn dirge
                over the desolation of the fallen heart of man! Yudishthira has won the throne, and
                his enemies are all fallen; and an inferior poet would have concluded the story with
                a p&#230;an upon his happiness! But the Hindu bard had a far deeper insight into man's
                nature, and his genius would not content itself with any such commonplace
                catastrophe; he knew well that the human soul was born for the infinite, and that no
                    finite<anchor xml:id="s60"/>
                
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf007v" facs="mid.00011.012.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <cb/>line could fathom the depths of its longings! It was no idle fiction in Grecian
                mythology, that Ulysses, after his return to Ithaca, <cb/> wandered forth again with
                his hungry heart into the world.</p>
            <lg type="stanza">
                <l>"For all experience is an arch, where thro'</l>
                <l>Gleams that untraversed land, whose margin fades</l>
                <l>For ever and for ever as we move."</l>
            </lg>
            <cb/>
            <p>And Ulysses had found that the Ithaca, which had lured him on through ten years of
                war, and ten more of wandering, changed, upon his arrival, into a bleak barren rock,
                and his restless soul stretched out her hands once more towards the untrodden
                beyond! Just in the same way, and with the same deep significance, Yudishthira
                learns, after his victory, that the throne for which he had suffered so much leaves
                him as unsatisfied and hungry as before. The friends of his youth are fallen, and
                the excitement of contest is over; and he learns <cb/> in sorrow that kings are but
                men, and that the Fall has overshadowed the throne as much as the poorest cottage!
                In gloomy disappointment, Yudishthira resigns his crown, and he and his brothers and
                Draupadi set out in a forlorn journey to mount Meru, where Indra's heaven lies
                amongst the wilds of the Himalayas,<ref target="#note4">*</ref> there to find that rest which seemed denied to
                their search upon earth. We present a literal prose version of their pilgrimage, and
                with it close our extracts.</p>
            <lg type="stanza" n="I.">
                <l>"Having heard Yudishthira's resolve, and seen the destruction of Krishna,</l>
                <l>The five brothers set forth, and Draupadi, and the seventh was a dog that
                    followed them.</l>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h5" place="left">&#182;</note>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h5" place="left">&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</note>
                <l>Yudishthira himself was the last that quitted Hastinapura;</l>
                <l>And all the citizens and the court followed them on their way,</l>
                <l>But none felt able to say unto him, "return;"</l>
                <l>And at length they all went back unto the city.</l>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h5" place="left">&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</note>
                <l>Then the high-souled sons of Pandu, and far-famed Draupadi</l>
                <l>Pursued their way, fasting and with their faces turned towards the east,</l>
                <l>Resolved upon separation from earth, and longing for release from its laws;</l>
                <l>They roamed onward over many regions, and to many a river and sea.</l>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h5" place="left">&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</note>
                <l>Yudishthira went before, and Bhima followed next behind him,</l>
                <l>And Arjuna came after him, and then the twin sons of Madri,</l>
                <l>And sixth, after them, came Draupadi, with her fair face and lotus eyes,</l>
                <l>And last of all followed the dog, as they wandered on till they came to the
                    ocean.</l>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h5" place="left">	&#182;</note>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h5" place="left">&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</note>
                <l>But Arjuna left not hold of his heavenly bow,</l>
                <l>Lured by the splendour of its gems, nor of those two heavenly arrows;</l>
                <l>And suddenly they saw Agni<ref target="#ref2">+</ref> standing like a mountain
                    before them,</l>
                <l>Standing in gigantic form, and stopping up their path;</l>
                <l>And thus to them spoke the god,&#8212;'O sons of Pandu, do you know me not?</l>
                <l>O Yudishthira, mighty hero, knowest thou not my voice?</l>
                <l>I am Agni, who gave that bow unto Arjuna;</l>
                <l>Let him leave it here and go, for none other is worthy to bear it;</l>
                <l>For Arjuna's sake I stole that bow from Varuna, the ocean-god,</l>
                <l>Let Gandhiva, that best of bows, be given back to ocean again!'</l>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h5" place="left">&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</note>
                <l>Then the brothers all besought Arjuna to obey;</l>
                <l>And he flung the bow into the sea, and he flung those immortal arrows;</l>
                <l>And lo! as they fell into the sea, Agni vanished before them.</l>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h5" place="left">&#182;</note>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h5" place="left">&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</note>
                <l>And once more the sons of Pandu set forth, with their faces turned to the
                    south.</l>
                <l>And then by the upper shore of the briny sea</l>
                <l>They turned toward the south-west, and went on in their way.</l>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h5" place="left">&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</note>
                <l>And as they journeyed onwards, and came unto the west,</l>
                <l>There they beheld the old city of Krishna, now washed over by the ocean-tide.</l>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h5" place="left">&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</note>
                <l>Again they turned to the north, and still they went on in their way,</l>
                <l>Circumambulating round the continent, to find separation from earth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza" n="II.">
                <l>Then, with their senses subdued, the heroes having reached the north,</l>
                <l>Beheld, with their heaven-desiring eyes, the lofty mountain Himavat,</l>
            </lg>
            <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
           <note type="footnote" xml:id="note4"><p>*This is, in fact a precise counterpart to the legend of Ulysses, as Tennyson
                describes it in his poem;&#8212;the most epic fragment since Milton's days.</p>
            <lg type="stanza">
                <l>"For my purpose holds</l>
                <l>To sail unto the West, until I die.</l>
                <l>It may be that the gulfs will wash us down,</l>
                <l>It may be we shall reach the blessed isles,</l>
                <l>And see the great Achilles, whom we knew."</l></lg></note>
                <note type="footnote" xml:id="ref2">The God of Fire from whom Arjuna had obtained
                    the bow Gandhiva.</note>
                <pb xml:id="leaf008r" facs="mid.00011.013.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="date" place="top left">1848</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top" rend="italic">Indian Epic Poetry.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">31</fw>
                <lg><l>And having crossed its height, they beheld the sea of sand,</l>
                <l>And next they saw rocky Meru, the king of mountains.</l>
                    <note type="authorial" resp="#h5" place="left">&#8212;&#8212;</note>
                <l>But while they were thus faring onwards, in eager search for separation,</l>
                <l>Draupadi lost hold of her hope, and fell on the face of the earth;</l>
                <l>And Bhima the mighty having beheld her fall,</l>
                <l>Spoke to the king of justice,<ref target="#note5">*</ref> looking back to her, as
                    there she lay,</l>
                <l>'No act of evil hath she done, that faultless daughter of a king,</l>
                <l>Wherefore, then, oh conqueror! hath she fallen thus low on the ground?'</l>
                    <note type="authorial" resp="#h5" place="left">&#8212;&#8212;</note>
                <l>And thus to him answered Yudishthira, 'too great was her love for Arjuna,</l>
                <l>And the fruit thereof, oh Bhima! hath she gathered this day.'</l>
                    <note type="authorial" resp="#h5" place="left">&#8212;&#8212;</note>
                <l>Thus speaking, Bharata's glorious descendant went onwards, not looking back,</l>
                <l>Gathering up his soul in himself in his unstooping wisdom and justice.</l>
                    <note type="authorial" resp="#h5" place="left">&#8212;&#8212;</note>
                <l>Next the fair Sahadeva fell upon the face of the earth,</l>
                <l>And Bhima, beholding him fall, thus spake to the king;</l>
                <l>'Oh Yudishthira, <hi rend="italic">he</hi> the greatest, the least froward and
                    wilful of us all,</l>
                <l>He the son of fair Madri,&#8212;wherefore hath he fallen on the ground?'</l>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h5" place="left">&#8212;&#8212;</note>
                <l>And him thus answered Yudishthira, 'He esteemed none equal to himself,</l>
                <l>This was his fault, and therefore hath the Prince fallen this day.'</l>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h5" place="left">&#8212;&#8212;</note>
                <l>Thus speaking, he left Sahadeva, and went on,</l>
                <l>Yudishthira, king of justice, with his brothers and the dog.</l>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h5" place="left">&#8212;&#8212;</note>
                <l>But when Nakula saw the fall of Draupadi and his brother,</l>
                <l>The hero, full of love for his kindred, in his grief fell down like them to the
                    earth,</l>
                <l>And when Nakula, the fair-faced, had thus fallen like the others,</l>
                <l>Once more, in his wonder, spoke Bhima unto the king;</l>
                <l>'What! <hi rend="italic">he</hi> the undeviating in virtue, ever true to his
                    honour and faith,</l>
                <l>Unequalled for beauty in the world,&#8212;hath he too fallen on the ground?"</l>
                    <note type="authorial" resp="#h5" place="right">&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</note>
                <l>And him thus answered Yudishthira, 'Ever was the thought in his heart,</l>
                <l>"There is none equal in beauty to me, and I am superior unto all!"</l>
                <l>Therefore hath Nakula fallen; come Bhima, and follow my steps;</l>
                <l>Whatsoever each hath done, assuredly he eateth thereof.'</l>
                    <note type="authorial" resp="#h5" place="right">&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</note>
                <l>And when Arjuna beheld them thus fallen behind him,</l>
                <l>He too, the great conqueror, fell, with his soul pierced through with sorrow;</l>
                <l>And when he, the lion-heart, was fallen, like Indra himself in majesty,</l>
                <l>When he, the invincible, was dead, once more Bhima spoke unto the king;</l>
                <l>'No act of evil do I remember in all that Arjuna hath done;</l>
                <l>Wherefore then is this change, and why hath he too fallen on the ground?"</l>
                    <note type="authorial" resp="#h5" place="right">&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</note>
                <l>And him thus answered Yudishthira, '"In one day I could destroy all my
                    enemies,"</l>
                <l>Such was Arjuna's boast, and he falls, for he fulfilled it not!</l>
                <l>And he ever despised all warriors beside himself,</l>
                <l>This he ought not to have done, and therefore hath he fallen to-day.'</l>
                    <note type="authorial" resp="#h5" place="right">&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</note>
                <l>Thus speaking, the king went on, and then Bhima himself next fell to the
                    earth,</l>
                <l>And as he fell, he cried with a loud voice unto Yudishthira;</l>
                <l>'Oh king of justice, look back, I&#8212;[ thy dear brother am fallen,</l>
                <l>What is the cause of my fall! Oh tell it to me if thou knowest!'</l>
                    <note type="authorial" resp="#h5" place="right">&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</note>
                <l>Once more him answered Yudishthira, 'When thou gazed'st on thy foe,</l>
                <l>Thou hast cursed him with thy breath, therefore thou too fallest to-day.'</l>
                    <note type="authorial" resp="#h5" place="right">&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</note>
                <l>Thus having spoken, the mighty king, not looking back, went on,</l>
                <l>And still, as ever, behind him, went following that dog alone!"</l>
            </lg>
            
            <lg type="section"><head type="sub">III.</head>
                <l>"Lo! suddenly with a sound which ran through heaven and earth,</l>
                <l>Indra came riding on his chariot, and he cried to the king, 'ascend!'</l>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h5" place="right">&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</note>
                <l><hi rend="italic">Then</hi>, indeed, did the lord of justice look back to his
                    fallen brothers,</l>
                <l>And thus unto Indra he spoke, with a sorrowful heart:&#8212;</l>
                <l>'Let my brothers, who yonder lie fallen, go with me,</l>
                <l>Not even into thy heaven would I enter, if they were not there;</l>
                <l>And yon fair-faced daughter of a king, Draupadi the all-deserving,</l>
                <l>Let <hi rend="italic">her</hi> too enter with us! Oh Indra, approve my
                    prayer!'</l></lg>
            <lg type="section"><head type="sub">INDRA</head>
                <l>In heaven thou shalt find thy brothers, they are already there before thee,</l>
                <l>There are they all, with Draupadi; weep not then, O son of Bharata!</l>
                <l>Thither are they entered, prince, having thrown away their mortal weeds,</l>
                <l>But thou alone shalt enter, still wearing thy body of flesh.</l></lg>
                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
                <note type="footnote" place="bottom" xml:id="note5">*The usual title of
                    Yudishthira.</note>
                
                <pb xml:id="leaf008v" facs="mid.00011.014.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">32</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top" rend="italic">Causes of Poverty.</fw>
            <lg type="section"><head type="sub">YUDISHTHIRA</head>
                <l>Oh Indra, and what of this dog? It hath faithfully followed me through; Let it go
                    with me into heaven, for my soul is full of compassion.</l></lg>
            <lg type="section"><head type="sub">INDRA</head>
                <l>Immortality and fellowship with me, and the height of joy and felicity,</l>
                <l>All these hast thou reached to day; leave then the dog behind thee</l></lg>
            <lg type="section"><head type="sub">YUDISHTHIRA</head>
                <l>The good may oft act an evil part, but never a part like this;</l>
                <l>Away then with that felicity whose price is to abandon the faithful.</l></lg>
            <lg type="section"><head type="sub">INDRA</head>
                <l>My heaven hath no place for dogs; they steal away our offerings on earth,</l>
                <l>Leave then thy dog behind thee, nor think in thy heart that it is cruel.</l></lg>
            <lg type="section"><head type="sub">YUDISHTHIRA</head>
                <l>To abandon the faithful and devoted, is an endless crime, like the murder of a
                    Brahmin,</l>
                <l>Never, therefore, come weal or woe, will I abandon yon faithful dog.</l>
                <l>Yon poor creature, in fear and distress, hath trusted in my power to save it;</l>
                <l>Not, therefore, for e'en life itself, will I break my plighted word.</l></lg>
            
            <lg type="section"><head type="sub">INDRA</head>
                <l>If a dog but beholds a sacrifice, men esteem it unholy and void;</l>
                <l>Forsake then the dog, O hero, and heaven is thine own as a reward.</l>
                <l>Already thou hast borne to forsake thy fondly-loved brothers, and Draupadi,</l>
                <l>Why then forsakest thou not the dog? Wherefore now fails thy heart?</l></lg>
            
            <lg type="section"><head type="sub">YUDISHTHIRA</head>
                <l>Mortals, when they are dead, are dead to love or hate, so runs the world's
                    belief;</l>
                <l>I could not bring them back to life, but while they lived I never left them.</l>
                <l>To oppress the suppliant, to kill a wife, to spoil a Brahmin, and to betray one's
                    friends,</l>
                <l>These are the four great crimes; and to forsake a dependent, I count equal unto
                    them."</l>
            </lg>
            <cb/>
            <p>Yudishthira then enters heaven; but one more trial awaits him. He finds there
                Duryodhana and the other suns of Dhritarashtra, but he looks in vain for his own
                brothers. He refuses to stay in the Swerga without them, and a messenger is sent to
                bring him where they are. He descends to the Indian hell, and finds them there; and
                he proudly resolves to stay with them and share their sorrows, rather than dwell in
                heaven without them. But the whole scene was only a <hi rend="italic">máyá</hi>, or
                illusion to prove his virtue; the sorrows suddenly vanish, the surrounding hell
                changes into heaven, where Yudishthira and his brothers dwell with Indra, in full
                content of heart for ever.</p>
            <p>Thus closes the Mahabharata, the new mythic world, which a modern Columbus has
                opened! Greatly as our times are distinguished by discovery and progress, we are yet
                continually reminded, amidst its changes, of that world of the Past, out of which
                the Present is born. The century which has witnessed such onward strides of physical
                and political science, has also unlocked the secrets of the hieroglyphics of Egypt.
                Major Rawlinson is now giving a <cb/> voice to dumb inscriptions upon Persian rocks;
                and, in the same way, in India's mythic poetry we become contemporaries with
                Greece's earliest history. The heroic times and youth of the race thus rise up in
                earth's later days, in startling contrast with our science and commerce, as if
                Nature would expressly teach us, that there lies a romance in the past which can
                never grow obsolete to man; and howsoever our civilization may change us, and under
                all the new developments of the human race, the memories of old ages will still
                survive and come back to us, like the stories of childhood among the sterner
                realities of manhood!</p><ab>C.</ab>
            <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
            <del rend="hashmark" hand="#h5"><p>ART. III.&#8212;1. <hi rend="italic">Le Moniteur de
                        Juillet</hi> 3, 1848.</p>
                <p>2.&#8212;<hi rend="italic">Principles of Political Economy.</hi> By J. S. Mill.
                    Parker.</p>
                <p>T<hi rend="smallcaps">HE</hi> following remarks, in reference to the sufferings
                    of the working classes, were made by M. Thiers, in a committee of the
                Na</p></del>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
