<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="unl.00003">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Tupper's Complete Poetical Works</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author xml:id="mft">Martin Farquhar Tupper</author>
                <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="slg">Samantha Gilmore</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2019</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>unl.00003</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain
                        exceptions, public domain works may be freely copied or used in the creation
                        of derivative works without permission, or authorization, of the former
                        copyright owners.</p>
                    <p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and
                        is governed by a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"
                            >Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY
                        4.0).</p>
                    <p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted
                        by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Tupper's Complete Poetical Works</title>
                    <idno type="callno">PR5699.T5.A17</idno>
                    <date notBefore="1853">1853 or later</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="unl">University of Nebraska-Lincoln Archives and Special
                        Collections</orgName>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from digital images of the original
                        item.</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl type="base">
                    <author>Martin Farquhar Tupper</author>
                    <title level="m">Tupper's Complete Poetical Works</title>
                    <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                    <date>1853</date>
                    <note type="project"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="h1" scribeRef="#ww" medium="blue pencil"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h2" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h3" scribeRef="#mft" medium="type"/>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#slg" when="2019-10-16">Transcribed and encoded.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="marginalia">


        <front>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="unl_sg.00001.jpg" type="recto"/>

            <titlePage>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="top-right">W.W. '<unclear
                        reason="illegible" cert="high" resp="#slg">8</unclear>2</note>

                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart type="main">TUPPER'S<lb/>COMPLETE<lb/>POETICAL WORKS:</titlePart>
                </docTitle>

                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart type="sub">CONTAINING<lb/> "PROVERBIAL PHILOSOPHY," "A THOUSAND<lb/>
                        LINES," "HACTENUS," "GERALDINE,"<lb/> AND "MISCELLANEOUS POEMS:"<lb/> WITH A
                        PORTRAIT OF THE AUTHOR.</titlePart>
                </docTitle>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

                <byline>A NEW EDITION</byline>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

                <docImprint><pubPlace>BOSTON:</pubPlace> PHILLIPS, SAMPSON AND COMPANY,<lb/> 110
                    WASHINGTON STREET. <docDate when="1853">1853.</docDate></docImprint>
            </titlePage>
        </front>



        <body>
            <div1>


                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="unl_sg.00002.jpg" type="recto"/>

                <head>THE WORDS OF WISDOM.</head>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="s1" from="#s1" to="#s2"
                            /><span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s3" from="#s3"
                            to="#s2"/><hi rend="smallcaps">FEW</hi> and precious are the words which
                        the lips of Wisdom utter:</l>
                    <l>To what shall their rarity be likened? What price shall count their
                        worth?</l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s2"/>
                    <l>Perfect and much to be desired, and giving joy with riches,</l>
                    <l>No lovely thing on earth can picture all their beauty.</l>
                    <l>They be chance pearls, flung among the rocks by the sullen waters of
                        Oblivion.</l>
                    <l>Which Diligence loveth to gather, and hang round the neck of Memory;</l>
                    <l>They be white-winged seeds of happiness, wafted from the island of the
                        blessed,</l>
                    <l>Which Thought carefully tendeth, in the kindly garden of the heart;</l>
                    <l>They be sproutings of an harvest for eternity, bursting through the tilth of
                        time,</l>
                    <l>Green promise of the golden wheat, that yieldeth angels' food;</l>
                    <l>They be drops of the crystal dew, which the wings of seraphs scatter,</l>
                    <l>When on some brighter Sabbath, their plumes quiver most with delight;</l>
                    <l>Such, and so precious, are the words which the lips of Wisdom utter.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <note place="supraliner" type="authorial" resp="#h1">&#10003; &#10003;
                        &#10003;</note>
                    <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="s4" from="#s4" to="#s5"/>
                    <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="s6" from="#s6" to="#s5"/>
                    <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="s7" from="#s7" to="#s5"/>
                    <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s8" from="#s8" to="#s5"/>
                    <l>Yet more, for the half is not said, of their might, and dignity, and
                        value,</l>
                    <l>For live-giving be they glorious, redolent of sanctity and heaven:</l>
                    <l>As the fumes of hallowed incense, that veil the throne of the Most High;</l>
                    <l>As the beaded bubbles that sparkle on the rim of the cup of Immortality;</l>
                    <l>As wreaths of the rainbow spray, from the pure cataracts of Truth.</l>
                    <l>Such, and so precious, are the words which the lips of Wisdom utter.</l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s5"/>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Yet once again, loving student, suffer the praises of thy teacher.</l>
                    <l>For verily the sun of the mind, and the life of the heart, is Wisdom:</l>
                    <l>She is pure and full of light, crowning gray hairs with lustre,</l>
                    <l>And kindling the eye of youth with a fire not its own;</l>
                    <l>And her words, whereunto canst thou liken them> for earth cannot show their
                        peers:</l>
                </lg>

            </div1>



            <div1>

                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="unl_sg00003.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top">OF TRUTH IN THINGS FALSE.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-right">13</fw>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Somewhat of fair and good, though blotted by the finger of corruption:</l>
                    <l>And if error cometh in like a flood, it mixeth with streams of truth,</l>
                    <l>And the Adversary loveth to have it so, for thereby many are decoyed.</l>
                    <l>Providence is dark in its permissions; yet one day, when all is known,</l>
                    <l>The universe of reason shall acknowledge how just and good were they;</l>
                    <l>For the wise man leaneth on his wisdom, and the righteous trusteth to his
                        righteousness,</l>
                    <l>And those who thirst for independence, are suffered to drink of
                        disappointment.</l>
                    <l>Wherefore?&#8212;to prove and humble them; and to teach the idolaters of
                        truth,</l>
                    <l>That it is but the ladder unto Him, on whom only they should trust.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="s9" from="#s9" to="#s10"/>
                    <l>There is truth in the wildest scheme that imaginative heat hath
                        engendered,</l>
                    <l>And a man may gather somewhat from the crudest theories of fancy:</l>
                    <l>The alchemist laboureth in folly, but catcheth chance gleams of wisdom.</l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s10"/>
                    <l>And findeth out many inventions, though his crucible breed not gold;</l>
                    <l>The sinner, toying with witchcraft, thinketh to delude his fellows,</l>
                    <l>But there be very spirits of evil, and what if they come at his bidding;</l>
                    <l>He is a bold bad man who dareth to tamper with the dead;</l>
                    <l>For their whereabout lieth in a mystery&#8212;that vestibule leading to
                        Eternity,</l>
                    <l>The waiting-room for unclad ghosts, before the presence-chamber of their
                        King:</l>
                    <l>Mind may act upon mind, though bodies be far divided;</l>
                    <l>For the life is in the blood, but souls communicate unseen:</l>
                    <l>And the heat of an excited intellect, radiating to its fellows,</l>
                    <l>Doth kindle dry leaves afar off, while the green wood around it is
                        unwarmed.</l>
                    <l>The dog may have a spirit as well as his brutal master;</l>
                    <l>A spirit to live in happiness; for why should he be robbed of his
                        existence?</l>
                    <l>Hath he not a conscience of evil, a glimmer of moral sense,</l>
                    <l>Love and hatred, courage and fear, and visible shame and pride?</l>
                    <l>There may be a future rest for the patient victims of the cruel;</l>
                    <l>And a season allotted for their bliss, to compensate for unjust
                        suffering.</l>
                    <l>Spurn not at seeming error, but dig below its surface for the truth;</l>
                    <l>And beware of seeming truths, that grow on the roots of error:</l>
                    <l>For comely are the apples that spring from the Dead Sea's cursed shore:</l>
                    <l>But within are they dust and ashes, and the hand that plucked them shall rue
                        it.</l>
                </lg>

            </div1>



            <div1>

                <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="unl_sg00004.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top">OF HIDDEN USES.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-right">17</fw>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Not long hath the twisted leaf, the fragrant gift of China,</l>
                    <l>Nor that nutritious root, the boon of far Peru,</l>
                    <l>Nor the many-<choice>
                            <orig>coloured</orig>
                            <reg>colored</reg>
                        </choice>dahlia, nor the gorgeous flaunting cactus,</l>
                    <l>Nor the multitude of fruits and flowers, ministered to life and luxury;</l>
                    <l>Even so, there be virtues yet unknown in the wasted foliage of the elm,</l>
                    <l>In the sun-dried harebell of the downs, and the hyacinth drinking in the
                        meadow,</l>
                    <l>In the sycamore's winged fruit, and the facet-cut cones of the cedar;</l>
                    <l>And the pansy and bright geranium live not alone for beauty,</l>
                    <l>Nor the waxen flower of the arbute, though it dieth in a day,</l>
                    <l>Nor the sculptured crest of the fir, unseen but by the stars;</l>
                    <l>And the meanest weed of the garden serveth unto many uses,</l>
                    <l>The salt tamarisk, and juicy flag, the freckled orchis, and the daisy.</l>
                    <l>The world may laugh at famine when forest-trees yield bread,</l>
                    <l>When acorns give out fragrant drink,(5) and the sap of the linden is as
                        fatness:</l>
                    <l>For every green herb, from the lotus to the darnel,</l>
                    <l>Is rich with delicate aids to help incurious man.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><hi rend="circled" hand="#h1">Still, Mind is up and stirring, and pryeth in
                            the corners of contrivance,</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled" hand="#h1">Often from the dark recesses picking out bright
                            seeds of truth:</hi></l>
                    <!-- circles do not render; target will not work -->
                    <note type="authorial" place="right" resp="#h1">!</note>
                    <l>Knowledge hath clipped the lightning's wings, and mewed it up for a
                        purpose,</l>
                    <l>Training to some domestic task the fiery bird of heaven;</l>
                    <l>Tamed is the spirit of the storm, to slave in all peaceful arts,</l>
                    <l>To walk with husbandry and science; to stand in the vanguard against
                        death:</l>
                    <l>And the chemist balanceth his elements with more than magic skill,</l>
                    <l>Commanding stones that they be bread, and draining sweetness out of the
                        wormwood.</l>
                    <l>Yet man, heedless of a God, counteth up vain reckonings,</l>
                    <l>Fearing to be jostled and starved out, by the too prolific increase of his
                        kind;</l>
                    <l>And asketh, in unbelieving dread, for how few years to come</l>
                    <l>Will the black cellars of the world yield unto him fuel for his winter.</l>
                    <l>Might not the wide-ways sea be pent within narrower bounds?</l>
                    <l>Might not the arm of diligence make the tangled wilderness a garden?</l>
                    <l>And for aught thou canst tell, there may be a thousand methods</l>
                    <l>If comforting thy limbs in warmth, though thou kindle not a spark.</l>
                </lg>

            </div1>


            <div1>


                <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="unl_sg.00005.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top">OF INDIRECT INFLUENCES.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-right">23</fw>

                <head>Of INDIRECT INFLUENCES.</head>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><hi rend="smallcaps">FACE</hi> thy foe in the field, and perchance thou wilt
                        meet thy master,</l>
                    <l>For the sword is chained to his wrist, and his <choice>
                            <orig>armour</orig>
                            <reg>armor</reg>
                        </choice> buckled for the battle;</l>
                    <l>But find him when he looketh not for thee, aim between the joints of his
                        harness,</l>
                    <l>And the crest of his pride will be humbled, his cruelty will bite the
                        dust</l>
                    <l>Beard not a lion in his den, but fashion the secret pitfall,</l>
                    <l>So shalt thou conquer the strong, thyself triumphing in weakness.</l>
                    <l>The hurricane rageth fiercely, and the promontory standeth in its might,</l>
                    <l>Breasting the artillery of heaven, as darts glance from the crocodile;</l>
                    <l>But the small continual creeping of the silent footsteps of the sea</l>
                    <l>Mineth the wall of adamant, and stealthily compasseth its ruin.</l>
                    <l>The weakness of accident is strong, where the strength of design is weak:</l>
                    <l>And a casual analogy convinceth, when a mind beareth not argument.</l>
                    <l>Will not a man listen? be silent; and prove thy maxim by example:</l>
                    <l>Never fear, thou losest not thy hold, though thy mouth doth not render a
                        reason.</l>
                    <l>Contend not in wisdom with a fool, for thy sense maketh much of his
                        conceit;</l>
                    <l>And some errors never would have thriven, had it not been for learned
                        refutation;</l>
                    <l>Yea, much evil hath been caused by an honest wrestler for truth,</l>
                    <l>And much of unconscious good, by the man that hated wisdom:</l>
                    <l>For the intellect judgeth closely, and if thou overstep thy argument,</l>
                    <l>Or seem not consistent with thyself, or fail in thy direct purpose,</l>
                    <l>The mind that went along with thee, shall stop and return without thee,</l>
                    <l>And thou shalt have raised a foe, where thou mightest have won a friend.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Hints, shrewdly strown, mightily disturb the spirit,</l>
                    <note type="authorial" place="right" resp="#h1">&#8212;</note>
                    <l>Where a barefaced accusation would be too ridiculous for calumny:</l>
                    <l>The sly suggestion toucheth nerves, and nerves contract the frongs,</l>
                    <l>And the sensitive miimosa of affection trembleth to its root;</l>
                    <l>And friendships, the growth of half a century, those oaks that laugh at
                        storms,</l>
                    <l>Have been cankered in a night by a worm, even as the prophet's gourd.</l>
                    <l>Hast thou loved, and not known jealousy? for a sidelong look</l>
                    <l>Can please or pain thy heart more than the multitudes of proofs:</l>
                </lg>
            </div1>


            <div1>


                <pb xml:id="leaf006r" facs="unl_sg.00006.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top">OF INDIRECT INFLUENCES.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-right">25</fw>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>He stealeth all goodly names, as worth, and value, and substance,</l>
                    <l>Which be the ancient heritage of Virtue, but such an one ascribeth unto
                        Wealth:</l>
                    <l>He spurneth the needy sage, whose wisdom hath enrich nations,</l>
                    <l>And the sons of poverty and learning, without whom earth were a desert.</l>
                    <l>Music, the soother of cares, the tuner of the dank discordant
                        heart-strings,</l>
                    <l>It is nought unto such an one but sounds, whereby some earn their living:</l>
                    <l>The poem, and the pictures, and the statue, to him seem idle baubles,</l>
                    <l>Which wealth condescendeth to <choice>
                            <orig>favour</orig>
                            <reg>favor</reg>
                        </choice>, to gain him the name of patron.</l>
                    <l>But little wotteth he the might of the means his folly despiseth;</l>
                    <l>He considereth not that these be the wires which move the puppets of the
                        world.</l>
                    <l>A sentence hath formed a character, (7) and a character subdued a
                        kingdom;</l>
                    <l>A picture hath ruined souls, or raised them to commerce with the skies:</l>
                    <l>The pen hath shaken nations, and stablished the world in peace;</l>
                    <l>And the whole full horn of plenty been filled from the vial of science.</l>
                    <l>He regardeth man as sensual, the monarch of created matter,</l>
                    <l>And careth not aught for mind, that linketh him with spirits unseen:</l>
                    <l>He feedeth his carcass and is glad, though his soul be faint and
                        famished,</l>
                    <l>And the dull brute power of the body bindeth him a captive to himself.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>
                        <span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="s11" from="#s11" to="#s12"/>
                        <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="s13" from="#s13" to="#s12"/>Man
                        liveth from hour to hour, and knoweth not what may happen;</l>
                    <l>Influences circle him on all sides, and yet must he answer for his
                        actions,</l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s12"/>
                    <note type="authorial" place="right" resp="#h1" target="#s12">?</note>
                    <l>For the being that is master of himself, bendeth events to his will,</l>
                    <l>But a slave to selfish passion is the wavering creature of circumstance.</l>
                    <l>To this man temptation is a poison, to that man it addeth <choice>
                            <orig>vigour</orig>
                            <reg>vigor</reg>
                        </choice>;</l>
                    <l>And each may render to himself influences good or evil.</l>
                    <l>As thou directest the power, harm or advantage will follow;</l>
                    <l>And the torrent that swept the valley, may be led to turn a mill;</l>
                    <l>The wild electric flash, that could have kindled comets,</l>
                    <l>May by the ductile wire give ease to an ailing child.</l>
                    <l>For outward matter or event, fashion not the character within,</l>
                    <l>But each man, yielding or resisting, fashioneth his mind for himself.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Some have said, What is in a name?&#8212;most potent plastic influence;</l>
                    <l>A name is a word of character, and repetition stablisheth the fact;</l>
                    <l>And greatest is the power of a name, when its power is least suspected.</l>
                </lg>

                <fw type="sig" place="bottom-left">2</fw>

            </div1>


            <div1>


                <pb xml:id="leaf007v" facs="unl_sg.00007.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-left">62</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top">PROVERBIAL PHILOSOPHY.</fw>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Help thee to humour infirmities, to wink at innocent errors,</l>
                    <l>To take small count of forms, to bear with prejudice and fancy:</l>
                    <l>Discretion guard thine asking, discretion aid thine answer,</l>
                    <l><span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="s14" from="#s14" to="#s15"/>
                        <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s16" from="#s16" to="#s15"
                        />Teach thee that well-timed silence hath more eloquence than speech,</l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s15"/>
                    <l>Whisper thee, thou art Weakness, though thy cause be strength,</l>
                    <l>And tell thee, the keystone of an arch can be loosened with least <choice>
                            <orig>labour</orig>
                            <reg>labor</reg>
                        </choice> from within.</l>
                    <l>The snows of Hecla lie around its troubled smoking Geysers;</l>
                    <l>Let the cool streams of prudence temper the hot spring of zeal:</l>
                    <l>So shalt thou gain thine <choice>
                            <orig>honourable</orig>
                            <reg>honorable</reg>
                        </choice> end, nor lose the midway prize;</l>
                    <l>So shall thy life be useful, and thy young heart happy.</l>
                </lg>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

            </div1>


            <div1>

                <head>OF TRIFLES.</head>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><hi rend="smallcaps">YET</hi> once more, saith the fool, yet once, and is it
                        not a little one?</l>
                    <l>Spare me this folly yet an hour, for what is one among so many?</l>
                    <l>And he blindeth his conscience with lies, and stupefieth his heart with
                        doubts;&#8212;</l>
                    <l>Whom shall I harm in this matter? and a little ill breedeth much good;</l>
                    <l>My thoughts, are they not mine own? and they leave no mark behind them;</l>
                    <l>And if God so pardoneth crime, how should these petty sins affect
                        him?&#8212;</l>
                    <l>So he transgresseth yet again, and falleth by little and little,</l>
                    <l>Till the ground crumble beneath him, and he sinketh in the gulf
                        despairing.</l>
                    <l>For there is nothing in the earth so small that it may not produce great
                        things,</l>
                    <l>And no swerving from a right line, that may not lead eternally astray.</l>
                    <l>A landmark tree was once a see, and the dust in the balance maketh a
                        difference;</l>
                    <l>And the cairn is heaped high by each one flinging a pebble:</l>
                    <l>The dangerous bar in the <choice>
                            <orig>harbour's</orig>
                            <reg>harbor's</reg>
                        </choice> mouth is only grains of sand;</l>
                    <l>And the shoal that hath wrecked a navy is the work of a colony of worms:</l>
                    <l>Yea, and a despicable gnat may madden the mighty elephant;</l>
                    <l>And the living rock is worn by the diligent flow of the brook.</l>
                    <l>Little art thou, O man, and in trifles thou contendest with thine equals,</l>
                    <l>For atoms must crowd upon atoms, ere crime groweth to be a giant.</l>
                </lg>

            </div1>


            <div1>


                <pb xml:id="leaf008r" facs="unl_sg.00008.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top">OF THINKING.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-right">71</fw>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Yea, let the heathen be thy teacher, who adoreth many gods,</l>
                    <l>For there is no wide-spread error that hath not truth for its beginning.</l>
                    <l>Be content; thine eye cannot see all the sides of a cube at one view,</l>
                    <l>Nor thy mind in the self-same moment follow two ideas:</l>
                    <l>There are now many marvels in thy creed, believing what thou seest,</l>
                    <l>Then let not the conceit of intellect hinder thee from worshipping
                        mystery</l>
                </lg>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

            </div1>

            <div1>

                <head>OF THINKING.</head>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><hi rend="smallcaps">REFLECTION</hi> is a flower of a mind, giving out
                        wholesome fragrance,</l>
                    <l>But reverie is the same flower, when rank and running to seed.</l>
                    <l>Better to read little with thought, than much with levity and quickness</l>
                    <l>For mind is not as merchandise, which decreaseth in the using,</l>
                    <l>But liker to the passions of man, which rejoice and expand in exertion:</l>
                    <l>Yet live not wholly on thine own ideas, lest they lead thee astray;</l>
                    <l>For in spirit, as in substance, thou art a social creature;</l>
                    <l>And if thou leanest on thyself, thou rejectest the guidance of thy
                        betters</l>
                    <l>Yea, thou contemnest all men,&#8212;Am I not wiser than they?</l>
                    <l>Foolish vanity hath blinded thee, and warped thy weak judgment;</l>
                    <l>For, though new ideas flow from new springs, and enrich the treasury of
                        knowledge,</l>
                    <l>Yet listen often, ere thou think much; and look around thee ere thou
                        judgest.</l>
                    <l>Memory, the <choice>
                            <sic>daugter</sic>
                            <corr>daughter</corr>
                        </choice> of Attention, is the teeming mother of Wisdom,</l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled" hand="#h1">And safer is he that storeth knowledge, than he
                            that would make it for himself.</hi></l>
                    <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="right">!</note>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Imagination is not thought, neither is fancy reflection:</l>
                    <l>Thought paceth like a hoary sage, but imagination hath wings as an eagle:</l>
                    <l>Reflection sternly considereth, nor is sparing to condemn evil,</l>
                    <l>But fancy lightly laugheth, in the sun-clad garden of amusement.</l>
                    <l>For the shy game of the fowler is the quickest shot is the surest;</l>
                    <l>But with slow care and measured aim the gunner pointeth his cannon:</l>
                    <l>So for all less occasions, the surface thought is best,</l>
                    <l>But to be master of the great take thou heavier metal.</l>
                    <l>It is a good thing, and a wholesome, to search out bosom sins,</l>
                </lg>

            </div1>


            <div1>


                <pb xml:id="leaf009v" facs="unl_sg.00009.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-left">102</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top">PROVERBIAL PHILOSOPHY.</fw>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>For, alas, how few be friends, of whom charity hath hoped well!</l>
                    <l>How few there be among men who forget themselves for others!</l>
                    <l>Each one seeketh his own, and looketh on his brethren as rivals,</l>
                    <l>Masking envy with friendship, to serve his secret ends.</l>
                    <l>And the world, that corrupteth all good, hath wronged that sacred name,</l>
                    <l>For it calleth any man friend, who is not known for an enemy;</l>
                    <l>And such be as the flies of summer, while plenty sitteth at thy board;</l>
                    <l>But who can wonder at their flight from the cold denials of want?</l>
                    <l>Such be as vultures round a carcass, assembled together for the feast:</l>
                    <l>But a sudden noise scareth them, and forthwith are thy specks among the
                        clouds.</l>
                    <l>There be few, O child of sensibility, who deserve to have thy confidence;</l>
                    <l>Yet weep not, for there are some, and such some live for thee:</l>
                    <l>To them is the chilling world a drear and barren scene,</l>
                    <l>And gladly seek they such as thou art, for seldom find they the occasion:</l>
                    <l>For, though no man excludeth himself from the high capability of
                        friendship,</l>
                    <l>Yet verily is the man a marvel whom truth can write a friend.</l>
                </lg>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

            </div1>

            <div1>

                <head>OF LOVE.</head>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><hi rend="smallcaps">THERE</hi> is a fragrant blossom, that maketh glad the
                        garden of the heart:</l>
                    <l><hi rend="underline">Its root lieth deep</hi>; <hi rend="underline">it
                            is</hi> delicate, <hi rend="underline">yet</hi> lasting, as lilac crocus
                        of autumn;</l>
                    <l>Loneliness and thought are the dews that water it morn and even;</l>
                    <l>Memory and Absence cherish it, as the balmy breathings of the south:</l>
                    <l>Its sun is the brightness of affection, and it bloometh in the borders of
                        Hope;</l>
                    <l>Its companions are gentle flowers, and the brier withereth by its side.</l>
                    <l>I saw it budding in beauty; I felt the magic of its smile;</l>
                    <l>The violet rejoiced beneath it, the rose stooped down and kissed it;</l>
                    <l>And I thought some cherub had planted there a truant flower of Eden,</l>
                    <l>As a bird bringeth foreign seeds, that they may flourish in a kindly soil</l>
                    <l>I saw, and asked not its name; I knew no language was so wealthy,</l>
                    <l>Though every heart of every clime findeth its echo within.</l>
                    <l>And yet what shall I say? Is a sordid man capable of&#8212;Love?</l>
                </lg>

            </div1>


            <pb xml:id="leaf010r" facs="unl_sg.00010.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <fw type="header" place="top">OF LOVE.</fw>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top-right">103</fw>

            <div1>
                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Hath a seducer known it? Can an adulterer perceive it?</l>
                    <l>Or he that seeketh strange women, can he feel its purity?</l>
                    <l><span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="s17" from="#s17" to="#s18"/>
                        <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s19" from="#s19" to="#s18"/>Or
                        he that changeth often, can he know its truth?</l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s18"/>
                    <l>Longing for another's happiness, yet often destroying its own;</l>
                    <l>Chaste, and looking up to God, as the fountain of tenderness and joy;</l>
                    <l>Quiet, yet flowing deeps, as the Rhine among rivers;</l>
                    <l>Lasting, and knowing not change&#8212;it walketh with Truth and
                        Sincerity.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Love:&#8212;what a volume in a word, an ocean in a tear,</l>
                    <l>A seventh heaven in a glance, a whirlwind in sigh,</l>
                    <l>The lightning in a touch, a millennium in a moment:</l>
                    <l>What consecrated joy or woe in blest or blighted love!</l>
                    <l>For it is, that native poetry springing up indigenous to Mind,</l>
                    <l>The heart's own-country music thrilling all its chords,</l>
                    <l>The story without an end that angels throng to hear,</l>
                    <l>The word, the king of words, carved on Jehovah's heart!</l>
                    <l>Oh! call thou snake-eyed malice mercy, call envy honest praise,</l>
                    <l>Count selfish raft for wisdom, and coward treachery for prudence,</l>
                    <l>Do homage to blaspheming unbelief as to bold and free philosophy,</l>
                    <l>And estimate the recklessness of license as the right attribute of
                        liberty,&#8212;</l>
                    <l>But with the world, thou friend and scholar, stain not this pure name;</l>
                    <l>Nor suffer the majesty of Love to be likened to the meanness of desire:</l>
                    <l>For Love is no more such, than seraphs' hymns are discord,</l>
                    <l>And such is no more Love, the &#230;na's breath is summer.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Love is a sweet idolatry, enslaving all the soul,</l>
                    <l>A mighty spiritual force, warring with the dullness of matter,</l>
                    <l>An angel-mind breathed into a mortal, though fallen, yet how beautiful!</l>
                    <l>All the devotion of the heart in all its depth and grandeur.</l>
                    <l>Behold that pale geranium, pent within the cottage window;</l>
                    <l>How yearningly it stretcheth to the light its sickly long-staked leaves,</l>
                    <l>How it straineth upward to the sun, coveting his sweet influences,</l>
                    <l>How real a living sacrifice to the God of all its worship!</l>
                    <l>Such is the soul that loveth; and so the rose-tree of affection</l>
                    <l>Bendeth its every leaf to look on those dear eyes,</l>
                    <l>Its every blushing petal basketh in the light,</l>
                    <l>And all its gladness, all its life, is hanging on their love.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>If the love of the heart is blighted, it buddeth not again;</l>
                </lg>
            </div1>


            <div1>


                <pb xml:id="leaf010v" facs="unl_sg.00011.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-left">104</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top">PROVERBIAL PHILOSOPHY.</fw>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>If that pleasant song is forgotten, it is to be learnt no more:</l>
                    <l>Yet often that will thought look back, and weep over early affection;</l>
                    <l>And the dim notes of that pleasant song will be heard as a reproachful
                        spirit,</l>
                    <l>Moaning in &#230;olian strains over the desert of the heart,</l>
                    <l>Where the hot siroccos of the world have withered its one oasis</l>
                </lg>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

            </div1>

            <div1>

                <head>OF MARRIAGE.</head>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><hi rend="circled"><hi rend="smallcaps">SEEK</hi> a good wife of thy God, for
                            she is the best gift of his providence</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled">Yet ask not in bold confidence that which he hath not
                            promised.</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled">Thou knowest not his good-will:&#8212;be thy prayer then
                            submissive there unto;</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled">And leave thy petition to his mercy, assured that he will
                            deal well with thee.</hi></l>
                    <l>If thou art to have a wife of thy youth, she is now living on the earth;</l>
                    <l>Therefore think of her, and pray for her weal; yea, though thou hast not seen
                        her.</l>
                    <span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="s20" from="#s20" to="#s21"/>
                    <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s22" from="#s22" to="#s21"/>
                    <l>They that love early become like-minded, and the tempter touches them
                        not.</l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s21"/>
                    <l>They grow up leaning on each other, as the olive and vine.</l>
                    <l>Youth longeth for a kindred spirit, and yearneth for a heart that can commune
                        with his own;</l>
                    <l>He meditateth night and day, doting on the image of his fancy.</l>
                    <l>Take heed that what charmeth thee is real, nor springeth of thine own
                        imagination;</l>
                    <l>And suffer not trifles to win thy love; for a wife is thine unto death.</l>
                    <l>The harp and the voice may thrill thee,&#8212;sound may enchant thine
                        ear,</l>
                    <l>But considere thou, the hand will wither, and the sweet notes turn to
                        discord:</l>
                    <l>The eye, so brilliant at even, may be red with sorrow in the morning;</l>
                    <l>And the sylph-like form of elegance must writhe in the crampings of pain.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>O happy lot, and hallowed, even as the joy of angels,</l>
                    <l>Where the golden chain of godliness is entwined with the roses of love:</l>
                    <l>But beware, thou seem not to be holy, to win favour in the eyes of a
                        creature,</l>
                </lg>
            </div1>


            <div1>


                <pb xml:id="leaf011r" facs="unl_sg.00012.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top">OF MARRIAGE.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-right">105</fw>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>For the guilt of the hypocrite is deadly, and winneth thee wrath
                        elsewhere.</l>
                    <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s23" from="#s23" to="#s24"/>
                    <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="s25" from="#s25" to="#s26"/>
                    <l>The idol of thy heart is, as thou, a probationary sojourner on earth;</l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s26"/>
                    <span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="s27" from="#s27" to="#s28"/>
                    <l>Therefore be chary of her soul, for that is a jewel in her casket.</l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s24"/>
                    <anchor xml:id="s28"/>
                    <l>Let her be a child of God, that she bring with her a blessing to thy
                        house,&#8212;</l>
                    <l>A blessing above riches, and leading contentment in its train:</l>
                    <l>Let her be an heir of heaven; so shall she help thee on thy way;</l>
                    <l>For those who are one in faith, fight double-handed against evil.</l>
                    <l>Take heed lest she love thee before God; that she be not an idolator</l>
                    <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s29" from="#s29" to="#s30"/>
                    <l>Yet see thou that she love thee well: for her heart is the heart of
                        woman;</l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s30"/>
                    <l>And the triple nature of humanity must be bound by a triple chain,</l>
                    <l>For soul and mind and body&#8212;godliness, esteem, and affection.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s31" from="#s31" to="#s32"/>
                    <l>How beautiful is modesty! it winneth upon all beholders:</l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s32"/>
                    <l>But a word or a glance may destroy the pure love that should have been for
                        thee.</l>
                    <l>Affect not to despise beauty; no one is freed from its dominion:</l>
                    <l><note type="authorial" place="inline" resp="#h2">(</note>But regard it not a
                        pearl of price<note type="authorial" place="inline" resp="#h2"
                        >)</note>:&#8212;it is fleeting as the bow in the clouds.</l>
                    <note type="authorial" place="right" resp="#h2">?</note>
                    <l>If the character within be gentle, it often hath its index in the
                        countenance:</l>
                    <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s33" from="s33" to="#s34"/>
                    <l>The soft smile of a loving face is better than <choice>
                            <orig>splendour</orig>
                            <reg>splendor</reg>
                        </choice> that hath fadeth quickly</l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s34"/>
                    <l>When thou choosest a wife, think not only of thyself,</l>
                    <l>But of those God may give thee of her, that they reproach thee not for their
                        being;</l>
                    <l>See that he hath given her heath, lest thou lose her early and weep;</l>
                    <l>See that she springeth of a wholesome stock, that thy little ones perish not
                        before thee:</l>
                    <l>For many a laughing cheek been bright with the glare of madness</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s35" from="s35" to="#s36"/>
                    <l>Mark the converse of one thou lovest, that it be sim<hi rend="underline"
                            >p</hi>le and <hi rend="underline">since</hi>re;</l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s36"/>
                    <l>For an artful or <hi rend="underline">fal</hi>se wo<hi rend="underline"
                            >ma</hi>n shall set thy pil<hi rend="underline">lo</hi>w wit<hi
                            rend="underline">h thorns.</hi></l>
                    <l>O<hi rend="underline">bse</hi>rve her de<hi rend="underline">por</hi>tment
                        with ot<hi rend="underline">he</hi>rs, w<hi rend="underline">h</hi>en she
                            th<hi rend="underline">inket</hi>h not that t<hi rend="underline"
                            >ho</hi>u art <hi rend="underline">nigh</hi>,</l>
                    <l>For with thee will the blushes of love conceal the true <choice>
                            <orig>colour</orig>
                            <reg>color</reg>
                        </choice> of her mind</l>
                    <l>Hath she learning? it is good, so that <hi rend="underline">modest</hi>y go
                        with it:</l>
                    <l>Hath she wisdom? is it precious, <note type="authorial" place="inline"
                            resp="#h2">(</note>but beware that though exceed;<note type="authorial"
                            place="inline" resp="#h2">)</note></l>
                    <l>For woman must be subject, and the true mastery is of the mind.</l>
                    <l><note type="authorial" place="inline" resp="#h2">(</note>Be joined to thine
                        equal in rank, or the foot of pride will kick at thee:<note type="authorial"
                            place="inline" resp="#h2">)</note></l>
                    <l>And look not only for riches, lest thou be mated with misery:</l>
                    <l>Marry not without means; for so shouldst thou tempt Providence;</l>
                </lg>
            </div1>


            <div1>


                <pb xml:id="leaf011v" facs="unl_sg.00013.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-left">106</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top">PROVERBIAL PHILOSOPHY.</fw>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>But wait not for more than enough; for marriage is the duty of most men;</l>
                    <l>Grievous indeed must be the burden that shall outweigh innocence and
                        health,</l>
                    <l>And a well-assorted marriage hath not many cares.</l>
                    <l>In the day of thy joy consider the poor; thou shalt reap a rich harvest of
                        blessing;</l>
                    <l>For these be the pensioners of One who filleth up thy cup with pleasures;</l>
                    <l>In the day of thy joy be thankful; He hath well deserved thy praise;</l>
                    <l>Mean and selfish is the heart that seeketh him only sorrow.</l>
                    <l>For her sake, who leaneth on thine arm, court not the notice of the
                        world,</l>
                    <l>And remember that so<hi rend="underline">ber</hi> pri<hi rend="underline"
                            >va</hi>cy is c<hi rend="underline">ome</hi>lier than public <hi
                            rend="underline">dis</hi>play.</l>
                    <l>If thou marriest, thou art allied unto strangers: see they be not such as
                        shame thee:</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Bride and bridgegroom, <note type="authorial" place="inline" resp="#h2"
                            >(</note>pilgrims of life,<note type="authorial" place="inline"
                            resp="#h2">)</note> henceforward to travel together,</l>
                    <l>In this the beginning of your journey, <note type="authorial" place="inline"
                            resp="#h2">(</note>neglect not the favour of Heaven:<note
                            type="authorial" place="inline" resp="#h2">)</note></l>
                    <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="s37" from="s37" to="#s38"/>
                    <l>And at eventide k<hi rend="underline">ne</hi>el ye to<hi rend="underline"
                            >geth</hi>er, that yo<hi rend="underline">ur</hi> joy be not
                        unhallowed:</l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s38"/>
                    <l>Angels that are round you shall be glad, those loving ministers of mercy,</l>
                    <l>And the richest blessings of your God shall be poured on his <choice>
                            <orig>favoured</orig>
                            <reg>favored</reg>
                        </choice> children.</l>
                    <l>Marriage is a figure and an earnest of holier things unseen,</l>
                    <l>And reverence well becometh the symbol of dignity and glory.</l>
                    <l>Keep thy heart pure, lest thou do <choice>
                            <orig>dishonour</orig>
                        <reg>dishonor</reg></choice> to thy state;</l>
                    <l>Selfishness is base and hateful; but love considereth not itself.</l>
                    <l>The wicked turneth good into evil, for his mind is warped within him:</l>
                    <l>But the heart of the righteous is chaste; his conscience casteth off sin.</l>
                    <l>If th<hi rend="underline">ou</hi> <hi rend="underline">wilt</hi> be <hi rend="underline">lov</hi>ed, <hi rend="underline">rend</hi>er imp<hi rend="underline">lic</hi>it con<hi rend="underline">fiden</hi>ce;</l>
                    <l>If thou wouldst not suspect, receive full confidence in turn:</l>
                    <l>For where trust is not reciprocal, the love that trusted withereth.</l>
                    <l>Hid<hi rend="underline">e no</hi>t your <hi rend="underline">gri</hi>ef nor
                        your <hi rend="underline">gladne</hi>ss; be<hi rend="underline"> open</hi>
                        one wi<hi rend="underline">th the other</hi>,</l>
                    <l>Let bitterness be strange unto your tongues, but sympathy a dweller in your
                        hearts:</l>
                    <l>Imparting halveth the evils, while it is doubleth the pleasures of life,</l>
                    <l>But sorrows breed and thicken in the gloomy bosom of Reserve.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Young wife, be not forward, nor forget that modesty becometh thee:</l>
                    <l>If it be discarded now, who will not hold it feigned before?</l>
                    <l>But be not as a timid,&#8212;there is <choice>
                            <orig>honour</orig>
                            <reg>honor</reg>
                        </choice> due to thine estate;</l>
                </lg>
            </div1>


            <div1>


                <pb xml:id="leaf012r" facs="unl_sg.00014.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top">OF EDUCATION.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-right">107</fw>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><note type="authorial" place="inline" resp="#h2">(</note>A matron's modesty
                        is dignified:<note type="authorial" place="inline" resp="#h2">)</note></l>
                    <l>Be kind to the friends of thine husband, for the love they have to him:</l>
                    <l>And gently bear with his infirmities; has thou no need of his
                        forbearance?</l>
                    <l><note type="authorial" place="inline" resp="#h2">(</note>Be not always in
                        each other's company;<note type="authorial" place="inline" resp="#h2"
                            >)</note>
                        <note type="authorial" place="inline" resp="#h2">(</note>it is often good to
                        be alone;<note type="authorial" place="inline" resp="#h2">)</note></l>
                    <l><span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s39" from="s39" to="#s40"
                        />And if there be too much sameness, <note type="authorial" place="inline"
                            resp="#h2">(</note>ye cannot but grow weary of each other:<note
                            type="authorial" place="inline" resp="#h2">)</note></l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s40"/>
                    <l>Ye have each a soul to be nourished, and a mind to be taught in wisdom,</l>
                    <l>Therefore, as accountable for time, help one another to improve it.</l>
                    <l><span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s41" from="s41" to="#s42"/>If
                        ye feel love to decline, track out quickly the secret cause; <note
                            type="authorial" place="inline" resp="#h2">&#8212;</note></l>
                    <l><span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="s43" from="s43" to="#s42"
                        />Let it not rankle for a day, but <hi rend="underline">con</hi>fess and
                            b<hi rend="underline">ew</hi>ail it to<hi rend="underline"
                        >get</hi>her:</l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s42"/>
                    <l>Speedily seek to be reconciled, for l<hi rend="underline">ov</hi>e is the <hi
                            rend="underline">life </hi>of m<hi rend="underline">arri</hi>age;</l>
                    <l>And be ye co-partners in triumph, conquering the peevishness of self.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s44" from="s44" to="#s45"
                        />Let no one have thy confidence, O wife, saving they husband:<note
                            type="authorial" place="inline" resp="#h2">&#8212;</note></l>
                    <l>Have not a friend more intimate,<span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h2"
                            xml:id="s46" from="s46" to="#s45"/>O husband, than thy wife.<anchor
                            xml:id="s45"/></l>
                    <l>In the joy of a well-ordered home, be warned that this is not your rest;</l>
                    <l>For the substance to come may be forgotten in the present beauty of the
                        shadow.</l>
                    <l>If ye are blessed with children, ye have a fearful pleasure,</l>
                    <l>A deeper care and a higher joy, and the range of your existence is
                        widened.</l>
                    <l>If God in wisdom refused them, thank him for an unknown mercy:</l>
                    <l>For how can ye tell if they might be a blessing or a curse?</l>
                    <l>Yet ye may pray, like Hannah, simply dependent on his will:</l>
                    <l>Resignation sweeteneth the cup, but impatience dasheth it with vinegar.</l>
                    <l>Now this is the sum of the matter:&#8212;if ye will be happy in marriage,</l>
                    <l>Confide, love, and be patient: be faithful, firm, and holy.</l>
                </lg>

                <note type="authorial" place="center" resp="#h2"><milestone unit="undeclared"
                        rend="horbar-full"/></note>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

            </div1>

            <div1>

                <head>OF EDUCATION.</head>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><hi rend="smallcaps">A BABE</hi> in a house is a well-spring of pleasure, a
                        messenger of peace and love:</l>
                    <l>A resting-place for innocence on earth; a link between angels and men:</l>
                    <l>Yet is it a talent of trust, a loan to be rendered back with interest;</l>
                    <l>A delight, but redolent of care; honey-sweet, but lacking not the bitter.</l>
                    <l>For character groweth day by day, and all things aid it in unfolding,</l>
                </lg>

            </div1>

            <div1>

                <pb xml:id="leaf013v" facs="unl_sg.00015.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-left">118</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top">PROVERBIAL PHILOSOPHY.</fw>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>I turned aside to weep; I lost him a little while:</l>
                    <l>I looked, and years had past: he was hoar with the winter of his age.</l>
                    <l>And what was not his hope? where was the balm for his sadness?</l>
                    <l>The memory of the past was guilt: the feeling of the present, remorse.</l>
                    <l>Then he set his affections on gold, he worshipped the shrine of Mammon.</l>
                    <l>And to lay richer gifts before his idol, he starved his own bowels;</l>
                    <l>So, the youth spent in profligacy ended in the gripings of want:</l>
                    <l>The miser grudged himself husks, to take deeper vengeance of the
                        prodigal.</l>
                    <l>And I said, this is sorrow; but pity cannot reach it.</l>
                    <l>This is to be wretched indeed, to be guilty without repentance</l>
                </lg>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

            </div1>

            <div1>

                <head><note type="authorial" place="inline" resp="#h2">&#43;</note>OF JOY.</head>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><hi rend="smallcaps">MY</hi> soul was sickened within me, so I sought the
                        dwelling-place of Joy</l>
                    <l>And I met it not in laughter; I found it not in wealth or power;</l>
                    <l>But I saw it in the pleasant home, where religion smiled upon content,</l>
                    <l>And the satisfied ambition of the heart rejoiced in the <choice>
                            <orig>favour</orig>
                            <reg>favor</reg>
                        </choice> of its God.</l>
                    <l>Behold the happy man, his face is rayed with pleasure,</l>
                    <l>His thoughts are of calm delight, and none can know his blessedness;</l>
                    <l>I have watched him from his infancy, and seen him in the grasp of death,</l>
                    <l>Yet never have I noted on his brow the cloud of desponding sorrow.</l>
                    <l>He hath knelt beside his cradle; his mother's hymn lulled him to sleep:</l>
                    <l>In childhood he hath loved holiness, and drank from that fountain-head of
                        peace.</l>
                    <l>Wisdom took him for her scholar, guiding his steps in purity:</l>
                    <l>He lived unpolluted by the world; and his young heart hated sin.</l>
                    <l>But he owned not the spurious religion engendered of faction and
                        moroseness,</l>
                    <l>Neither were the sproutings of his soul seared by the brand of
                        superstition.</l>
                    <l>His love is pure and single, sincere, and knoweth not change:</l>
                    <l>Behold his one beloved, she leaneth on his arm,</l>
                </lg>

            </div1>


            <div1>


                <pb xml:id="leaf014r" facs="unl_sg.00016.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top">OF JOY.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-right">119</fw>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>And he looketh on the years that are past, to review the dawn of her
                        affection.</l>
                    <l>Memory is sweet unto him as a perfect landscape to the sight;</l>
                    <l>Each object is lovely in itself, but the whole is the harmony of nature.</l>
                    <l>Behold his little ones around him, they bask in the sunshine of his smile</l>
                    <l>And infant innocence and joy lighten their happy faces;</l>
                    <l>He is holy, and they <choice>
                            <orig>honour</orig>
                            <reg>honor</reg>
                        </choice> him; he is loving, and they love him;</l>
                    <l>He is consistent, and they esteem him; he is firm, and they fear him.</l>
                    <l>His friends are the excellent among men; and the bands of their friendships
                        are strong;</l>
                    <l>His house is the palace of peace: for the Prince of Peace is there.</l>
                    <l>As the wearied man to his couch, as the thoughtful man to his musings,</l>
                    <l>And though he often sin, he returneth with weeping eyes:</l>
                    <l>For he feeleth the mercies of forgiveness, and gloweth with warmer
                        gratitude.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza" xml:id="lg1">
                    <l><hi rend="circled">Thus did he walk in happiness, and sorrow was a stranger
                            to his soul;</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled">The light of affection sunned his heart, the tear of the
                            grateful bedewed his feet,</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled">He put his hand with constancy to good, and angels knew
                            him as a brother,</hi></l>
                    <note type="authorial" place="right" resp="#h1">&#10003;</note>
                    <l><hi rend="circled">And the busy satellites of evil trembled as at God's
                            ally:</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled">He used his wealth as a wise steward, making him friends
                            for futurity;</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled">He bent his learning to religion, and religion was with
                            him at the last:</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled">For I saw him after many days, when the time of his
                            release was come.</hi></l>
                    <note type="authorial" place="right" resp="#h1">&#10003;</note>
                    <l><hi rend="circled">And I longed for a congregated world, to behold that dying
                            saint.</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled">As the aloe is green and well-liking, till the last best
                            summer of its age,</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled">And then hangeth out its golden bells to mingle glory with
                            corruption;</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled">As a meteor travelleth in <choice>
                                <orig>splendour</orig>
                                <reg>splendor</reg>
                            </choice>, but bursteth in dazzling light;</hi></l>
                    <note type="authorial" place="right" resp="#h1">&#10003;</note>
                    <l><hi rend="circled">Such was the end of the righteous: his death was the sun
                            at his setting.</hi></l>
                </lg>

                <note type="authorial" place="right" resp="#h1" target="#lg1">True</note>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Look on this picture of joy, and remember that portrait of sorrow:</l>
                    <l>Behold the beauty of holiness, behold the deformity of sin!</l>
                    <l>How long, ye sons of men, will ye scorn the words of wisdom?</l>
                    <l>How long will ye hunt for happiness in the caverns that breed despair?</l>
                    <l>Will ye comfort yourselves in misery, by denying the existence of
                        delight,</l>
                    <l>And from experience in woe, will <choice>
                            <sic>ve</sic>
                            <corr>ye</corr>
                        </choice> reason that none are happy?</l>
                </lg>
            </div1>


            <div1>

                <pb xml:id="leaf015v" facs="unl_sg.00017.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-left">166</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top">PROVERBIAL PHILOSOPHY.</fw>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>And, even like as exiles of idolatry, should quaff from the cisterns of
                        creation</l>
                    <l>Stagnant draughts, for those fresh springs that rise in the Creator.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Only, being burthened with the body, spiritual appetite is warped,</l>
                    <l>And sensual man, with taste corrupted, drinketh of pollutions:</l>
                    <l>Impulse is left, but indiscriminate; his hunger feasteth upon carrion;</l>
                    <l>His natural love of beauty doteth over beauty in decay.</l>
                    <l>He still thirsteth for the beautiful; but his delicate ideal hath grown
                        gross,</l>
                    <l>And the very sense of thirst hath been fevered from affection into
                        passion.</l>
                    <l>He remembereth the blessedness of light, but it is with an old man's
                        memory,</l>
                    <l>A blind old man from infancy, that once hath seen the sun,</l>
                    <l>Whom long experience of night hath darkened in his cradle recollections,</l>
                    <l>Until his brightest thought of noon is but a shade of black.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>This then is thy charm, O beauty, all pervading;</l>
                    <l>And this thy wondrous strength, O beauty, conqueror of all:</l>
                    <l>The outline of our shadowy best, the pure and comely creature,</l>
                    <l>That winneth on the conscience with a saddening admiration:</l>
                    <l>And some untutored thirst for God, the root of every pleasure,</l>
                    <l>Native to creatures, yea in ruin, and dating from the birthday of the
                        soul.</l>
                    <l>For God sealeth up the sum, confirmed exemplar of proportions,</l>
                    <l>Rich in love, full of wisdom, and perfect in the pentitude of Beauty. (8)</l>
                </lg>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

            </div1>

            <div1>

                <head>OF FAME.</head>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="s47" from="s47" to="#s48"/>
                    <span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="s49" from="s49" to="#s48"/>
                    <l><hi rend="smallcaps">BLOW</hi> the trumpet, spread the wing, fling thy scroll
                        upon the sky,</l>
                    <l>Rouse the slumbering world, O Fame, and fill the sphere with echo:</l>
                    <l>&#8212;Beneath thy blast they wake, and murmurs come hoarsely on the
                        wind,</l>
                    <l>And flashing eyes and bristling hands proclaim they hear thy message:</l>
                    <l>Rolling and surging as a sea, that upturned flood of faces</l>
                    <l>Hasteneth with its million tongues to spread the wondrous tale;</l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s48"/>
                </lg>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="bottom">&#10003;</note>

            </div1>




            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf016r" facs="unl_sg.00018.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top">OF NEGLECT.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-right">179</fw>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Alas, thou <choice>
                            <sic>nast</sic>
                            <corr>hast</corr>
                        </choice> a juster grief, defrauded of their kindness:</l>
                    <l>It is a theme for tears to feel the soft heart hardening,</l>
                    <l>The frozen breath of apathy sealing up the fountain of affection;</l>
                    <l>It is a pang keen only to the best, to be injured well-deserving,</l>
                    <l>And slumbering Neglect is injury,&#8212;could ye not watch one hour?</l>
                    <l>When God himself complained, it was that none regarded,</l>
                    <l>And indifference bowed to the rebuke, Thou gavest Me no kiss when I came
                        in.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s80" from="s80" to="#s81"/>
                    <l>Moreover, praise is good; <choice>
                            <orig>honour</orig>
                            <reg>honor</reg>
                        </choice> is a treasure to be hoarded;</l>
                    <l>A good man's praise foreshadoweth God's, and in His smile is heaven:</l>
                    <l>But men walk on in hardihood, steeling their sinfulness to censure,</l>
                    <l>And where rebuke is ridiculed, the love of praise were an infirmity;</l>
                    <l>The judge thou heedest not in fear, cannot have deep homage of thy hope,</l>
                    <l>And who then is the wise of this world, that will own he trembleth at his
                        fellows?</l>
                    <l>Calm, careless, and insensible, he mocketh blame or calumny,</l>
                    <l>Neither should his dignity be humbled to some pittance of their praise:</l>
                    <l>The rather, let false pride affect to trample on the treasure</l>
                    <l>Which evermore in secret strength unconquered Nature prizeth;</l>
                    <l>Rather, shall he stifle now the rising bliss of triumph,</l>
                    <l>Lest after, in the world's Neglect, he must acknowledge bitterness.</l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s81"/>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s82" from="s82" to="#s83"/>
                    <l>For lo, that world is wide, a huge and crowded continent,</l>
                    <l>Its brazen sun is mammon, and its iron soil is care,</l>
                    <l>A world full of men, where each man clingeth to his idol;</l>
                    <l>A world full of men, where each man cherisheth his sorrow;</l>
                    <l>A world full of men, multitude shoaling upon multitude;</l>
                    <l>A surging sea, where every wave is burdened with an argosy of self;</l>
                    <l>A boundless beach, where every stone is a separate microscopic world;</l>
                    <l>A forest of innumerable trees, where every root is independent.</l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s83"/>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>What then is the marvel or the shame, if units be lost among the million?</l>
                    <l>Canst thou reasonably murmur, if a leaf drop off unnoticed?</l>
                    <l>Wondrous in architecture, intricate and beautiful, delicately tinged and
                        scented,</l>
                    <l>Exquisite of feeling and mysterious in life, none cared for its growth, or
                        its decay:</l>
                    <l>None? yea,&#8212;no one of its fellows,&#8212;nor cedar, palm, nor
                        bramble&#8212;</l>
                </lg>

            </div1>





            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf017v" facs="unl_sg.00019.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-left">184</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top">PROVERBIAL PHILOSOPHY.</fw>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Where is the sick untended, or in prison, and they visited him not?</l>
                    <l>The hungry is fed, and the thirsty satisfied, till ability set limits to the
                        will,</l>
                    <l>And those who did it unto them, have done it unto God!</l>
                    <l>For human benevolence is large, though many matters dwarf it,</l>
                    <l>Prudence, ignorance, imposture, and the straitenings of circumstance and
                        time.</l>
                    <l>And if to the body, so to the mind, the mass of men are generous:</l>
                    <l>Their estimate who know us best, is seldom seen to err:</l>
                    <l>Be sure the fault is thine, as pride, or shallowness, or vanity,</l>
                    <l>If all around thee, good and bad, neglect thy seeming merit:</l>
                    <l>No man yet deserved, who found not some to love him;</l>
                    <l>And he that never kept a friend need only blame himself:</l>
                    <l>Many for unworthiness will droop and die, but all are not unworthy;</l>
                    <l>It must indeed be cold clay soil that killeth every seed.</l>
                    <l>Therefore examine thy state, O self-accounted martyr of Neglect,</l>
                    <l>It may be, thy merit is a cubit, and thy measure thereof a furlong:</l>
                    <l>But grant it greater than thy thoughts, and grant that men thy fellows</l>
                    <l>For pleasure, business, or interest, misuse, forget, neglect thee,&#8212;</l>
                    <l>Still be thou conqueror in this, the consciousness of high deservings;</l>
                    <l>Let it suffice thee to be worthy; faint not thou for praise;</l>
                    <l>For that thou art, be grateful; go humbly even in thy confidence;</l>
                    <l>And set thy foot on the neck of an enemy so harmless as Neglect.</l>
                </lg>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

            </div1>

            <div1>

                <head>OF CONTENTMENT.</head>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><hi rend="smallcaps">GODLINESS</hi>with Contentment,&#8212;these be the
                        pillars of felicity,<note type="authorial" place="inline" resp="#h2"
                            >)</note></l>
                    <l>Jachin, wherewithal it is established, and Boaz, in the which is
                        strength:(13)</l>
                    <l>And upon their capitals is lily-work, the lotus fruit and flower,</l>
                    <l>Those fair and fragrant types of holiness, innocence, and beauty;</l>
                    <l>Great gain pertaineth to the pillars, nets and chains of wreathen gold,</l>
                    <l>And thy stand up straight in the temple porch, the house where Glory
                        dwelleth.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>The body craveth meats, and the spirit is athirst for peacefulness;</l>
                    <l>He that hath these, hath enough; for all beyond is vanity.</l>
                </lg>

            </div1>



            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf018r" facs="unl_sg.00020.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top">OF HONESTY.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-right">227</fw>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>For, in a simple village church, among those classic shades</l>
                    <l>Which sylvan Evelyn loved to rear, (his praise and my delight,)</l>
                    <l>These, the words of truth, are writ upon his sepulchre</l>
                    <l>Who learnt much lore, and knew all trees from the cedar to the hyssop on the
                        wall.</l>
                    <l>A just conjunction, godliness and honesty, ministering to both worlds,</l>
                    <l>Well wed, and ill to be divided, a pair that God hath joined together.</l>
                    <span rend="curlyBrace-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s50" from="s50" to="#s51"/>
                    <l>I touch not now the vulgar thought, as of tricks and cheateries in trade;</l>
                    <l>I speak of honest purpose, character, speech and action:</l>
                    <l>For an honest man hath special need of charity, and prudence,</l>
                    <l>If a deep and humbling self-acquaintance, and of blessed commerce with his
                        God,</l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s51"/>
                    <l>So that the keennesses of truth may be freed from asperities of censure,</l>
                    <l>And the just but vacillating mind be not made the pendulum of arguments:</l>
                    <l>For a false reason, shrewdly put, can often not be answered on the
                        instant,</l>
                    <l>And prudence looketh unto faith, content to wait solutions:</l>
                    <l>Yea, it looketh, yea, it waiteth, still holding honesty in leash,</l>
                    <l>Lest, as a hot young hound, it track not game, but vermin.</l>
                    <l>Many a man of honest heart, but ignorant of self and God,</l>
                    <l>Hath followed the marsh-fires of pestilence, esteeming them the lights of
                        truth;</l>
                    <l>He heard a cause which he had not skill to solve,&#8212;and so received it
                        gladly,</l>
                    <l>And that cause brought its consequence of harm to an unstable soul.</l>
                    <l>Prudence for a man's own sake, never should be separate from honesty</l>
                    <l>And charity, for other's good and his, must still be joined therewith:</l>
                    <l>For the harshly chiding tongue hath neither pleasuring nor profit,</l>
                    <l>And the cold unsympathizing heart never gained a good.</l>
                    <l>Sin is a sore, and folly is a fever; touch them tenderly for healing;</l>
                    <l>The bad chirurgeon's awkward knife harmeth spite of honesty.</l>
                    <l>Still, a rough diamond is better than the polished paste,&#8212;</l>
                    <l>That courteous flattering foll, who spake of vice as virtue:</l>
                    <l>And honesty, even by itself, though making many adversaries,</l>
                    <l>Whom prudence might have set aside, or charity have softened,</l>
                    <l>Evermore will prosper at the last, and gain a man great <choice>
                            <orig>honour</orig>
                            <reg>honor</reg>
                        </choice></l>
                    <l>By giving others many goods, to his own cost and hindrance.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Freedom is father of the honest, and sturdy Independence is his brother:</l>
                    <l>These three, with heart and hand, dwell together in unity.</l>
                </lg>

            </div1>



            <div1>

                <pb xml:id="leaf019v" facs="unl_sg.00021.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-left">242</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top">PROVERBIAL PHILOSOPHY.</fw>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>I have shown thee thy captivity to Law; yet bade thee hide Humilities;</l>
                    <l>I have lifted the curtains of Memory; and smoothed the soft pillow of
                        Rest.</l>
                    <l>Experience had his sober hour; and Character its keen appreciation;</l>
                    <l>And holy Anger stood sublime, where Hatred fell condemned.</l>
                    <l>Prayer spake the mind of God, even in his own good words;</l>
                    <l>And Zeal, with kindness warmly mixt, allied him top Discretion.</l>
                    <l>I led three with the Train of Religion, to be dazzled at the name of the
                        Triune.</l>
                    <l>Thought confessed his unseen fears; and Speech declared his triumphs;</l>
                    <l>I sang the blessedness of books; and commended the prudence of a letter;</l>
                    <l>Riches found their room, either unto <choice>
                            <orig>honour</orig>
                            <reg>honor</reg>
                        </choice>&#8212;or despising;</l>
                    <l>Inventions took their lower place, for all things come of God.</l>
                    <l>I scorned Ridicule; nor would humble me for Praise; for I had gained
                        Self-knowledge;</l>
                    <l>And pleased fervently for Brutes, who suffer for man's sin.</l>
                    <l>Then, I rose to Friendship; and bathed in all the tenderness of Love;</l>
                    <l>Knew the purity of Marriage: and blessed the face of Children.</l>
                    <l>And whereas by petulance or pride, I had haply said some evil,</l>
                    <l>Mine after-thought was Tolerance, to bear the faults of all:</l>
                    <l>Many faults, ill to hear, bred the theme of Sorrow;</l>
                    <l>Many virtues, dear to see, induced the gush of Joy.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <span rend="curlyBrace-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s52" from="s52" to="#s53"/>
                    <l>Thus, for a while, as leaving thee in joy, was I loth to break that
                        spell;</l>
                    <l>I roamed to other things and thoughts, and fashioned other books.</l>
                    <l>But in a season of reflection, after many days,</l>
                    <l>A thought stood before me in its garment of the past,&#8212;and lo, a legion
                        with it!</l>
                    <l>They came in thronging bands,&#8212;I could not fight nor fly
                        them,&#8212;</l>
                    <l>And so they took me to their tent, the prisoner of thoughts.</l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s53"/>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Then, I bade thee greet me well, and heed my cheerful counsels;</l>
                    <l>For every day we have a Friend, who changeth not with time.</l>
                    <l>Gladly did I speak of my commission, for I felt it graven on my heart,</l>
                    <l>And could not hold my wiser peace, but magnified mine office.</l>
                    <l>Mystery had left her echoes in my mind, and I discoursed her secret:</l>
                    <l>And thence I turned aside to Man, and judged him for his Gifts.</l>
                    <l>Beauty, noble thesis, had a world of sweets to sing of,</l>
                </lg>
            </div1>



            <div1>


                <pb xml:id="leaf020r" facs="unl_sg.00022.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top">NATURE'S NOBLEMAN.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-right">261</fw>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>For ever young,&#8212;though life's old age</l>
                    <l>Hath every nerve unstrung:</l>
                    <l>The heart, the heart is a heritage</l>
                    <l>That keeps the old man young!</l>
                </lg>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

            </div1>

            <div1>

                <head>NATURE'S NOBLEMAN.</head>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><note type="authorial" place="inline" resp="#h2">(</note><hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >AWAY</hi> with false fashion,<note type="authorial" place="inline"
                            resp="#h2">)</note> so calm and so chill,</l>
                    <l>Where pleasure itself cannot please;</l>
                    <l>Away with cold breeding, that faithlessly still</l>
                    <l>Affects to be quite at its ease;</l>
                    <l>For the deepest in feeling is highest in rank,</l>
                    <l>The freest is first in the band,</l>
                    <l><note type="authorial" place="inline" resp="#h2">(</note>And nature's own
                        Nobleman, friendly and frank,</l>
                    <l>Is a man with his heart in his hand!<note type="authorial" place="inline"
                            resp="#h2">)</note></l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Fearless in honesty, gentle yet just,</l>
                    <l>He warmly can love,&#8212;and can hate,</l>
                    <l>Nor will he bow down with his face in the dust</l>
                    <l>To Fashion's intolerant state:</l>
                    <l>For best in good breeding, and highest in rank,</l>
                    <l>Though lowly or poor in the land,</l>
                    <l>Is nature's own Nobleman, friendly and frank,</l>
                    <l>The man with his heart in his hand!</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><hi rend="italic">His</hi> fashion is passion, sincere and intense,</l>
                    <l><hi rend="italic">His</hi> impulses, simple and true,</l>
                    <l>Yet tempered by judgment, and taught by good sense,</l>
                    <l>And cordial with me, and with you:</l>
                    <l>For the finest in manners, as highest in rank,</l>
                    <l>It is <hi rend="italic">you</hi>, man! or <hi rend="italic">you</hi>, man!
                        who stand</l>
                    <l>Nature's own Nobleman, friendly and frank,&#8212;</l>
                    <l>A man with his heart in his hand!</l>
                </lg>

            </div1>



            <div1>

                <pb xml:id="leaf020v" facs="unl_sg.00023.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-left">262</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top">A THOUSAND LINES.</fw>

                <head>N<hi rend="underline">E</hi>VER G<hi rend="underline">I</hi>VE <hi
                        rend="underline">U</hi>P.</head>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s54" from="s54" to="#s55"/>
                    <l><hi rend="smallcaps">NEVER</hi> give up! it is wiser and better</l>
                    <l>Always to hope, than once to despair;</l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s55"/>
                    <l>Fling off the load of Doubt's cankering fetter,</l>
                    <l>And break the dark spell of tyrannical care:</l>
                    <l>Never give up! or the burthen may sink you,&#8212;</l>
                    <l>Providence kindly has mingled the cup,</l>
                    <l>And in all trials or troubles, bethink you,</l>
                    <l><note type="authorial" place="inline" resp="#h2">(</note>The watchword of
                        life must be, Never give up!<note type="authorial" place="inline" resp="#h2"
                            >)</note></l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Never give up! there are chances and changes</l>
                    <l>Helping the hopeful, a hundred to one,</l>
                    <l>And through the chaos High Wisdom arranges</l>
                    <l>Ever success,&#8212;if you'll only hope on:</l>
                    <l>Never give up! for the wisest is boldest,</l>
                    <l>Knowing that Providence mingles the cup,</l>
                    <l>And of all maxims the best, as the oldest,</l>
                    <l>Is the true watchword of Never give up!</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Never give up!&#8212;though the grape-shot may rattle,</l>
                    <l>Or the full thunder-cloud over you burst,</l>
                    <l>Stand like a rock,&#8212;and the storm or the battle</l>
                    <l>Little shall harm you, though doing their worst:</l>
                    <l>Never give up!&#8212;if adversity presses,</l>
                    <l>Providence wisely has mingled the cup,</l>
                    <l>And the best counsel, in all your distresses,</l>
                    <l>Is the stout watchword of Never give up!</l>
                </lg>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

            </div1>

            <div1>

                <head>THE SUN.</head>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><hi rend="smallcaps">BLAME</hi> not, ye million worshippers of
                        gold&#8212;</l>
                    <l>Modern idolaters&#8212;their works and ways,</l>
                    <l>When Asia's children, in the times of old,</l>
                    <l>Knelt to the sun, outpouring prayer and praise</l>
                </lg>

            </div1>



            <div1>


                <pb xml:id="leaf021r" facs="unl_sg.00024.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top">FORGIVE AND FORGET.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-right">265</fw>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>And Meekness is writhing in torment and thrall,</l>
                    <l>By the hands of Ingratitude wrung,&#8212;</l>
                    <l>In the heat of injustice, unwept and unfair,</l>
                    <l>While the anguish is festering yet,</l>
                    <l><note type="authorial" place="inline" resp="#h2">(</note>None, none but an
                        angel, or God, can declare?<note type="authorial" place="inline" resp="#h2"
                            >)</note></l>
                    <l><hi rend="underline">"I now can forgive and forget."</hi></l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>But, if the bad spirit is chased from the heart,</l>
                    <l>And the lips are in penitence steep'd,</l>
                    <l>With the wrong so repented the wrath will depart,</l>
                    <l>Though scorn on injustice were heaped;</l>
                    <l>For the best compensation is paid for all ill,</l>
                    <l>When the cheek with contrition is wet,</l>
                    <l>And every one feels it is possible still,</l>
                    <l>At once to forgive and forget.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l> To forget? It is hard for a man with a mind,</l>
                    <l>However his heart may forgive,</l>
                    <l>To blot out all perils and dangers behind,</l>
                    <l>And but for the future to live:</l>
                    <l>Then how shall it be? for at every turn</l>
                    <l>Recollection the spirit will fret,</l>
                    <l>And the ashes of injury <choice>
                            <orig>smoulder</orig>
                            <reg>smolder</reg>
                        </choice> and burn,</l>
                    <l>Though we strive to forgive and forget.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Oh, hearken! my tongue shall the riddle unseal,</l>
                    <l>And mind shall be partner with heart,</l>
                    <l>While thee to thyself I bid conscience reveal,</l>
                    <l>And show thee how evil thou art:</l>
                    <l>Remember thy follies, thy sins, and&#8212;thy crimes,</l>
                    <l>How vast is that infinite debt!</l>
                    <l><note type="authorial" place="inline" resp="#h2">(</note>Yet Mercy hath seven
                        by seventy times</l>
                    <l><hi rend="underline">Been swift to forgive and forget!</hi><note
                            type="authorial" place="inline" resp="#h2">)</note></l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Brood not on insults or injuries old,</l>
                    <l>For thou art injurious too,&#8212;</l>
                    <l>Count not their sum till the total is told,</l>
                    <l>For thou art unkind and untrue:</l>
                </lg>

                <fw type="sig" place="bottom">12</fw>

            </div1>



            <div1>


                <pb xml:id="leaf022r" facs="unl_sg.00037.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top">MY MIND'S KINGDOM.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-right">269</fw>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>From thy throne in some bright sphere</l>
                    <l>On this poor brother grovelling here;</l>
                    <l>For I, too, I can stoutly sing</l>
                    <l>I am every inch a king!</l>
                    <l>A king of Thought, a Potentate</l>
                    <l>Of glorious spiritual state,</l>
                    <l>A king of Thought, a king of Mind,</l>
                    <l>Realms unmapp'd and undefined,&#8212;</l>
                    <l>A king! beneath no man's control,</l>
                    <l>Invested with a royal soul,</l>
                    <l>Crown'd by God's imperial hand</l>
                    <l>Before him as a king to stand,</l>
                    <l>And by His wisdom train'd and taught</l>
                    <l>To rule my realm as King of Thought.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>O thoughts,&#8212;how ill my fellow-men,</l>
                    <l>O thoughts,&#8212;how scanty my poor pen</l>
                    <l>Can guess or tell the myriad host</l>
                    <l>Wherewith you crowd my kingdom's coast!</l>
                    <l>For I am hemm'd and throng'd about</l>
                    <l>With your triumphant rabble-rout,</l>
                    <l>Hurried along by that mad flood,</l>
                    <l>The joy-excited <choice>
                            <sic>multitud</sic>
                            <corr>multitude</corr>
                        </choice></l>
                    <l>A conqueror, borne upon the foam,</l>
                    <l>Of his great people's gladness home,</l>
                    <l>A monarch in his grandest state,</l>
                    <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s56" from="s56" to="#s57"/>
                    <l>On whom a thousand thousand wait!</l>
                    <l>Lo! they come&#8212;my Tribes of Thought,</l>
                    <l>Fierce and flush'd and fever-fraught!</l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s57"/>
                    <l>From the horizon all around</l>
                    <l>I hear with pride their coming sound;</l>
                    <l>See! their banners circling near,&#8212;</l>
                    <l>Glittering groves of shield and spear,</l>
                    <l>Flying clouds of troopers gay,</l>
                    <l>Serried lines in dark array,</l>
                    <l>Veterans calm with temper'd sword,</l>
                    <l>And a dishevelled frantic horde,&#8212;</l>
                    <l>On they come with furious force,</l>
                    <l>Tramping foot and thundering horse,</l>
                </lg>

            </div1>



            <div1>

                <pb xml:id="leaf022v" facs="unl_sg.00025.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-left">270</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top">A THOUSAND LINES.</fw>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>On they come, converging loud,</l>
                    <l>With clanging arms, a glorious crowd</l>
                    <l>Shouting impatient, fierce and free,</l>
                    <l>For me, their Monarch, yea, for me!</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Then, in my majesty and power,</l>
                    <l>I quell the madness of the hour,</l>
                    <l>Bid that tumultuous turmoil cease,</l>
                    <l>And frown my multitudes to peace.</l>
                    <l>Each to his peril and his post!</l>
                    <l>All hush'd throughout my might host:</l>
                    <l>Courage clear, and duty stern,&#8212;</l>
                    <l>Heads that freeze and hearts that burn;</l>
                    <l>Marshalled straight in order due,</l>
                    <l>Legions! pass in swift review,</l>
                    <l>Bending to my blazoned will,</l>
                    <l>Loyal to that standard still,</l>
                    <l>And hailing me with homage then</l>
                    <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s58" from="s58" to="#s59"/>
                    <l>King of Thoughts&#8212;and thus, of Men!</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>What? am I powerless to control</l>
                    <l>Nations, by my single soul?</l>
                    <l>What? have I not made thousands thrill</l>
                    <l>By the mere impulse of my will,</l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s59"/>
                    <span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="s60" from="s60" to="#s61"/>
                    <l>When the strong Thought goes forth, and binds</l>
                    <l>Captive a wandering herd of minds?</l>
                    <l>And is not this to reign alone</l>
                    <l>More than the ermine and the throne,</l>
                    <l>The jewelled state, the gilded rooms,</l>
                    <l>The mindless man in borrowed plumes?</l>
                    <l>Yes,&#8212;if Eternity be true,</l>
                    <l>And Time both false and fleeting too,</l>
                    <l>Then, humbler kings, my boast be this,</l>
                    <l>"My mind to me a kingdom is.<choice>
                            <sic>'</sic>
                            <corr>"</corr>
                        </choice></l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s62" from="s62" to="#s63"/>
                    <l>And what, though weak and slow of speech,</l>
                    <l>Ill to comfort, dull to teach?</l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s63"/>
                </lg>

            </div1>


            <div1>


                <pb xml:id="leaf023r" facs="unl_sg.00026.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top">MY MIND'S KINGDOM.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-right">271</fw>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>What, though hiding from the ken</l>
                    <l>Of my small prying fellow-men,&#8212;</l>
                    <l>Still within my musing mind,</l>
                    <l>Wisdom's secret stores I find,</l>
                    <l>And, little noticed, sweetly feed</l>
                    <l>On hidden manna, meat indeed,</l>
                    <l><hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">Blessed thoughts I never told</hi></l>
                    <l>Unconsidered, uncontroll'd,</l>
                    <l>Rushing by as thick and fast</l>
                    <l>As autumn leaves upon the blast:</l>
                    <l>Or better, like the gracious rain</l>
                    <l>Dropping on some thirsty plain.</l>
                    <l>And is not this to be a king,</l>
                    <l>To carry in my heart a spring</l>
                    <l>Of ceaseless pleasures, deep and pure,</l>
                    <l><hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">Wealth cannot buy, nor power
                        procure?</hi></l>
                    <l>Yea,&#8212;by the poet's artless art,</l>
                    <l>And the sweet searchings of his heart,</l>
                    <l>By his unknown, unheeded bliss,</l>
                    <l>"My mind to me a kingdom is."</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Place me on some desert shore</l>
                    <l>Foot of man ne'er wandered o'er;</l>
                    <l>Lock me in a lonely cell</l>
                    <l>Beneath some prison citadel;</l>
                    <l>Still, here or there, within I find</l>
                    <l>My quiet kingdom of the Mind;</l>
                    <l>Nay,&#8212;mid the tempest fierce and dark,</l>
                    <l>Float me on peril's frailest bark,</l>
                    <l>My quenchless soul could sit and think</l>
                    <l>And smile at danger's dizziest brink:</l>
                    <l>And wherefore?&#8212;God, my God, is still</l>
                    <l>King of kings in good and ill;</l>
                    <l>And where dwelleth&#8212;every where&#8212;</l>
                    <l>Safety supreme and peace are there;</l>
                    <l>And where he reigneth&#8212;all around&#8212;</l>
                    <l>Wisdom, and love, and power are found;</l>
                    <l>And reconciled to Him and bliss,</l>
                    <l>"My mind to me a kingdom is."</l>
                </lg>


            </div1>



            <div1>

                <pb xml:id="leaf023v" facs="unl_sg.00027.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-left">272</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top">A THOUSAND LINES.</fw>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Thus for my days; each waking hour</l>
                    <l>Grand with majesty and power,</l>
                    <l>Every minute rich in treasure,</l>
                    <l>Gems of peace, and pearls of pleasure.</l>
                    <l>And for my nights&#8212;those wondrous nights?</l>
                    <l>How manifold my Mind's delights,</l>
                    <l>When the young truant, gladly caught</l>
                    <l>In its own labyrinths of thought,</l>
                    <l>Finds there is another realm to range,</l>
                    <l>The dynasties of Chance and Change.</l>
                    <l>O dreams,&#8212;what know I not of dreams?</l>
                    <l>Their name, their very essence, seems</l>
                    <l>A tender light, not dark nor clear,</l>
                    <l>A sad sweet mystery wild and dear,</l>
                    <l>A dull soft feeling unexplained,</l>
                    <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s64" from="s64" to="#s65"/>
                    <l>A lie half true, a truth half feigned:</l>
                    <l>O dreams,&#8212;what know I not of dreams?</l>
                    <l>When Reason, with inebriate gleams,</l>
                    <l>Loses from his wise control</l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s65"/>
                    <l>The prancing Fancies of the soul,</l>
                    <l>And sober Judgement, slumbering still,</l>
                    <l>Sets free Caprice to guide the Will.</l>
                    <l>Within one night have I not spent</l>
                    <l>Years of adventurous banishment,</l>
                    <l>Strangely groping like the blind</l>
                    <l>In the dark caverns of my mind?</l>
                    <l>Have I not dwelt, from eve till morn,</l>
                    <l>Lifetimes in length for praise or scorn,</l>
                    <l>With fancied joys, ideal woes,</l>
                    <l>And all sensation's warmest glows,</l>
                    <l>Wondrously thus expanding Life</l>
                    <l>Though seeming scenes of peace or strife,</l>
                    <span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="s66" from="s66" to="#s67"/>
                    <l>Until I verily reign sublime,</l>
                    <l>A great creative king of Time?</l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s67"/>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>And there are people, things, and places,</l>
                    <l>Usual themes, familiar faces,</l>
                    <l>A second life, that looks as real</l>
                    <l>As this dull world's own unideal,</l>
                </lg>


            </div1>

            <div1>

                <pb xml:id="leaf024r" facs="unl_sg.00028.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top">BYEGONES.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-right">277</fw>

                <head>HOME.</head>
                <head type="sub">FOR MUSIC.</head>


                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><hi rend="smallcaps">I NEVER</hi> left the place that knew me,</l>
                    <l>And may never know me more,</l>
                    <l>Where the chords of kindness drew me,</l>
                    <l>And have gladdened me of yore,</l>
                    <l>But my secret soul has smarted</l>
                    <l>With a feeling full of gloom</l>
                    <l>For the days that are departed,</l>
                    <l>And the place I call'd my Home.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>I am not of those who wander</l>
                    <l>Unaffectioned here and there,</l>
                    <l>But my heart must still be fonder</l>
                    <l>Of my sites of joy or care;</l>
                    <l>And I point sad memory's finger</l>
                    <l>(Though my faithless foot may roam)</l>
                    <l>Where I've most been made to linger</l>
                    <l>In the place I call'd my Home</l>
                </lg>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

            </div1>

            <div1>

                <head>BYEGONES.</head>
                <head type="sub">FOR MUSIC.</head>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><hi rend="smallcaps">"LET</hi> byegones be byegones,"&#8212;they foolishly
                        say,</l>
                    <l>And bid me be wise and forget them;</l>
                    <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s68" from="s68" to="#s69"/>
                    <l><hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">But old recollections are active
                        to-day,</hi></l>
                    <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="s70" from="s70" to="#s69"/>
                    <l>And I can do nought but regret them;</l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s69"/>
                    <l>Though the present be pleasant, all joyous and gay,</l>
                    <l>And promising well for the morrow,</l>
                    <l>I love to look back on the years past away,</l>
                    <l>Embalming my byegones in sorrow.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>If the morning of life has a mantle of gray,</l>
                    <l>Its noon will be blither and brighter,</l>
                </lg>

            </div1>




            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf024v" facs="unl_sg.00029.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-left">278</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top">A THOUSAND LINES.</fw>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>If March has its storm, there is sunshine in May,</l>
                    <l>And light out of darkness is lighter:</l>
                    <l>Thus the present is pleasant, a cheerful to-day,</l>
                    <l>With a wiser, a soberer gladness,</l>
                    <l><note type="authorial" place="inline" resp="#h2">(</note>Because it is tinged
                        with the mellowing ray</l>
                    <l><hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">Of a yesterday's sunset of sadness.<note
                                type="authorial" place="inline" resp="#h2">)</note></hi></l>
                </lg>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

            </div1>

            <div1>

                <head>RULE, BRITANNIA!</head>
                <head type="sub">A <unclear reason="illegible" cert="medium" resp="#slg"
                        >STI</unclear>RRING SONG FOR PATRIOTS, IN THE YEAR 1860.</head>

                <ab>To the tune of "Wha wouldna fight for Charlie?"</ab>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><hi rend="smallcaps">RISE!</hi> ye gallant youth of Britain,</l>
                    <l>Gather to your country's call,</l>
                    <l>On your hearts he name is written,</l>
                    <l>Rise to help her, one and all!</l>
                    <l>Cast away each feud and faction,</l>
                    <l>Brood not over wrong nor ill,&#8212;</l>
                    <l>Rouse your virtues into action,</l>
                    <l>For we love our country still,&#8212;</l>
                    <l>Hail, Britannia! Rule, Britannia!</l>
                    <l>Raise that thrilling shout once more;</l>
                    <l>Rule, Britannia! Rule, Britannia!</l>
                    <l>Conqueror over sea and shore!</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>France is coming, full of bluster,</l>
                    <l>Hot to wipe away her stain,</l>
                    <l>Therefore, brothers, here we muster</l>
                    <l>Just to give it her again!</l>
                    <l>And if foemen, blind with fury,</l>
                    <l>Dare to cross our ocean-gulf,</l>
                    <l>Wait not then for judge nor jury,&#8212;</l>
                    <l>Shoot them as you would a wolf!</l>
                </lg>


            </div1>

            <div1>

                <pb xml:id="leaf025r" facs="unl_sg.00030.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top">OLD HAUNTS&#8212;THE BATTLE OF ROLEIA.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-right">293</fw>

                <head>OLD HAUNTS.</head>
                <head type="sub">FOR MUSIC.</head>


                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>&#8212;</l>
                    <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="s71" from="s71" to="#s72"/>
                    <l><hi rend="smallcaps">I LOVE</hi> to linger on my track</l>
                    <l>Wherever I have dwelt,</l>
                    <l>In after years to loiter back,</l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s72"/>
                    <l>And feel as once I felt;</l>
                    <l>My foot falls lightly on the sward,</l>
                    <l>Yet leaves a deathless dint,</l>
                    <l>With tenderness I still regard</l>
                    <l>Its unforgotten print.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Old places have a charm for me</l>
                    <l>The new can ne'er attain,</l>
                    <l>Old faces&#8212;how I long to see</l>
                    <l>Their kindly looks again!</l>
                    <l>Yet, these are gone:&#8212;while all around</l>
                    <l>Is changeable as air,</l>
                    <l>I'll anchor in the solid ground,</l>
                    <l>And root my memories there!</l>
                </lg>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

            </div1>

            <div1>

                <head>THE BATTLE OF ROLEIA</head>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><hi rend="smallcaps">YE</hi> children of the veterans</l>
                    <l>Who fought for faithless Spain,</l>
                    <l>And for ungrateful Portugal</l>
                    <l>Pour'd out their blood like rain,&#8212;</l>
                    <l>Come near me, and hear me,</l>
                    <l>For I would tell you well</l>
                    <l>How gallantly your fathers fought,</l>
                    <l>Or gloriously they fell!</l>
                </lg>

            </div1>




            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf026v" facs="unl_sg.00031.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-left">302</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top">HACTENUS.</fw>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>The foe was rushing on his fate</l>
                    <l>At chosen Waterloo.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>What? should the hunter waste his strength,</l>
                    <l>Nor hold his good hounds back</l>
                    <l>Before he knows they near the foes</l>
                    <l>And open on the track?</l>
                    <l>No: let "surprise" blight Frenchmen's eyes,</l>
                    <l>For truly thy shall rue</l>
                    <l>The giant skill that, stern and still,</l>
                    <l>Drew them to Waterloo!</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Hotly the couriers gallop up</l>
                    <l>To Richmond's festive scene,&#8212;</l>
                    <l>Alone, and alone the chieftain stood</l>
                    <l>Undaunted and serene;</l>
                    <l>Ready, ready,&#8212;staunch and steady,&#8212;</l>
                    <l>And forth the orders flew</l>
                    <l>That marched us off to Quatre Bras,</l>
                    <l>And whelming Waterloo.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Begin, begin with Quatre Bras,</l>
                    <l>That twin-born field of fame</l>
                    <l>Where many a gallant name,</l>
                    <l>That battle-field, which seemed to yield</l>
                    <l>An earnest and review</l>
                    <l>And did at Waterloo.</l>
                </lg>


                <note type="authorial" place="center" resp="#h2"><milestone unit="undeclared"
                        rend="horbar-short-center"/></note>


                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>We heard from far old Blucher's guns,</l>
                    <l>At Ligny's blazing street,</l>
                    <l>And hurried on to Weimar's aid,</l>
                    <l>Right glad the foe to meet;</l>
                    <l>A score of miles to Quatre Bras;</l>
                    <l>But still to arms we stood,</l>
                    <l>And cheerly rushed without a pause</l>
                    <l>To win the Boissy wood.</l>
                </lg>
            </div1>



            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf027v" facs="unl_sg.00032.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-left">314</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top">HACTENUS</fw>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>This, this is wisdom, manful and serene,</l>
                    <l>Towards God all penitence and prayer and trust,</l>
                    <l>But to the troubles of this shifting scene</l>
                    <l>Simply courageous and sublimely just:</l>
                    <l>Be then such wisdom thin, my heart within,&#8212;</l>
                    <l>There is no foe nor woe nor grief but&#8212;Sin.</l>
                </lg>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

            </div1>

            <div1>

                <head>THE HEART'S HUSBAND.</head>
                <head type="sub">FOR MUSIC.</head>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><note type="authorial" place="inline" resp="#h2">(</note><hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >GO</hi>, leave me to weep for the years that are past,</l>
                    <l>For my youth, and its friends, and its pleasures all dead,</l>
                    <l>My spring and my summer are fading too fast,</l>
                    <l>And I long to live over the days that are fled;<note type="authorial"
                            place="inline" resp="#h2">)</note></l>
                    <l>It is not for sorrows or sins on my track</l>
                    <l>That I mournfully cast my fond yearnings behind,&#8212;</l>
                    <l>&#8212;Ah, no,&#8212;from affection I love to look back,</l>
                    <l>It is only my heart that has wedded my Mind.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>And still, let the Mind that has married a Heart</l>
                    <l>Though loving, be strong as a King in his pride,</l>
                    <l>And ever command that all weakness depart</l>
                    <l>From the realm that he rules in soul of his bride;</l>
                    <l>For what, if all time and all pleasures decay?</l>
                    <l>My Mind is myself, an invincible chief,&#8212;</l>
                    <l>Like a child's broken toys are the years past away,</l>
                    <l>And my Heart, half-ashamed, has forgotten her grief.</l>
                </lg>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

            </div1>



            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf028v" facs="unl_sg.00033.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-left">328</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top">HACTENUS</fw>

                <ab>II.</ab>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Soft little butterfly-guest of my heart,</l>
                    <l>Whither now flittest thou, spirit of mine?</l>
                    <l>Woe,&#8212;for thy merriment must it depart</l>
                    <l>Naked and frigid and pallid to pine?</l>
                </lg>

                <ab>III.</ab>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Soul, thou tiny truant dear,</l>
                    <l>Bosom friend for many a year,</l>
                    <l>Restless little darling, say,</l>
                    <l>Whither stealest thou away?</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Pallid as a fainting maid,</l>
                    <l>Naked, icy-cold, afraid,</l>
                    <l>Is then all thy wit in vain,&#8212;</l>
                    <l>Shalt thou never laugh again?</l>
                </lg>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

            </div1>


            <div1>

                <head>NO SURRENDER.</head>
                <head type="sub">FOR MUSIC.</head>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><note type="authorial" place="inline" resp="#h2">(</note><hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >EVER</hi> constant, ever true,</l>
                    <l>Let the word be, No surrender;<note type="authorial" place="inline"
                            resp="#h2">)</note></l>
                    <l>Boldly dare and greatly do!</l>
                    <l>This shall bring us bravely through,</l>
                    <l>No surrender, No surrender;</l>
                    <l>And though Fortune's smiles be few</l>
                    <l>Hope is always spring new,</l>
                    <l>Still inspiring me and you</l>
                    <l>With a magic&#8212;No surrender!</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Nail the colors to the mast,</l>
                    <l>Shouting glad, No surrender!</l>
                    <l>Troubles near are all but past&#8212;</l>
                </lg>

            </div1>



            <div1>

                <pb xml:id="leaf029r" facs="unl_sg.00034.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top">ERRATA&#8212;IMPROMPTU.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-right">335</fw>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>The pledge and promise of our Father's love!</l>
                    <l>God guard the babe; and cherish the young child;</l>
                    <l>And bless the boy with nurture wise and mild;</l>
                    <l>And lead the lad, and yearn upon the youth;</l>
                    <l>And make the man a man of trust and truth;</l>
                    <l>Through life and death uphold him all his days,</l>
                    <l>And then translate him to Thyself with praise!</l>
                </lg>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

            </div1>


            <div1>

                <head>ERRATA.</head>
                <head type="sub">AN AUTHOR'S COMPLAINT.</head>

                <note type="authorial" place="right" resp="#h1">&#10003;</note>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><hi rend="circled"><hi rend="smallcaps">O Friends</hi> and brothers, judge me
                            not unheard,</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled">Make not a man offender for a word:</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled">For often have I noted seeming fault</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled">That harm'd my rhymes, and made my reasons halt,</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled">Whilst all that error was some printer's sloth,</hi></l>
                    <note type="authorial" place="right" resp="#h1">&#10003;</note>
                    <l><hi rend="circled">Who, scorning rhyme and reason, slew them both:</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled">Be ye then liberal to your far-off friend</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled">Where garbled, guess him; and where maim'd amend</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled">Trust him for wit, when types have marr'd the
                        word,</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="circled">And wisdom, too, where only blockheads err'd.</hi></l>
                </lg>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

            </div1>


            <div1>

                <head>IMPROMPTU.</head>
                <head type="sub">TO ONE WHO SAID THAT SHE DISLIKED POETRY.</head>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><hi rend="smallcaps">LADY,</hi> thou lovest high and holy Thought,</l>
                    <l>And noble deeds, and hopes sublime or beauteous,</l>
                    <l>Thou lovest charities in secret wrought,</l>
                    <l>And all things pure and generous and duteous;</l>
                </lg>

            </div1>






            <div1>

                <pb xml:id="leaf030r" facs="unl_sg.00035.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top">"THE WARM YOUNG HEART."</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-right">337</fw>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>The star of Charity and Truth,</l>
                    <l>Of cheerful thoughts and sage,</l>
                    <l>The lamp to guide my steps in youth,</l>
                    <l>And gladden mine old age!</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>O brother, yield: thy fiery Mars,</l>
                    <l>For all his mailed might,</l>
                    <l>Is not so strong among the stars</l>
                    <l>As mine, the Queen of night:</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>A Queen to shine all nights away,</l>
                    <l>And make the morn more clear,</l>
                    <l>Contentment gilding everyday,&#8212;</l>
                    <l>&#8212;There is no twilight here!</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Yes; in a trial world like this</l>
                    <l>Where all that comes&#8212;is sent,</l>
                    <l>Learn how divine a thing it is</l>
                    <l>To smile and be content!</l>
                </lg>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

            </div1>


            <div1>

                <head>"THE WARM YOUNG HEART."</head>
                <head type="sub">FOR MUSIC.</head>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><hi rend="smallcaps">A BEAUTIFUL</hi> face, and a form of grace</l>
                    <l>Were a pleasant sight to see,</l>
                    <l>And gold, and gems, and diadems,</l>
                    <l>Right excellent they be:</l>
                    <l>But beauty and gold, tho' both be untold,</l>
                    <l>Are things of a worldly mart,</l>
                    <l><note type="authorial" place="inline" resp="#h2">(</note>The wealth that I
                        prize, above ingots or eyes,</l>
                    <l>Is a heart,&#8212;a warm young heart!<note type="authorial" place="inline"
                            resp="#h2">)</note></l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>O face most fair, shall thy beauty compare</l>
                    <l>With affection's glowing light?</l>
                </lg>

                <fw type="sig" place="bottom">15</fw>

            </div1>









            <div1>

                <pb xml:id="leaf031r" facs="unl_sg.00036.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top">FRIENDS.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-right">347</fw>


                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>My scathed and frozen from,</l>
                    <l>For heart and hand together we'll stand,</l>
                    <l>And mock at the baffled storm,</l>
                    <l>Ha, ha! Together.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>And so when grief is withering the leaf,</l>
                    <l>And checking hope's young flower,</l>
                    <l>And frosts do bite with their teeth so white</l>
                    <l>In disappointment's hour,</l>
                    <l>Tho' it might o'erwhelm either ivy or elm</l>
                    <l>If alone each stood in the strife,</l>
                    <l>If heart and hand together they stand,</l>
                    <l>They may laugh at the troubles of life,</l>
                    <l>Ha, ha! Together.</l>
                </lg>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

            </div1>


            <div1>

                <head>FRIENDS.<note type="authorial" place="inline" resp="#h1">!!</note></head>


                <lg type="stanza">

                    <l><note type="authorial" place="inline" resp="#h1">(</note><hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >I CANNOT</hi> move a mile upon this earth,</l>
                    <l>I could not, did I walk from end to end,</l>
                    <l>But there I find a heart of wit and worth,</l>
                    <l>Some gracious spirit to be hailed a friend:<note type="authorial"
                            place="right" resp="#h1">&#10003;</note></l>
                    <l>O there are frequent angels unawares,</l>
                    <l>And many have I met upon my way,</l>
                    <l>Kind Christian souls, to make me rich with prayers,</l>
                    <l>Whilst in like a coin their mercies I repay;</l>
                    <l>And oft the sun of praise hath lit mine eyes,</l>
                    <l>Generous praise and just encouragement,</l>
                    <l>From some who say I help them to be wise,</l>
                    <l>And teach them to be happy in content:</l>
                    <l>Ah soul, rejoice! for thou hast thickly sown</l>
                    <l>The living world with friendships all thine own.<note type="authorial"
                            place="inline" resp="#h1">)</note></l>

                </lg>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

            </div1>




            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf031v" facs="unl_sg.00038.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-left">396</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top">MISCELLANEOUS POEMS.</fw>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>It is a terrible thing to dream</l>
                    <l>Of strangled throats and heart-blood spilt,</l>
                    <l>And ghosts that in the darkness gleam,</l>
                    <l>And horrid eyes of midnight guilt.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><note type="authorial" place="inline" resp="#h2">(</note>I love a dream, I
                        dread a dream,<note type="authorial" place="inline" resp="#h2">)</note></l>
                    <l>Sometimes all bright and full of gladness,</l>
                    <l>But other times my brain will teem</l>
                    <l>With sights that urge the mind to madness.</l>
                </lg>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

            </div1>


            <div1>

                <head>INFANT CHRIST, WITH A WREATH OF FLOWERS.</head>
                <head type="sub">FROM A PICTURE BY CORREGGIO.</head>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><hi rend="smallcaps">YES,</hi>&#8212;I can fancy, in the spring</l>
                    <l>Of childhood's sunny hours,</l>
                    <l>That nature's infant, priest, and king,</l>
                    <l>Lov'd to gaze on flowers:</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>For lightly, 'mid the wreck of all,</l>
                    <l>When torn from Eden's bowers,</l>
                    <l>Above the billows of the fall</l>
                    <l>Floated gentle flowers.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Unfallen, sinless, undefil'd,</l>
                    <l>Fresh bath'd in summer showers,</l>
                    <l>What wonder that the holy child</l>
                    <l>Lov'd to play with flowers?</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>In these he saw his Father's face,</l>
                    <l>All Godhead's varied powers,</l>
                    <l>And joy'd each attribute to trace</l>
                    <l>In sweet unconscious flowers:</l>
                </lg>

            </div1>

            <div1>

                <pb xml:id="leaf032r" facs="unl_sg.00039.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top">MARRIAGE.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top-right">415</fw>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>You bride,&#8212;a tear for thee!</l>
                    <l>A tear in all thy gladness;</l>
                    <l>For thy young heart shall not see</l>
                    <l>Joy unmix'd with sadness.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Young bride,&#8212;a smile for thee!</l>
                    <l>To shine away thy sorrow,</l>
                    <l>For heaven is kind to-day, and we</l>
                    <l>Will hope as well to-morrow.</l>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Young bride,&#8212;a prayer for thee!</l>
                    <l>That all thy hopes possessing,</l>
                    <l>Thy soul may praise her God, and he</l>
                    <l>May crown thee with his blessing.</l>
                </lg>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

            </div1>


            <div1>

                <head>MARRIAGE.</head>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s73" from="s73" to="#s74"/>
                    <l><hi rend="smallcaps">IT</hi> is most genial to a soul refined,</l>
                    <l>When love can smile unblushing, unconcealed,</l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s74"/>
                    <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s75" from="s75" to="#s76"/>
                    <l>When mutual thoughts, and words, and acts are kind,</l>
                    <l>And inmost hopes and feelings are revealed;</l>
                    <l>When interest, duty, trust, together bind,</l>
                    <l>And the heart's deep affections are unsealed,</l>
                    <l>When for each other live the kindred pair,&#8212;</l>
                    <l>Here is indeed a picture passing fair!</l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s76"/>
                </lg>

                <lg type="stanza">
                    <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s77" from="s77" to="#s78"/>
                    <l>Hail, happy state! which few have heart to sing,</l>
                    <l>Because they feel how faintly words express</l>
                    <l>So kind, and dear, and chaste, and sweet a thing</l>
                    <l>As tried affection's lasting tenderness;&#8212;</l>
                    <l>Yet, stop, my venturous muse! and fold thy wing</l>
                    <l>Nor to a shrine so sacred rudely press;</l>
                    <span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="s79" from="s79" to="#s78"/>
                    <l>For, marriage,&#8212;thine is still a silent boast,</l>
                    <l>"Like beauty unadorned, adorned the most."</l>
                    <anchor xml:id="s78"/>
                </lg>

            </div1>







        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
