<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="loc.03454">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">"The Pioneers of New York"</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
                <author xml:id="unk">Unknown</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="jyc">Jonathan Y. Cheng</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>University of Texas at Austin</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>loc.03454</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>kprice@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Ed-Folsom@uiowa.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>bbarney2@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain exceptions, public domain works may be freely copied or used in the creation of derivative works without permission, or authorization, of the former copyright owners.</p><p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and is governed by a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0).</p><p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>C. F. Hoffman</author>
                    <title>The Pioneers of New-York</title>
                    <idno type="callno">F122.1.H69 Copy 5</idno>
                    <date cert="high" when="1847-12-06">December 6, 1847</date>
                    <orgName>The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman,
                        1839&#8211;1919, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. </orgName>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from our digital image of original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="h1" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#jyc" when="2014-11-20">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="marginalia">
        <body>
            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="loc_nhg.00345.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">THE PIONEERS OF NEW-YORK.</hi></p>
                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">AN</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">ANNIVERSYARY DISCOURSE</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">DELIVERED BEFORE THE</hi></p>
                <p>St. Nicholas Society of Manhattan,</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">DECEMBER</hi> 6, 1847.</p>
                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
                <p>["The first settlement of this State coincided with its natural advantages. While
                    Englishmen came to America, either flying from ecclesiastical intolerance or
                    pursuing the treasure its savages were supposed to possess, Dutchmen, inspired
                    by the spirit of trade, instead of sitting down on the skirts of the New World,
                    boldly penetrated to the head navigation of the Hudson. They built there a fort
                    in the year 1614, and gave it the name of <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1"
                        xml:id="g001">that august family</hi>
                    <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="right" target="#g001">? That
                        Orange</note>, whose talents and labors, alike in the cabinet and the field,
                    secured the liberty of England as well as of Holland, and established the
                    Independence of Europe. ***Children of commerce, we were rocked in the cradle of
                    war, and sucked the principles of liberty with out mother's
                    milk."&#8212;Governeur Morris, Dec. 6,1812.]</p>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">BY C. F. HOFFMAN.</hi></p>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="infralinear">(June '57 &#8212; This man is
                    now in an Insane Asylum &#8211; it is said a confined lunatic.</note>
                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">NEW-YORK:</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">STANFORD AND SWORDS, 139, BROADWAY.</hi></p>
                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
                <p>1848.</p>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="loc_nhg.00346.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top">25</fw>
                <p>In 1624, ten years after the Hollanders established their three forts on the
                    Hudson, and commenced that line of posts which soon extended from the
                    Connecticut to the Delaware, we have the first infusion here of the different
                    races from which, one hundred years later, the genuine Knickerbocker was
                    evolved.</p>

                <p>A large body of <hi rend="smallcaps">WALLOONS</hi>, inhabitants of the frontier
                    between France and Flanders, who spoke the old Gallic language, and professed
                    the reformed religion, applied in 1622 to Sir Dudley Carlton to settle in
                    Virginia, with the privilege of erecting a town there. The Walloons, during "
                    the thirty years" war, distinguished themselves for their valor and savage
                    spirit, and the governor of Virginia seems not to have given a satisfactory
                    reply to what he probably considered an arrogant condition, which they proposed
                    as the basis of any settlement in his colony, viz:&#8212;That they should be
                    governed by magistrates elected by themselves.* <span rend="bracket-right"
                        resp="#h1" xml:id="b001" from="#b001" to="#b002"/>Several families of these
                    Walloons therefore, established themselves (in the year 1624,) in New
                    Netherland, within the confines of the present town of Brooklyn, on Long Island,
                    where the Wallabout (or "Bay of Foreigners,"&#8212;<hi rend="italic">Wale
                        Bocht</hi>,) still identifies their memory with the locality;<anchor
                        xml:id="b002"/> and several other families of the same race, taking one of
                    Christianse' " stations" as the nucleus of their colony, augmented the
                    settlement at the base of the Katzbergs, near the head of ship navigation, on
                    the Hudson.</p>

                <p>In 1642 a band of representatives of the English race appear in New Netherland,
                    and plant themselves beside their Belgic and Gallic predecessors, with whom they
                    soon become blended by intermarriage. In this year a band of religionists, led
                    on by the Rev. Mr. Doughty, Richard Smith, and others, who had followed the
                    Pilgrims from old England to New England, were compelled to withdraw from the
                    latter country by the persecution they received there; and, after making formal
                    application to the authorities of</p>
                <fw type="footer" place="bottom">English provincialism, in many respects so
                    different from other English provincialisms of New England, go far to disprove
                    an identy of provincial origin in the English settlers of either colony; much
                    less that the Puritans ever imprinted their peculiarities upon New-York as "New
                    England's eldest daughter!"</fw>
                <fw type="footer" place="bottom">*O'Callaghan</fw>
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="loc_nhg.00347.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top">26</fw>
                <p>New Netherland, they had a grant of land assigned to them. Endowed with the usual
                    privileges of free manors, such as free exercise of their religion, powers to
                    plant towns, build churches, nominate magistrates, and administer civil and
                    criminal jurisdiction. Six months later, Throgmorton, who had already been
                    driven with Roger Williams from Massachusetts by the fiery Hugh Peters, procured
                    permission to settle thirty-five families on the lands in Westchester county,
                    now known as Throg's Neck, which the New Netherlander at that time named <hi
                        rend="italic">Vredeland</hi>, or ''Land of Peace." <span rend="bracket-left"
                        resp="#h1" xml:id="b003" from="#b003" to="#b004"/>A meet application, as
                    O'Callaghan remarks, " for the spot selected by those who were bruised and
                    broken down by religious persecution." In the same year the Lady Moody, with her
                    minor son, Sir Henry, and many followers, fled in a similar manner from New
                    England to the asylum of New Netherland, and founded the town of Gravezande,
                    (now Gravesend,) on Long Island.<anchor xml:id="b004"/> To which island Thomas
                    Ffarrington, John Townsend, William Lawrence, John Ffirman, and others, were
                    compelled, in the next twenty months, to remove with their families, from New
                    England; and after accepting a grant of land from the authorities of New
                    Netherland, enroll themselves as liegemen of that province.</p>
                <p>The historian De Laet says, in speaking of this period of the history of New
                    Netherland, "numbers, nay, whole towns, to escape from the insupportable
                    government of New England, removed to New Netherland to enjoy that liberty
                    denied them by their own countrymen." So great was the influx of Englishmen who
                    came now, not as the veritable Pilgrims had proposed in Holland, " to reform any
                    thing which was amiss" among their entertainers, but to enjoy true Knickerbocker
                    freedom, that the director-general of this province, in order " to prevent the
                    disturbance of harmony and social intercourse, more or less, by the incoming of
                    so many strangers to reside here," appointed George Baxter as " English
                    secretary of the council of New Netherland." It is worth stating in this
                    connection, however, that the Dutch language is at this very day still spoken in
                    many of the localities of Long Island by some of the descendants of these, <hi
                        rend="italic">then</hi> "strangers." It is to this early English immigration
                    that certain ingenious theorists have attempted</p>
                <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="loc_nhg.00348.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top">29</fw>
                <p><span rend="bracket-right" resp="#h1" xml:id="b005" from="#b005" to="#b006"/>In
                    1664 crowded in the cavalier followers of the now restored Stuarts, some of
                    whom, (like the Pilgrim fathers,) had been sojourners, with their prince, in
                    Holland, and spoke her language; as did the brave Calvinist "Captain John
                    Underhill with his wife," Lyon Gardiner, who also " had served in the low
                    countries," and other English exiles and soldiers of fortune who preceded the
                    cavaliers, and played an active part in the Indian wars of Long Island; where
                    some of Charles II's <hi rend="italic">Tangier</hi> officers took up their manor
                    giants beside them, and in the mention of their neighborhood, bring up, to this
                    day, their military service in Africa as immortalized in the quaint periods of
                    old Pepys. Many were the manor grants made to these last comers amid the fair
                    lands of New-York, when the bigotted English Duke, from which The <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">NIAGRA STATE</hi> takes its unmeaning provincial name,
                    established a British government over the province.<anchor xml:id="b006"/></p>
                <p>Twenty years later, following the detached families of Norman Protestants, who
                    had previously come hither through the ports of Holland, began thegreat Huguenot
                    immigration into New-York, when so many families of persecuted Frenchmen,
                    migrated hither, and established themselves, some in the city of New-York, some
                    on Staten Island, some at New Rochelle, in Westchester county, some near De
                    Vrie's ancient station, in what is now Rockland county, and some, it is
                    believed, in New Paltz, Ulster county.</p>
                <p>In 1710 New-York, "originally only a field of wild-wood enterprize for the Dutch
                    and Scotch fur trader, but at an early day the chosen asylum of the French
                    anti-Romanist and English anti-Puritan,"became the asylum of three thousand
                    German exiles, who, flying from the devastation of " the blazing Palatinate,"
                    migrated in one body to the valley of the Hudson; while the wars of Europe, and
                    especially the discomfiture of the pretender to the British crown in- 1715, sent
                    hither many an English, Irish,* and</p>
                <fw type="footer" place="bottom">very name alone can sink the whole Swedish navy of
                    American emigration&#8212;the <hi rend="italic">Bird-grip</hi>, and <hi
                        rend="italic">Key of Calmer</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Swan</hi>, <hi
                        rend="italic">Eagle</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Golden Shark</hi>, the <hi
                        rend="italic">Fama</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Charitas</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Black-cat</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Mercurius</hi>.</fw>
                <fw type="footer" place="bottom">*The Irish immigration into New-York, which for
                    several generations has perhaps exceeded that of any other race, seems not to
                    have been very large before</fw>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="loc_nhg.00349.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top">32</fw>
                <p>plains of Normandy and the green vales of England; from the sunny hills of Savoy
                    and the bleak wastes of Finland, came they</p>
                <fw type="footer" place="bottom"><p>a woman in very easy circumstances and
                        abundantly gentle in form and manners, would sow and plant, and rake,
                        incessantly." These fair gardeners (we are also told) were likewise good
                        florists, and displayed much emulation and solicitude in their pleasing
                        employment.</p>
                    <p>In connection with this glimpse of not uninteresting homely habits it may be
                        worth while to recur to the condition of slavery in early New-York. So
                        utterly is this institution now effaced from among us, that it has become
                        difficult to realize how much is due to the far-seeing statesman and pure
                        patriot, through whose instrumentality, chiefly, abolition was effected
                        within our borders. Yet in no colony of our present Union did slavery more
                        generally prevail than in that of New-York; for while the social
                        distinctions, depending upon taste and education, were quietly respected,
                        there was here no division of society into two great classes, as at the
                        south; where one great landed proprietor could count hundreds of human
                        beings as his serfs, while another of the same blood, was sunk almost below
                        the servile tiller of the soil, by the very fact of his owning no property
                        in any man but himself. For, while the number of slaves in any New-York
                        family rarely exceeded a dozen, there was hardly a dwelling in the colony
                        that did not shelter some of these family appendages. Slavery was indeed
                        here literally " a domestic institution." " There were no field negroes," no
                        collection of cabins remote from the house, known as " tho negro quarters."
                        The slaves lived under the same roof, and partook of the same fare as the
                        rest of the family, to which they belonged. They were scrupulously baptised
                        too, and shared tho same religious instruction with the children of the
                        family. There was no especial law, we are told, preventing the barter of
                        slaves; but a natural sentiment, which had grown into a custom, as
                        compulsory as any law, prevented the separation of families; and, above all,
                        the sale of any child without the permission of the mother, who would often
                        exercise her own caprice in designating its future master. The exchange of
                        slaves was also almo3t invariably limited to family relatives. When a negro
                        woman's child attained the age of three years, it was solemnly presented,
                        the first new year's day following, to the son, or daughter, or other young
                        relation of the family, who was of the same sex with tho child so presented;
                        and when in after years, tho youthful master went out to seek his fortunes
                        upon the frontiers, a thousand instances are related of tho fidelity and
                        devotion of these sable squires, amid the perils of the wilderness.</p>
                    <p><span rend="bracket-right" resp="#h1" xml:id="b007" from="#b007" to="#b008"
                        />There is one remark which I will venture to make, in connection with this
                        branch of our subject, because its truth may be, even at this late day,
                        verified in Rockland, Orange, Kings, Queens, and other counties of this
                        State, where the full-blooded descendants of these negro slaves are still
                        found with their African features and complexions, wholly unchanged. In this
                        colony alone was it customary,</p><anchor xml:id="b008"/></fw>
                <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="loc_nhg.00350.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <p>memories of each name and service of her sons who, even in the humblest sphere,
                    have contributed aught to the glory of the commonwealth. Had the progress truths
                    for which Milbourne perished &#8212;had the eternal principles of right and wrong,
                    whose distinctions Leisler died in upholding&#8212;had these been promulgated in New
                    England, and sealed with the blood of a New England man, does any one doubt that
                    the names of the brave martyrs would have stood at this moment foremost in
                    American history as the joint embodiment, the first breathing types of
                    principles taught eighty-six years afterwards in the Declaration of
                    Independence?</p>
                <p>Strange, most strange is it, that the story of these memorable worthies of
                    New-York, so wholly, so peculiarly her own, should come up on the page of two
                    leading New England historians, to prove that they are not worth remembering, or
                    if worth remembering, that they acted under a Puritanic influence.*</p>
                <p>I respect, I reverence the zeal with which our intelligent neighbors preserve
                    their own annals ; but it is full time that they should so write them, as not to
                    overlay and obliterate ours.</p>
                <p>And the descendants of the Pilgrims here domesticated, are identified with
                    ourselves in maintaining the local associations and distinctive history of this
                    State, unless they mean their children of</p>
                
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="left"><!--what to do for slash?--></note>

                <fw type="footer" place="bottom">*Hutchinson, and Bancroft. The German mode of
                    writing history to illustrate a theory, a mode which Mr. Bancroft has followed
                    with such signal ability, can do no harm in Europe, where they only <hi rend="italic">re</hi>-write an
                    old story from printed works which are in every public library. But in this
                    country, where history as yet, and for some time to come, is to be prepared from
                    original documents, a system of the kind can hardly be beneficial to the cause
                    of truth? In adorning the new walls of the new British Parliament House their
                    historic characters of the civil wars on either side, and the portraits of
                    living men as directly opposed in political principle as Wentworth and Hampden,
                    are alike preserved, as all forming a part of England's story. Should similar
                    liberality of feeling ever grow up in this country, the faithful loyalty of
                    Bayard, of Livingston, and other opponents of the democratic party of Leisler's
                    time, will be honored even by those who disapprove their political principles ;
                    and the military valor of New-York, as illustrated by the brave De Lanceys of a
                    subsequent generation, receive its just meed, without any reference to the
                    failing cause which they espoused, not in treason, as Arnold did, but in the
                    blind and mistaken belief that it was the cause of "The Right."</fw>


            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
