<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="mid.00009">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Lessing (Gotthold</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
                <author xml:id="unk">Unknown</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="lmg">Lauren Grewe</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>University of Texas at Austin</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2013</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>mid.00009</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>kprice@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Ed-Folsom@uiowa.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>bbarney2@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability><p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain exceptions, public domain works may be freely copied or used in the creation of derivative works without permission, or authorization, of the former copyright owners.</p><p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and is governed by a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0).</p><p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Lessing's Laocoon</title>
                    <idno type="callno">Walt Whitman's Manuscript Notes on Southey, Browning and Others</idno>
                    <date notBefore="1851-01-01" notAfter="1892-05-26"/>
                    <orgName xml:id="mid">Middlebury College Library, Special Collections</orgName>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from our digital image of original.</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl type="pasteon" xml:id="r2">
                    <author>Unknown author</author>
                    <title level="a">Lessing's Laocoön</title>
                    <title level="j">The American Whig Review</title>
                    <date notBefore="1851-01-01" notAfter="1851-12-26">1851</date>
                    <biblScope type="vol">7</biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="pp">17</biblScope>
                    <note type="project"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="h1" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h2" scribeRef="#ww" medium="brown-ink"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h3" scribeRef="#unk" medium="typescript"/>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#lmg" when="2013-06-29">Transcribed and encoded.</change>
            <change who="#lmg" when="2014-01-22">Checked.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<text type="marginalia">
    <body>
        <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="mid.00009.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
        <ab><handShift new="#h1"/>Lessing (Gotthold Ephraim Lessing)&#8212;1729&#8212;1787
        cont. of Voltaire)
        very active&#8212;Lived in Berlin, Leipsic, Breslaw, Hamburg, &amp;c&#8212;
        &#8212;Was a severe and almost perfect critic&#8212;exposed Klopstok's deficien
        as a poet and the false imitations of the classics&#8212;author of
        "Laokoon" (1766)&#8212;and of good dramas&#8212;also a didactic
        drama "Nathan the Wise," inculcating Kosmos religious notions
        &#8212;Lessing was
        a Jew He was the R.W. Emerson
        of his age, and paved
        the way for Goethe and
        Schiller</ab>
        <fw type="date" place="top left"><handShift new="#h3"/>1851.</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top" rend="italic">Lessing's Laocoön.</fw>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">17</fw>
        <ab rend="centered">LESSING'S LAOCOÖN.</ab>
        <ab rend="centered">THE SECRET OF CLASSIC COMPOSITION IN POETRY, PAINTING, AND STATUARY.</ab>
        <cb/>
            <p>T<hi rend="smallcaps">HE</hi> "Laocoön" of Lessing has been
        but little read in America. Copies of the
        elegant translation by Ross are rare on this
        side of the Atlantic. Readers of German
        profess to understand it in German; but
        like our collegiate Grecians, they read it, as
        Homer is read in schools, with little advantage.
        The Laocoön cannot, however, be
        classed among "difficult books." In the
        translation of William Ross, it is easily and
        soon read. The style of that translator,
        which is clear and flowing, facilitates, no
        doubt, an easy comprehension of the author's
        meaning. At two sittings one may read
        the whole. Lessing was neither a mystic
        nor a transcendentalist. His characteristics
        are perspicuity and judgment, and an
        understanding very free of prejudice.</p>
        <p>The purpose of the Laocoön is to ascertain
            the limits of poetry and painting; to
            show what subjects, or rather, what conditions
            of subjects, are proper for poetic, and
            what for pictorial representation.</p>
        <p xml:id="p1a" next="#p1b">The work opens with an examination of
            Winkelman's theory, "that <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">the <hi rend="italic">primary law</hi>
            of the arts of design among the ancients,
            consisted in a noble simplicity and tranquil
            grandeur, both of attitude and expression."</hi>
            The illustrations of their principles are taken,
            both by Lessing and by Winkelman, who
            were contemporaries, from the celebrated
            group in marble of Laocoön and his two
            sons, represented as perishing together in the
            folds of two enormous serpents. The father
            appears to be in the very agony of death,
            but his features, in the marble, are not distorted
            to a revolting degree; they represent
            agony subdued by an exertion of the will,
            and yet agony extreme, even to death.
            Winkelman argues that <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">the representation
                of the moral power which subdues unseemly
                manifestations of pain and passion, was the
                true object of classic art.</hi> Lessing shows,
            on the contrary, that <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="s1" from="#s1" to="#s2"/><span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="s3" from="#s3" to="#s4"/><hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">the poets and dramatists
                of Greece did not confine themselves to
                the expression of subdued and dignified
                emotions; but gave room, in their dramatic
                exhibitions, to every variety and extreme of
                passionate expression, to a degree not tolerated</hi><anchor xml:id="s2"/><anchor xml:id="s4"/></p>
            <ab>VOL. VII. NO. I. NEW SERIES</ab>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="bottom">☝</note>
        <cb/>
            <p xml:id="p1b" prev="#p1a"><hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">on the modern stage</hi>; and that <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">only
                the painters and the sculptors,</hi> <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">in representing
                    the passions, kept within the limits
                    proscribed by Winkelman for all the representative
                    arts.</hi> <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">"Stoicism," says Lessing,
                        "is <hi rend="italic">undramatic</hi>, and our sympathy is always
                        commensurate with the suffering exhibited
                        by its object."</hi> "If it be true, that
                to give utterance to the expression of pain is
                perfectly compatible&#8212;at least, according to
                the notions of "the ancient Greeks&#8212;with
                grandeur of soul, it follows, that it could not
                have been from the fear of diminishing this
                elevation of character, that the artist refrained
                from tracing on his marble (the Laocoön)
                the outward indications of painful shrieks.
                He must then have had some other motive
                for departing, in this instance, from the line
                adopted by his rival, the poet, who has
                chosen deliberately to express those shrieks."</p>
        <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="s5" from="#s5" to="#s6"/><p>In the second section of his work Lessing
            endeavors to show that <hi rend="italic">beauty</hi> is the primary
            object of the arts, and that they were confined
            by the Greeks to the narrow limits of
            beauty. Mere representation, made for its<anchor xml:id="s6"/>
            <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="s7" from="#s7" to="#s8"/>own sake, was not permitted. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">There was
                even a law among the Thebans, which ordained
                the imitation of the beautiful alone:
                this law was directed against the caricaturists
                and delineators of vulgar subjects.
                The ancient statuaries avoided every kind
                and degree of passion which contorts the
                countenance and destroys the beauty of the
                figure;</hi> <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">while to the poets, every liberty of
                    representation was permitted.</hi> Jupiter, hurling
            his thunder-bolt, was <hi rend="italic">fierce</hi> with indignation
            in the song of the poet; while in the
            sculptor's image he was simply <hi rend="italic">grave</hi>.<anchor xml:id="s8"/></p>
        <span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="s9" from="#s9" to="#s10"/><p xml:id="p2a" next="#p2b">Imitation by the sculptor is confined to a
            single moment, and that of the painter to
            a single point of view, <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">while it is the <hi rend="italic">art</hi>
                of the poet to describe a series of movements,
                one following another,</hi> in the relation<anchor xml:id="s10"/>
            of cause and effect. Since, therefore, the
            arts are limited by their own intrinsic necessities,
            truth and expression ought not alone
            to be regarded. The difficulty of the artist
            is to select such a moment, and such a point
            of view, as shall be sufficiently pregnant</p>
        <ab>2</ab>
        <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="mid.00009.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">18</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top" rend="italic">Lessing's Laocoön.</fw>
        <fw type="date" place="top right">Jan.</fw>
        <cb/>
        <p xml:id="p2b" prev="#p2a">with meaning. "Nothing," says Lessing,
            "can possess this important qualification but
            that which leaves free scope to the imagination.
            The sight and the fancy must be permitted
            reciprocally to add to each other's
            enjoyment. There is not, however, any one
            moment less favorable for this purpose, in
            the object of art, than that of its highest
            state of excitement." <hi rend="italic">Transient</hi> situations
            and appearances, our author argues, are to
            be avoided. The portrait of a man laughing
            disgusts upon a second view. Falling
            bodies cannot be represented. Ajax distracted,
            after having murdered the sheep and
            oxen, which he mistook for men, leans
            gloomily upon his sword, meditating selfdestruction.
            That is the moment for the
            sculptor or the painter; and if an excess
            of passion is represented, it must be at
            instants of amazement and stupefaction, or
            at the pause or point of hesitation, on the
            <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="s11" from="#s11" to="#s12"/>eve of some terrible catastrophe. Thus we
            see the poet and the artist occupy the
            entire range of representation, and fill out
            the circle, <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">one representing <hi rend="italic">motion</hi>, and the
                other <hi rend="italic">rest</hi>.</hi></p>
            <p xml:id="p3a" next="#p3b">Passing over several chapters in which
                our author discusses questions that are interesting
                rather to the classical critic and the<anchor xml:id="s12"/>
                antiquary than to the artist, we come
                upon the seventh division of his subject, in
                which he distinguishes two kinds of imitation,
                &#8212;that of the genuine artist, and that
                of the servile copyist. The artist imitates
                the poet, and the poet the artist; but with
                different degrees of propriety. When <hi rend="italic">Virgil</hi>
                gives us a description of the shield of
                Æneas, he imitates in a certain sense the
                sculptor of the shield; but it was a true imitation
                only when he had seen such a shield,
                and when he described what he had seen.
                "If, on the other hand, Virgil had taken the
                marble group of the Laocoön for his model,"
                says Lessing, "he would have produced an
                imitation of the second kind; he would
                have copied the <hi rend="italic">subject</hi> only, and his description
                would not have been taken from
                any particular attitude chosen by the sculptor,
                nor would he describe it as one would
                draw it, piece by piece, and limb by limb.
                He would take the group as the suggestor
                of a series of actions leading to the catastrophe
                represented in the particular attitude
                selected by the statuary." Our author is careful
                to give a superior credit to the more original
                kind of imitation, in which the poet</p>
        <cb/>
            <p xml:id="p3b" prev="#p3a">describes what he has seen; taking for his
                example Virgil's description of the shield of
                Æneas, where the poet is also the inventor
                of the imagery described upon the shield.
                Lessing argues that it would have been a
                degradation for the poet to have taken a
                hint from the marble group of Laocoön.
                He might, however, show as great an originality
                and power in describing the series of
                events which led to the catastrophe of Laocoön,
                though his first hint of them may
                have been given by the marble group, as
                the statuary himself, who, from some ancient
                story or tradition, executed the work in
                marble. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">It is not originality, which is demanded
                    of the artist or the poet</hi>,&#8212;and this
                    we say of ourselves, and not after Lessing,&#8212;
                    <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">but the power of producing a combined
                        effect of pleasure and elevation, by whatever
                        means that effect may be produced.</hi></p>
            <p>"The Count de Caylus recommends the artist
                to make himself thoroughly acquainted with
                Homer, that greatest of all pictorial poets&#8212;that
                faithful follower of nature. The Count assures
                the artists that their execution will be more perfect
                in proportion to their intimacy with the
                minutest details of the poet's description."</p>
            <p>"The effect of the system here recommended,"
                continues Lessing, in his 11th section, "would be,
                to unite the two kinds of imitation, which I have
                already distinguished from each other. The
                painter would not only have to imitate that
                which the poet had imitated before him, but he
                would also be required to do so with the identical
                lineaments which the other had employed;&#8212;he
                would be required to make use of his prototype
                not only in his character of narrator, but in that
                of poet likewise.</p>
            <p>"But how does it happen that this second kind
                of imitation, which is so derogatory to the poet, is
                not equally so to the artist? If such a series
                of pictures as that which the Count de Caylus
                gives from Homer, had been in existence before the
                poet wrote; and if we knew that he had drawn
                his story from those materials, would not our admiration
                of him be infinitely diminished? How
                then does it happen, that we withhold none of
                our approbation from the artist, even when he
                does nothing more than embody the poet's words
                in forms and colors?"</p>
            <p>To this question Lessing replies, that in
                the works of the painter or statuary, the
                execution seems more difficult than the invention;
                while, with the poet, <hi rend="italic">invention</hi> is
                the test.</p>
            <p xml:id="p4a" next="#p4b">In offering this explanation, Lessing departs
                from his own principle; or rather,
                he loses sight of it, and neglects it. By
                his own showing, the merit of the painter or
                sculptor is <hi rend="italic">never</hi> the merit of the poet, in
                any case. Neither is invention more creditable</p>
        <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="mid.00009.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
        <fw type="date" place="top left">1851.</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top" rend="italic">Lessing's Laocoön.</fw>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">19</fw>
        <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="top">☟</note>
        <cb/>
        <p xml:id="p4b" prev="#p4a">in the poet, than in the statuary or
            <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="s13" from="#s13" to="#s14"/><span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="s15" from="#s15" to="#s16"/>painter. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">And, if we be not wrong in the
                conjecture, invention, so much prized by the
                moderns, was not in the least esteemed by
                the artists and poets of antiquity; their
                works being founded entirely upon tradition
                and history; a common stock, from which
                all alike drew their materials.</hi></p><anchor xml:id="s14"/><anchor xml:id="s16"/>
        <p>In every work, the spirit and circumstance
            of the plot, or situation, was given
            by tradition; and it was the duty of the
            poet to develop and characterize it&#8212;<hi rend="italic">impersonate</hi>
            it, if we may be allowed the expression,
            by the actions of the figures; while
            the statuary and painter restricted themselves
            to certain groups and tableaux, depicting
            points of rest and expectation. Consequently,
            there is no need of giving precedence
            <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="s17" from="#s17" to="#s18"/><span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="s19" from="#s19" to="#s20"/>to one art over the other, for the
            universe is both at rest and in motion in an
            equal degree, and the eternal rest is surely
            as sublime, to our imagination, as the eternal
            motion.<anchor xml:id="s18"/><anchor xml:id="s20"/></p>
            <p>In composing pictures from Homer, or in
                executing groups in <hi rend="italic">bas-relief</hi>, the artist
                does not adopt even the minutest trace of
                that which is the peculiar subject matter of
                poetry, nor is it possible for him to do so, in
                the nature of things, unless by caricature.
                He adopts only the dry bones of tradition,
                the history itself, which Homer may have
                got, and probably did get, as did <choice><orig>Shakspeare</orig><reg>Shakespeare</reg></choice>,
                from his predecessors, improving on
                them, it may be, and adding new features,
                but not using larger liberties with tradition
                itself than the statuary or the painter may
                use with the same. The arts are therefore
                free of each other, and make no serious
                encroachments upon each other's limits.</p>
            <p>Lessing argues, that should the poet take
                his descriptions from groups of statuary or
                from paintings, his merit would be infinitely
                less.</p>
            <p>"Had Virgil," says he, "delineated the fate of
                Laocoön and his sons from the sculpture, he would
                have forfeited the merit which we consider the
                most difficult of attainment, and would have been
                entitled only to that which is of comparatively
                smaller importance; for the first creation of such
                a work in the imagination, is a far higher effort of
                genius than its description in words: but had the
                artist, on the contrary, borrowed his subject from
                the poet, our admiration of him would scarcely
                have been diminished, though the merit of the
                conception would not have been his own; for
                to impart expression to the marble is infinitely
                more difficult than to give expression in words;
                and in comparing the relative value of expression
                and execution, we are always disposed to excuse
                <cb/>
            the sculptor's deficiency in the one to the same
            extent that we require his excellence in the other.</p>
            <p>"In some instances, it is even a greater merit in
                the artist to have imitated nature through the
                medium of the poet's imitation than without it.
                The painter who has delineated a beautiful landscape
                after the description of a Thomson, has
                performed a higher task than he who has copied it
                directly from nature."</p>
            <p>Were the principles of our critic, indicated
                in the above remarks, to pass into literature
                as critical canons, we conceive a great and
                serious injury would be inflicted upon the
                arts. It may be a much more <hi rend="italic">difficult</hi> task
                to paint a landscape after Thomson, but the
                difficulty of art does not in the remotest
                degree enhance its merit. Whether easily
                or with difficulty produced, is nothing to the
                point; works of art are not for the artist,
                but for others, and were we inclined to interpose
                between the artist and his work,
                we should rather say, the more easily it is
                done the better. "The painter of nature,"
                says our author, "has the original before his
                eyes; the painter after Thomson must exert
                his imagination:" but, in truth, there is no such
                thing in art as a pure imitation of nature;
                the entire work, from the composition of the
                colors to the last degree of sublimity in
                expression, is a production of talent and
                imagination. The artist has, indeed, nature
                before him, but the spiritual significance of
                nature he has only in his own mind; and
                it is not <hi rend="italic">every</hi> natural scene, every appearance
                on the face of nature, that <hi rend="italic">has</hi> significance;
                nor, to <hi rend="italic">some</hi> minds, has <hi rend="italic">any</hi> scene
                <hi rend="italic">any</hi> significance. If he paints after Thomson
                he does not take the colors of his stones and
                trees, (their most effective element,) nor their
                individual shapes, from Thomson. These he
                must take from nature, which is common to
                himself and to the poet. The poet may have
                expressed the spiritual significance of the
                scene, but by the canon which Lessing has
                himself established, he does so by the <hi rend="italic">changes</hi>
                which pass over the landscape, the æsthetic
                succession of the changes forming a natural
                drama or story; as, for instance, that of the
                rise and progress of a thunder-storm, of
                which nature retains the tradition, for the
                use both of the painter and the poet.</p>
        <p>We repeat, then, that the duty of the
            painter is to represent moments of rest,
            (<hi rend="italic">suggesting</hi> motions and changes,) and that,
            too, by Lessing's own established principle&#8212;
            a principle which marks a satisfactory limit
            between pictorial and poetical art.</p>
        <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="mid.00009.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
        <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="top"><add rend="insertion" place="supralinear">In art</add> Originality is an effect, just as much as a cause.</note>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">20</fw>
        <fw type="header" place="top" rend="italic">Lessing's Laocoön.</fw>
        <fw type="date" place="top right">Jan.</fw>
        <cb/>
        <span rend="doubleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="s21" from="#s21" to="#s22"/><p><hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">We firmly believe that while Invention is
            held to be the chief merit of an artist&#8212;
            while the attainment of what is called Originality
            is held up to the youthful poet
            or painter&#8212;we shall never produce great
            works of art. Let Art itself be its own merit,
            and let its subjects be taken, as they come,
            either from nature</hi> or from history indifferently;
            and he who can best select and
            <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s23" from="#s23" to="#s24"/>execute the subject, he is the greatest artist.
            How absurd would seem the efforts of that
            painter, who should endeavor to invent a
            new form of human face! Novelty in art
            is a contradiction in terms, for the soul of
            art is representation.<anchor xml:id="s24"/><anchor xml:id="s22"/></p>
            <p>Let us consider in what manner a great
                artist would choose to immortalize himself.
                Surely by the representation of a moral
                theme, and by no means of any extemporized
                fable. Were he a sculptor, his
                figure would be a Moses, a Cromwell, a
                Calhoun. He would turn to history both
                for story and sentiment; and chiefly to the
                oldest traditions, and the most sacred histories.
                Were he a poet, his choice would be
                <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="s25" from="#s25" to="#s26"/>of no idle scone, pregnant with no consequences:
                that which he represented would
                be significant either of the great laws which
                govern human nature in all conditions, or
                of the destiny of a nation, or perhaps, as
                in Milton's epic, of all mankind. He would
                endeavor to characterize the most powerful
                traits of humanity, in order, simply, <hi rend="italic">to express
                    the grandeur of his own spirit,</hi> (for the
                artist is ambitious, and seeks admission to
                the society of the great of all ages;) and he
                would, therefore, by a necessary sympathy,
                feel himself attracted only to the characters<anchor xml:id="s26"/>
                and actions of heroes and sages. If, like
                Milton, he chose to invent, his invention
                would be merely a combination,&#8212;an assemblage
                of known images, to express a series
                of established principles; and in this invention
                he would only imitate nature, and, as
                Milton has done, reproduce tradition in new
                actions, and describe what has already been
                described&#8212;battles, single conflicts, stratagems,
                statesmanship, and the interior struggles
                of the greater passions. He would
                never inquire whether or no he were original,
                but only whether he were true to
                nature in her highest passages, and correct
                and artistic in the combination of the forms
                and actions taken to illustrate his moral
                theme.</p>
            <p>In the fifteenth section of his work, Lessing<cb/>
                has marked the essential difference between
                the poet and the artist. Without
                adhering closely to the text, let us endeavor
                to develop the idea of which it contains the
                germ, and the germ only; for Lessing, although
                the originator, did not prove himself
                the master of criticism, and humbler spirits,
                following in his steps, may possibly add
                something to the work which he began.</p>
                <p>"Time is the sphere of the poet&#8212;space
                    that of the painter." More correctly, the
                    statuary and the painter make use of visible
                    fixed forms to represent passions and moral
                    emotions,&#8212;visible fixed <hi rend="italic">forms</hi>, which are
                    significant in themselves, as the human face
                    is, in itself, significant of what passes in
                    the mind and heart. The poet, on the other
                    hand, makes use of <hi rend="italic">sounds</hi>, the measures of
                    time and motion. Tho face and form of
                    man is the property of the painter; his
                    speech, the most significant and powerful of
                    his actions, belongs to the poet. It is important,
                    however, not to mistake written language,
                    or phonetics, for an essential in the
                    poet's art; since poetry may be composed
                    without the aid of letters, and intrusted
                    merely to the memory. The labor of the
                    painter and statuary is mechanical, and
                    their work requires no comment; its meaning,
                    like that of nature, being at once apparent
                    to all mankind. The work of the
                    poet is limited to the language in which he
                    writes; a medium variously colored, imperfect,
                    and artificial in tho highest degree.</p>
                <p>The poet cannot make us see a thing
                    which we have not seen; he can only represent
                    the motions and actions of things
                    which we <hi rend="italic">have</hi> seen; which gives a hint of
                    the mode in which poems should be illustrated;
                    that is to say, by pictures representing
                    points of rest in the progress of the story,
                    and giving us portraits of the personages in
                    groups preparatory to, or concluding an
                    action, as <choice><orig>Shakspeare</orig><reg>Shakespeare</reg></choice> has been illustrated
                    by the more recent limners.</p>
                <p>Because language can express and suggest
                    every action, sentiment, and feeling,
                    <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="s27" from="#s27" to="#s28"/>poetry can do the same; but as <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">language
                        proper always expresses by its nature a
                        <hi rend="italic">movement</hi> in the mind, while colors and
                        lines express only fixed images in the same,
                        poetry is the vehicle for expressing passions,
                        actions, and variable emotions, while painting
                        and statuary can only</hi> represent, in<anchor xml:id="s28"/>
                    <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">strictness, what</hi> is permanent and perpetual,
                    <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">or rather,</hi> what is <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">complete in itself,</hi> and that</p>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>