<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="mid.00012">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Hindu Drama</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
                <author xml:id="unk">unknown</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="lmg">Lauren Grewe</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="nhg">Nicole Gray</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="tra">Ty Alyea</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="cb">Caterina Bernardini</persName>

                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>University of Texas at Austin</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2018</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>mid.00012</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>kprice@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Ed-Folsom@uiowa.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>bbarney2@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain
                        exceptions, public domain works may be freely copied or used in the creation
                        of derivative works without permission, or authorization, of the former
                        copyright owners.</p>
                    <p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and
                        is governed by a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"
                            >Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY
                        4.0).</p>
                    <p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted
                        by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Thoreau and Others on Indian Poetry and Indian Drama</title>
                    <idno type="callno"/>
                    <date/>
                    <orgName xml:id="mid">Middlebury College Library, Special Collections</orgName>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from our digital image of original.</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl type="base" xml:id="r1">
                    <author>Unknown author</author>
                    <title>The HindÚ Drama</title>
                    <date when="1857">1857</date>
                    <publisher>Westminster Review</publisher>
                    <pubPlace/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="h1" scribeRef="#unk" medium="typescript"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h2" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h3" scribeRef="#ww" medium="blue-pencil"/>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#cb" when="2018-01-12">proofed</change>
            <change who="#lmg" when="2014-02-05">checked.</change>
            <change who="#lmg" when="2012-07-21">transcribed and encoded.</change>
            
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="marginalia">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="mid.00012.001.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="top">Hindu Drama (specimens rather too strongly
                Anglicised).</note>
            <fw type="date" place="top left"><handShift new="#h1"/>1857</fw>
            <fw type="header" rend="italic" place="top">The HindÚ Drama.</fw>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">199</fw>
            <cb/>
            <del rend="hashmark" hand="#h3"><del rend="hashmark" hand="#h2"><p>controversy is
                        strewn, look both respectable and enduring by the side of the porcelain ware
                        of this Theology of reflection. We cannot qusetion herein the justice of
                        history, which has ever denied the eclectic a separate niche in her temple,
                        and has obliged the theologian who has spent a life in accommodations and
                        concessions to submit to be tried by the standard of strict
                            Orthodoxy."&#8212;<hi rend="italic">Scwarz</hi>, p. 429.</p>
                    <p>The two sections of Theology, then, which seem at present in possession of
                        the field, have, it appears, no root in themselves, and can wield no
                        permanent power over opinion. The Orthodox Theology is intrinsically the
                        weakest, but externally the most powerfully backed. It is a mere
                        ecclesiastical flag, hoisted to give a colour of legitimacy to the way
                        against conscience. It may reign, but will not persuade; and its fortunes
                        are linked, for good and for evil, to those of the conservative and
                        aristocratic party in Europe.The Mediation-Theology exercises a respectable
                        sway over opinion, but is essentially shifting, indeterminate, and relative.
                        Whether or not circumstances may occur which would rekindle a real and
                        honest speculative Theology, it is idle to discuss. Should, however, some
                        renovating impulse be communicated to thought from without, it is impossible
                        that the experience of the past should be wasted. Real ground has been
                        gained. Intelligent men understand each other better; good sense and
                        earnestness have more and more weight. Meanwhile, the solid acquisition to
                        theological science has been won by the small and uninfluential circle of
                        scholars who have devoted their conscientious industry to the critical and
                        historical matters which have become so intimately bound up with the
                        Christian religion. While all the speculative attempts confess more or less
                        of defect and exhaustion, this school alone has established results. Its
                        power has lain also in its possessing a definite aim, and a limited
                        material. Criticism does not, like speculation, set out on a voyage of
                        discovery, or undertake the construction of a religion <hi rend="italic">À
                            priori</hi>. Its problem is comparatively narrow, and even this is not
                        its own selection. What is the character and value of the Christian records?
                        All of us were asking this question, either aloud, or in the silence of our
                        own hearts, and receiving mere accidental and most unsatisfactory answers.
                        Criticism attempts to answer this question, on distinctly stated principles
                        of inquiry&#8212;principles not arbitrarily laid down, but the same by which
                        all other written records whatsoever must be tested. When it has once
                        answered this question, its work is done. We are <cb/> not to look for
                        infinite discoveries in this direction. The point can be settled; and the
                        time is ripe for a settlement. While speculation is in abeyance, this, the
                        preliminary of all theological speculation, can be arranged. And once
                        settled, historical criticism has discharged its mission, the Renaissance
                        movement is complete, and philology may lay down her arms, with the
                        satisfaction of having removed at least one of the great stumbling-blocks in
                        the way of the truth-loving and serious religious inquirer.</p></del></del>
            <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
            <head type="main-authorial" rend="centered">ART. II.&#8212;THE HINDU DRAMA.</head>
            <p>1. <hi rend="italic">Sakoontalá; or, the Lost Ring. An Indian Drama. Translated into
                    English Prose and Verse, from the Sanskrit of Kálidása.</hi> By Monier Williams,
                M.A., Professor of Sanskrit at the East India College, Haileybury. Hertford: Stephen
                Austin. 1855.</p>
            <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Vikramorvasi, an Indian Drama. Translated into English Prose,
                    from the Sanskrit of Kálidása.</hi> By Edward Byles Cowell, B.A. Hertford:
                Stephen Austin. 1851.</p>
            <p>3. <hi rend="italic">Málaviká und Agnimitra, ein Drama des Kálidása in funf Akten,
                    &amp;c. (Málaviká and Adnimirka, a Drama by Kálidása.</hi> Translated from the
                Sanskrit for the first time, by Albrecht Weber.) Berlin. 1856.</p>
            <p>4. <hi rend="italic">Le Chariot d'Enfant, Drame en Vers. Traduction du Drame Indien
                    du Roi Soudraka.</hi> Par MM. MÉry et GÉrard de Nerval. Paris. 1850.</p>
            <p>H<hi rend="smallcaps">ORACE</hi> W<hi rend="smallcaps">ALPOLE</hi> said, "Life is a
                comedy to those who think, a tragedy to those who feel." Had he lived a hundred
                years later, he might have added, "and to those who both think and feel, who temper
                their passion with reason, and enliven their reason with sentiment, it is a HindÚ
                play." This mingling of the mask and the cothurnus, exciting passions only for the
                pleasure of allaying them, is essentially the characteristic of the Indian
                drama.</p>
            <p>Translations from the Sanskrit are yearly produced in Germany, France, England, and
                even Italy; but when we remember that specimens by good hands of some of the best
                literary pieces of India (<hi rend="italic">e.g.</hi> the "Sakoontalá," of Sir W.
                Jones, and the "Bhagavad-Gitá" of Sir C. Wilkins), have</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="mid.00012.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">214</fw>
            <fw type="header" rend="italic" place="top">The HindÚ Drama.</fw>
            <fw type="date" place="top right">April,</fw>
            <cb/>
            <p>antiquarianism to the enjoyment of the higher charms of literature. The last German
                version was that of Lobedanz, in 1854.</p>
            <p>Twenty years later than Sir W. Jones, Antoine LÉonard de ChÉzy found a MS. of the
                "Shakuntalá" in the Bibliothèque Royale, and studied Sanskrit for the sole purpose
                of enjoying its beauties, of which he had heard, in their original form. He gave the
                French an elegant free rendering of the piece, and his almost extravagant devotion
                to it formed the counterpart of Göthe's enthusiastic admiration.</p>
            <p>"Good wine needs no bush," and certainly Mr. Williams's translation seems in every
                respect to rise about our praise. If any excuse were wanting for giving the public
                an opportunity of reading the master-piece of the Indian drama, in a form that is
                worthy of it&#8212;the fine thoughts of a great Indian poet rendered by the
                beautiful expression of an English poet&#8212;for Mr. Williams has proved himself to
                be no stranger on Parnassus,&#8212;it would be found in the readablenss and
                enjoyableness of that translation itself; the book is its own excuse. But, on the
                other hand, those among us who care&#8212;and what man of education does
                not?&#8212;to know the beauties that various ages and lands of the world have
                produced, will rejoice to have Sir W. Jones's translation superseded.</p>
            <p>Mr. Williams has rightly understood those modern rules of translation from one tongue
                to another, which determine how much of the original is capable of being rendered
                into metre&#8212;how much absolutely demands the easier mediume of prose. This in
                itself requires the observation of a mind by no means common-place. We will not now
                enter into the <hi rend="italic">vexata quæstio</hi> of whether the philosophical
                poetry (or rather, perhaps, <hi rend="italic">poetical philosophy</hi>), the
                metrical Puránas and other half-scientific works of India, are better rendered into
                English by prose or metre. We believe that no general rule&#8212;such as that metre
                should be rendered by metre, prose by prose&#8212;will hold good in the case of
                Indian literature. We confess that the subject seems to us of more importance than
                the form in deciding this question. But the doubt arises in a lesser degree with
                respect to the drama. Here prose and metre are mingled, as the Hindú author rightly
                perceived the error of making people talk metre about the merest trifles on the
                stage any more than in common life, and knew, on the other hand, that rhythm was the
                best&#8212;and on the stage, perhaps, the only efficient&#8212;vehicle for the finer
                outbursts of <cb/> passion and poetical feeling. His object was to combine the
                natural and the effective, and so far he has succeeded. It then became a question
                whether, on the one hand, prose or verse could best develope this art of the
                original in the translation, &#8212;on the other, whether it were <hi rend="italic"
                    >possible</hi> to follow the system of the Hindú author. The "Shakuntalá" has
                been translated into plain prose throughout by Sir W. Jones, into metre throughout
                by Lobedanz, into mingled prose and verse by Ernst Meier in German, and by Mr.
                Williams in English, and we do not hesitate to give our verdict in favour of the
                last. He has proved the possibility of what is, in truth, by no means an easy
                task&#8212;finding a conversational prose for the merely conversational portions of
                the original, and an easy metre&#8212;the change to which from prose does not jar
                upon the ear of the reader&#8212; for its metrical portions. Moreover, he has felt
                the suggestiveness of some of the shorter musical couplets for English rhyme, and he
                has introduced it with much tact and delicacy. As a general rule it is easy to
                translate the Sanskrit. The <hi rend="italic">shloka,</hi> or couplet, is always
                complete in itself, <hi rend="italic">teres atque rotundus.</hi> The prose is
                straightforward and simple. But when we come to handle the various metres of the
                drama, and to find a line of Sanskrit succeeded by one of Prákrit, it is by no means
                a light task to do justice at the same time to the meaning and the music of the
                Hindú poet. Mr. Williams has not only succeeded in doing so, but he is also the
                first translator who has done so, and we congratulate him on his success.</p>
            <p>We cannot conclude the expression of our admiration of this recent <hi rend="italic"
                    >chef-d'&#x99;uvre</hi> of Oriental translation, without a few words on the
                external garb in which it appears. Mr. Austin, of Hertford, is well known already as
                the Mæcenas of Indianists. The liberality of the publisher has given an impulse to
                the ambition of the writer. In the present instance he has spared neither expense
                nor trouble in finding a robe of state suited to Shakuntalá's beauty. He has
                collected from the illuminated MSS. of the British Museum and the East India House a
                large number of splendid chromatic borders, head-pieces, tail-pieces, and arabesques
                of every description, and added all the luxuries that fine wood-cuts, choice paper,
                and clear type can supply. If Mr. Williams has given the Orientalist a <hi
                    rend="italic">bonne-bouche</hi>, Mr. Austin, resolved that the general reading
                public should not be denied a share of this rich mind of Eastern gems, has given us
                all a masterpiece of illustration</p>
            <add rend="pasteon" source="#r1"><q who="unknown" type="written"><floatingText
                        rend="flat">
                        <body>
                            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="mid.00012.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
                            <p>and typography, which is a real contribution no less to the library
                                than to the boudoir.</p>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText></q></add>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
