<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="mid.00008">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">"What is Poetry"</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
                <author xml:id="unk">Unknown</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="jyc">Jonathan Y. Cheng</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>University of Texas at Austin</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>mid.00008</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>kprice@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Ed-Folsom@uiowa.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>bbarney2@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability><p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain exceptions, public domain works may be freely copied or used in the creation of derivative works without permission, or authorization, of the former copyright owners.</p><p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and is governed by a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0).</p><p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Leigh Hunt</author>
                    <title>What is Poetry</title>
                    <!--<idno type="callno"></idno>-->
                    <date cert="high" when="1847-12-06">December 6, 1847</date>
                    <orgName>Middlebury College</orgName>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from our digital image of original.</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl type="pasteon" xml:id="ref1">
                    <author>Francis William Newman</author>
                    <title>The Iliad of Homer, Faithfully Translated into Unrhymed English
                        Metre</title>
                    <date when="1856">1856</date>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="h1" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h2" scribeRef="#ww" medium="dark-pencil"/>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#jyc" when="2014-11-20">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="marginalia">
        <body>
            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="mid.00008.001" type="recto"/>
                <note xml:id="n001" place="top right"><handShift new="#h1"/>a good essay.</note>
                <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="smallcaps">WHAT IS POETRY?</hi></fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">601</fw>
                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="hobar-full"/>

                <div2>
                    <delSpan rend="hashmark" spanTo="#d001"/>
                    <lg type="poem">
                        <l>To secure yourselves from these</l>
                        <l>Be not too secure in ease;</l>
                        <l>Let one eye his watches keep</l>
                        <l>While the other eye doth sleep;</l>
                        <l>So you shall good shepherds prove,</l>
                        <l>And for ever hold the love</l>
                        <l>Of our great God. Sweetest slumbers,</l>
                        <l>And soft silence, fall in numbers</l>
                        <l>On your eyelids! So, farewell!</l>
                        <l>Thus I end my evening's knell.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">FLETCHER.</hi></p>
                    <anchor xml:id="d001"/>
                </div2>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
                <div2>
                    <head type="main-authorial"><hi rend="smallcaps">89.&#8212;WHAT IS
                        POETRY?</hi></head>
                    <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="right">Leigh Hunt born in 1784 is he
                        now living? aged 72 <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-right"/></note>
                    <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="right">Yes, (July '59) he lives old and
                        in fair condition in London&#8212;aged 73</note>
                    <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="right">Died Aug. '59 aged 75</note>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">LEIGH HUNT</hi></p>
                    <p>[We could not close this first Volume of "Half-Hours with the Best Authors"
                        at all satisfactorily, if we did not give an extract from the writings of
                        one of the most original and fascinating of English prose writers&#8212;one,
                        also, who has won an enduring station amongst English poets. Leigh Hunt, the
                        son of a West Indian who came to England and took orders in the Church, was
                        horn in 1784. He was educated at Christ's Hospital. As early as 1805 he was
                        a writer of theatrical criticism in his brother's paper,"The News;"&#8212;in
                        1808 the brothers established "the Examiner"&#8212;a weekly paper which
                        surpassed all its then contemporaries in ability and taste. In those days it
                        was almost impossible for a public writer to speak out; and Leigh Hunt had
                        to expiate a sarcasm upon the Prince Regent by two years' imprisonment. Mr.
                        Hunt's subsequent connection with Lord Byron was not a fortunate one; and we
                        are inclined to think that in future literary history most honest sympathies
                        will be with the plebeian asserting his independence as a brother in
                        letters, instead of with the patrician,&#8212;heartless and
                        insolent,&#8212;a declaimer for liberty but in practice a tyrant. Mr. Hunt,
                        who has' borne much adversity with a cheerfulness beyond all praise, writes
                        as freshly and brilliantly as ever. Long may those unfailing spirits which
                        are the delight of his social and family circle be the sunshine of his old
                        age. The following extract is from a delightful volume, published in 1847,
                        entitled, 'Selections from the English Poets&#8212;Imagination and
                        Fancy."]</p>
                    <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">IF</hi> a young reader should ask, after all, What is
                        the best way of knowing bad poets from good, the best poets from the next<pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="mid.00008.002" type="verso"/><fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="smallcaps">HALF-HOURS WITH THE BEST
                            AUTHORS.</hi></fw>
                        <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">602</fw>
                        <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>best, and so on? the answer
                        is, the only and twofold way; first, the perusal of the best poets with the
                        greatest attention; and second, the cultivation of that love of truth and
                        beauty which made them what they are. Every true reader of poetry partakes a
                        more than ordinary portion of the poetic nature; and no one can be
                        completely such, who does not love, or take an interest in every thing that
                        interests the poet, from the firmament to the daisy&#8212;from the highest
                        heart of man, to the most pitiable of the low. It is a good practice to read
                        with pen in hand, marking what is liked or doubted. It rivets the attention,
                        realizes the greatest amount of enjoyment, and facilitates reference. It
                        enables the reader also, from time to time, to see what progress he makes
                        with his own mind, and how it grows up to the stature of its exalter.</p>
                    <p>If the same person should ask, What class of poetry is the highest? I should
                        say, undoubtedly, the Epic; for it includes the drama, with narration
                        besides; or the speaking and action of the characters, with the speaking of
                        the poet himself, whose utmost address is taxed to relate all well for so
                        long a time, particularly in the passages least sustained by enthusiasm.
                        Whether this class has included the greatest poet, is another question still
                        under trial; for <choice>
                            <orig>Shakspeare</orig>
                            <reg>Shakespeare</reg>
                        </choice> perplexes all such verdicts, even when the claimant is Homer;
                        though if a judgment may be drawn from his early narratives ("Venus and
                        Adonis," and the "Rape of Lucrece"), it is to be doubted whether even <choice>
                            <orig>Shakspeare</orig>
                            <reg>Shakespeare</reg>
                        </choice> could have told a story like Homer, owing to <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="left" target="#b001">☞
                            </note><span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="b001" from="#b001" to="#b002"/><hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">that incessant activity and
                            superfcetation of thought, a little less of which might be occasionally
                            desired even in his plays</hi><anchor xml:id="b002"/>;&#8212;if it were
                        possible, once possessing anything of his, to wish it away. Next to Homer
                        and <choice>
                            <orig>Shakspeare</orig>
                            <reg>Shakespeare</reg>
                        </choice> come such narrators as the less universal but intenser <hi rend="italic">Dante</hi>; Milton, with his dignified imagination; the
                        universal profoundly simple Chaucer; and luxuriant remote
                        Spenser&#8212;immortal child in poetry's most poetic solitudes: then the
                        great second-rate dramatists; unless those who are better acquainted with
                        Greek tragedy than I am, demand a place for them before Chaucer: then the
                        airy yet robust universality of Ariosto; the hearty out-of-door nature of
                        Theocritus, also a universalist; the finest lyrical poets (who only take
                        short nights, compared with the narrators); the <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="mid.00008.003" type="recto"/>
                        <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="smallcaps">WHAT IS POETRY?</hi></fw>
                        <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">603</fw>
                        <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="hobar-full"/> purely contemplative poets
                        who have more thought than feeling; the descriptive, satirical, didactic,
                        epigrammatic. It is to be borne in mind, however, that the first poet of an
                        inferior class may be superior to followers in the train of a higher one,
                        though the superiority is by no means to be taken for granted; otherwise
                        Pope would be superior to Fletcher, and Butler to Pope. <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="right" target="#b003">☜</note><span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="b003" from="#b003" to="#b004"/><hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">Imagination,
                            teeming with action and character, makes the greatest poets; feeling and
                            thought the next; fancy (by itself) the next; wit the last.<anchor xml:id="b004"/> Thought by itself makes no poet at all; for the mere
                            conclusions of the understanding can at best be only so many
                            intellectual matters of fact.</hi> Feeling, even destitute of conscious
                        thought, stands a far better poetical chance; feeling being a sort of
                        thought without the process of thinking&#8212;a grasper of the truth without
                        seeing it. And what is very remarkable, feeling seldom makes the blunders
                        that thought does. An idle distinction has been made between taste and
                        judgment. Taste is the very maker of judgment. Put an artificial fruit in
                        your mouth, or only handle it, and you will soon perceive the difference
                        between judging from taste or tact, and judging from the abstract figment
                        called judgment. The latter does but throw you into guesses and doubts.
                        Hence the conceits that astonish us in the gravest and even subtlest
                        thinkers, whose taste is not proportionate to their mental perceptions; men
                        like Donne, for instance; who, apart from accidental personal impressions,
                            <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="right" target="b005">☜</note><span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="b005" from="#b005" to="#b006"/><hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">seem to look at
                            nothing as it really is, but only as to what may be thought of it.</hi>
                        Hence, on the other hand, the delightfulness of <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">those poets who never violate <anchor xml:id="b006"/> truth
                            of feeling, whether in things real or imaginary; who are always
                            consistent with their object and its requirements; and who run the great
                            round of nature, not to perplex and be perplexed, but to make themselves
                            and us happy.</hi> And luckily, delightfulness is not incompatible with
                        greatness, willing soever as men may be in their present imperfect state to
                        set the power to subjugate above the power to please.<span rend="doublieLine-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="b007" from="#b007" to="#b008"/><hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">Truth, of any kind
                            whatsoever, makes great writing.</hi> This is the reason why such poets
                        as Ariosto, though not writing with a constant detail of thought and feeling
                        like Dante, are justly considered great as well as delightful.<anchor xml:id="b008"/> Their greatness proves itself by the same truth of
                        nature, and sustained power, though in a different way. Their action is <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="mid.00008.004" type="verso"/><fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="smallcaps">HALF-HOURS WITH THE BEST
                            AUTHORS.</hi></fw>
                        <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">604</fw><milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>not so crowded and weighty; their sphere has more
                        territories less fertile; but it has enchantments of its own which excess of
                        thought would spoil&#8212;luxuries, laughing graces, animal spirits; and not
                        to recognise the beauty and greatness of these, treated as they treat them,
                        is simply to be defective in sympathy. Every planet is not Mars or Saturn.
                        There is also Venus and Mercury. There is one genius of the south, and
                        another of the north, and others uniting both. The reader who is too
                        thoughtless or too sensitive to like intensity of any sort, and he who is
                        too thoughtful or too dull to like anything but the greatest possible
                        stimulus of refection or passion, are equally wanting in complexional
                        fitness for a thorough enjoyment of books. Ariosto occasionally says as fine
                        things as Dante, and Spenser as <choice>
                            <orig>Shakspeare</orig>
                            <reg>Shakespeare</reg>
                        </choice>; but the business of both is to enjoy; and in order to partake
                        their enjoyment to its full extent, you must feel what poetry is in the
                        general as well as the particular, must be aware that there are different
                        songs of the spheres, some fuller of notes, and others of a sustained
                        delight; and as the former keep you perpetually alive to thought or passion,
                        so from the latter you receive a constant harmonious sense of truth and
                        beauty, more agreeable perhaps on the whole, though less exciting. Ariosto,
                        for instance, does not <hi rend="italic">tell a story</hi> with the brevity
                        and concentrated passion of Dante; every sentence is not so full of matter,
                        nor the style so removed from the indifference of prose; yet you are charmed
                        with a truth of another sort, equally characteristic of the writer, equally
                        drawn from nature, and substituting a healthy sense of enjoyment for
                        intenser emotion. Exclusiveness of liking for this or that mode of truth,
                        only shows, either that a reader's perceptions are limited, or that he would
                        sacrifice truth itself to his favourite form of it. Sir Walter Raleigh, who
                        was as trenchant with his pen as his sword, hailed the 'Faerie <choice>
                            <orig>Queene</orig>
                            <reg>Queen</reg>
                        </choice>' of his friend Spenser in verses in which he said that "Petrarch"
                        was henceforward to be no more heard of; and that, in all English poetry,
                        there was nothing he counted "of any price" but the effusions of the new
                        author. <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="b009" from="#b009" to="#b010"/>Yet Petrarch is still living; Chaucer was not abolished by
                        Sir Walter; and <choice>
                            <orig>Shakspeare</orig>
                            <reg>Shakespeare</reg>
                        </choice> is thought somewhat valuable. <span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="b011" from="#b011" to="#b012"/>A botanist might as
                        well have said that myrtles and oaks were to disappear because acacias had
                        come up. It is with the Poet's crea-<anchor xml:id="b010"/><anchor xml:id="b012"/><note type="autorial" resp="#h1" place="bottom" target="b009">☞</note>
                        <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="mid.00008.005" type="recto"/>
                        <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="smallcaps">WHAT IS POETRY?</hi></fw>
                        <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">605</fw>
                        <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="hobar-full"/>tions as with Nature's,
                        great or small. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">Wherever truth and beauty,
                            whatever their amount, can be shaped into verse, and answer to some
                            demand for it in our hearts, there poetry is to be found; whether in
                            productions grand and beautiful as some great event, or some mighty,
                            leafy solitude, or no bigger and more pretending than a sweet face or a
                            bunch of violets</hi>; whether in Homer's epic or Gray's "Elegy," in the
                        enchanted gardens of Ariosto and Spenser, or the very pot-herbs of the
                        "Schoolmistress" of Shenstone, the balms of the simplicity of a cottage. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">Not to know and feel this, is to be
                            deficient in the universality of Nature herself, who is a poetess on the
                            smallest as well as the largest scale</hi>, and who calls upon us to
                        admire all her productions; not indeed with the same degree of admiration,
                        but with no refusal of it, except to defect.</p>
                    <p>I cannot draw this essay towards its conclusion better than with <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">three memorable words of Milton; who has
                            said, that poetry, in comparison with science, is "simple, sensuous, and
                            passionate." By simple, he means imperplexed and self-evident; by
                            sensuous, genial and full of imagery; by passionate, excited and
                            enthusiastic</hi>. <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="b013" from="#b013" to="#b014"/>I am aware that different constructions have
                        been put on some of these words; but the <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1" xml:id="u001">contest</hi> seems to me to necessitate those before
                            us.<anchor xml:id="b014"/><note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="left" target="b013"><hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">true</hi></note>I quote,
                        however, not from the original, but from an extract in the ' Remarks on
                        Paradise Lost' by Richardson.</p>
                    <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="right" target="u001">contract</note>
                    <p>What the poet has to cultivate above all things is love and <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="b015" from="#b015" to="#b016"/>truth;&#8212;<hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">what he has to avoid,
                            like poison, is the fleeting and the false</hi>. He will get no good by
                        proposing to be "in earnest at the moment."<anchor xml:id="b016"/> His
                        earnestness must be innate and habitual; born with him, and felt to be his
                        most precious inheritance. <span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="b017" from="#b017" to="#b018"/><span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="b019" from="#b019" to="#b020"/><hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">I expect neither profit nor general fame by my writings,"
                            says Coleridge, in the Preface to his Poems; "and I consider myself as
                            having been amply repaid without either. Poetry has been to me its <hi rend="italic">own exceeding great reward;</hi></hi> it has soothed
                        my afflictions; it has multiplied and refined my enjoyments; it has endeared
                        solitude; and it has given me the habit of wishing to discover the good and
                        the beautiful in all that meets and surrounds me."&#8212;<hi rend="italic">Pickering's edition</hi>, p. 10.</p>
                    <anchor xml:id="b018"/>
                    <p>"Poetry," says Shelley, "lifts the veil from the hidden beauty of the world,
                            <hi rend="italic">and makes familiar objects be as if they were
                            not</hi><anchor xml:id="b020"/><pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="mid.00008.006" type="verso"/><fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="smallcaps">HALF-HOURS WITH THE BEST AUTHORS.</hi></fw>
                        <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">606</fw><milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/><hi rend="italic">familiar</hi>. It reproduces all
                        that it represents; and the impersonations clothed in its Elysian light
                        stand thenceforward in the minds of those who have once contemplated them,
                        as memorials of that gentle and exalted content which extends itself over
                        all thoughts and actions with which it coexists. The great secret of morals
                        is love, or a going out of our own nature, and an identification of
                        ourselves with the beautiful which exists in thought, action, or person, not
                        our own. A man, to be greatly good, must imagine intensely and
                        comprehensively; he must put himself in the place of another, and of many
                        others: the pains and pleasures of his species must become his own. The
                        great instrument of moral good is imagination; and poetry administers to the
                        effect by acting upon the cause."&#8212;<hi rend="italic">Essays and
                            Letters</hi>, vol. i. p. 16.</p>
                    <p>I would not willingly say anything after perorations like these; but as
                        treatises on poetry may chance to have auditors who think them selves called
                        upon to vindicate the superiority of what is termed useful knowledge, it may
                        be as well to add, that<span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="b021" from="#b021" to="#b022"/><hi rend="underline" hand="#h1"><span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="b023" from="#b023" to="#b024"/>if the poet may be allowed to pique himself on any one thing more than
                            another, compared with those who undervalue him, it is on that power of
                            undervaluing nobody, and no attainments different from his own, which is
                            given him by the very faculty of imagination they despise. The greater
                            includes the less. They do not see that their inability to comprehend
                            him argues the smaller capacity. No man recognises the worth of utility
                            more than the poet<anchor xml:id="b022"/>: he only desires that the
                            meaning of the term may not come short of its greatness, and exclude the
                            noblest necessities of his fellow-creatures.</hi><anchor xml:id="b024"/>
                        He is quite as much pleased, for instance, with the facilities for rapid
                        conveyance afforded him by the railroad, as the dullest confiner of its
                        advantages to that single idea, or as the greatest two-idead man who varies
                        that single idea with hugging himself on his "buttons" or his good dinner.
                        But he sees also the beauty of the country through which he passes, of the
                        towns, of the heavens, of the steam-engine itself, thundering and fuming
                        along like a magic horse; of the affections that are carrying, perhaps, half
                        the passengers on their journey, nay, of those of the great two-idead man;
                        and, beyond all this, he discerns the incalculable amount of good, and
                        knowledge, and refinement, and mutual consideration, which this wonderful
                        invention is fitted to</p>
                </div2>
                <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="mid.00008.007" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="smallcaps">HALF-HOURS WITH THE BEST
                        AUTHORS.</hi></fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">610</fw>
                <div2>
                    <p>are the masters that instruct us without rods and ferulas, without hard words
                        and anger, without clothes or money. If you approach them, they are not
                        asleep; if investigating you interrogate them, they conceal nothing; if you
                        mistake them, they never grumble; if you are ignorant, they cannot laugh at
                        you.</p>
                    <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="b025" from="#b025" to="#b026"/>
                    <add rend="pasteon" source="#ref1" xml:id="add1">
                        <q who="Francis William Newman" type="printed">
                            <floatingText rend="flat">
                                <body>
                                    <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="top">Hexameter
                                        translation of Homer (Prof. Newman's translation</note>
                                    <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">171</fw>
                                    <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="hobar-full"/>
                                    <p>quaint, flowing garrulous, abounding with formulas, redundant
                                        in particles and affirmatory interjections, as also in
                                        grammatical connectives of time place, and argument. In all
                                        those respects it is similar to the old English ballad, and
                                        is in sharp contrast to the polished style of Pope, Sotheby,
                                        and Cowper, the best known English translators of Homer. By
                                        general consent, Chapman's version is far more Homeric that
                                        these. In regard to diction, Dryden in part agrees with
                                        Homer, namely, in his love of strong and racy words. A
                                        phrase can hardly be too homely for the true Epic style, if
                                        it be but energetic and graphic." How far Professor Newman
                                        has succeeded in carrying out these principles will be best
                                        understood from a specimen. The passage selected is in the
                                        Twenty-first Book, where Achilles refuses mercy to
                                        Lyceaon:&#8212;</p>
                                    <q who="Newman" type="extract">
                                            <lg type="poem">
                                                <l>No ransom now to me set forth, though simpleton,
                                                  nor argue;</l>
                                                <l>For once, ere that his day of doom Patroclus
                                                  overhended,*</l>
                                                <l>So long, my heart more pleasure had to spare the
                                                  lives of Trojans,</l>
                                                <l>Nor loved their carnage: many then I took alive
                                                  and sold them.</l>
                                                <l>But now in fornt of Illium whome'er the God
                                                  entrusteth</l>
                                                <l>Into my hands, no longer one would I expect from
                                                  slaughter</l>
                                                <l>Of all the Trojans; most of all not one of
                                                  Priam's children.</l>
                                                <l>But come, my friend! die also thou. Why thus to
                                                  railing yieldest?</l>
                                                <l>Dead also is Patroclus, who than thee was greatly
                                                  better,</l>
                                                <l><hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">Behold me, what a
                                                  man am I, how comely and majestic!</hi></l>
                                                <l><hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">Me did a noble
                                                  sire beget; a goddess mother bare me.</hi></l>
                                                <l>Yet even upon <hi rend="italic">me</hi> will
                                                  Death and Destiny restless</l>
                                                <l>Come in midday or afternoon, or haply in the
                                                  morning,</l> 
                                                <l>When some one shall from me also in battle rieve
                                                  my spirit,</l>
                                                <l>Whether the spear-throw strike me down, or arrow
                                                  from the bowstring.</l>
                                            </lg>
                                        
                                    </q>
                                    <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="b027" from="#b027" to="#b028"/>
                                    <p>The style may seem rugged at first, but after a little it
                                        becomes far from unpleasant, and certainly gives a better
                                        idea of the original than the un-Homeric rhymes of Pope.</p>
                                </body>
                            </floatingText>
                        </q>
                        <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="hobar-short-center"/>
                        <anchor xml:id="b026"/><anchor xml:id="b028"/><note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="left" target="b025">☞</note><note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="left" target="b025">☞</note>
                    </add>
                    <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="bottom">☞ get Buckling's prose
                        trans of Iliad unpublished here by Harpers</note>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>