<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="rut.00020">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">"The English Mind"</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
                <author xml:id="unk">Unknown</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="jyc">Jonathan Y. Cheng</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>University of Texas at Austin</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>rut.00020</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>kprice@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Ed-Folsom@uiowa.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>bbarney2@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability><p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain exceptions, public domain works may be freely copied or used in the creation of derivative works without permission, or authorization, of the former copyright owners.</p><p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and is governed by a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0).</p><p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Unknown</author>
                    <title>"The English Mind"</title>
                    <!--<idno type="callno"></idno>-->
                    <!--<date cert="high" when="1851-08">August 1851</date>-->
                    <orgName xml:id="rut">Special Collections and University Archives, Rutgers University
                        Libraries, Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey </orgName>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from our digital image of original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="h1" scribeRef="#ww" medium="black-ink"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h2" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#jyc" when="2014-11-18">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="marginalia">
        <body>
            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="rut_nhg.00024.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">835</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="smallcaps">LITERARY NOTICES.</hi></fw>
                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
                <p>readers are ignorant of the deadly herb whose infernal power is here recorded,
                    let them know that hasheesh is the juice of the Indian hemp, the southern branch
                    of the same family which, in northern climes, grows almost totally to fibre,
                    producing materials for mats and cordage. Under a tropical sun the plant loses
                    its fibrous texture, and secretes profusely an opaque and greenish resin. This
                    has been used for ages in the East as a narcotic and stimulant, and at this day
                    forms a habitual indulgence with all classes of society in India, Persia, and
                    Turkey. The efi‘ects which it produces, both physical and intellectual, are of
                    the most extraordinary character. The experience of the author in its use is
                    here frankly and fully related, in a narrative which is equally rich in
                    psychological illustration and in imaginative vision.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Lectures on Temperance</hi>, by <hi rend="smallcaps">ELIPHALET
                        NOTT, D.D</hi>. (Published by Sheldon, Blakeman, and Co.) The devotion of
                    the venerable President of Union College to the cause of temperance is a no less
                    striking feature of his career than his exuberant eloquence, his tenacity of
                    purpose, and his wonderful elasticity of intellect. The lectures, which are here
                    published under the auspices of Mr. M‘Coy, a well-known leader in the Temperance
                    movement, and with a characteristic introduction by the learned Professor of
                    Greek in Union College, Mr. Taylor Lewis, are admirable specimens of research,
                    vigor of reasoning, vivacity of style, and a candid, catholic spirit. The chart
                    at the close of the volume, exhibiting the Bible texts which allude to wine, is
                    a document of great interest and value.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The Legal Adviser&gt;</hi>, by <hi rend="smallcaps">EDWIN D.
                        FREEDLEY</hi>. (Published by Lippincott and Co.) It is no part of the design
                    of this volume to assist any conceited ignoramus to set up as a lawyer on his
                    own account, and dispense with the services of the regular profession in case of
                    need. On the contrary, it aims at giving intelligent business-men such
                    information in regard to the elementary principles of mercantile law as may
                    guide them in their daily routine, save them the annoyance and expense of
                    litigation, or at least enlighten them as to the probable issue of a proposed
                    lawsuit. Mr. Freedley has discussed several important topics in a lucid and
                    popular manner, illustrating them with a variety of apposite examples and
                    incidents, some of which are of a singularly curious character. The doctrine of
                    agents and administrators, of commission and guarantee, of partnership, of
                    insurance, and of testamentary provisions, receives ample attention in this
                    volume; but a clear explanation of the principles and processes of mortgage and
                    hypothecation would add greatly to its completeness, and to the value of a
                    second edition.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Life Studies; or, How to Live</hi>, by the <hi rend="smallcaps">REV. JOHN BAILLIE</hi>. (Published by Harper and Brothers.) The influence
                    of religious principle, as illustrated in the biography of several eminently
                    pious individuals, is the subject of this little volume. John Bunyan is made the
                    representative of the “Good Soldier," Gerhardt Tersteegen of the “Christian
                    Laborer,” James Montgomery of the “Christian Man of Letters," Frederic Perthes
                    of the “ Man of Business," and Mary Winslow of the “Christian Mother." The
                    author has skillfully constructed a series of interesting narratives from the
                    most salient incidents of their lives, producing a work of practical religious
                    value, without the formality and dryness almost inseparable from a merely
                    didactic treatise.</p>
                <cb/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Life of Handel</hi>, by <hi rend="smallcaps">VICTOR
                        SCHOELCHER</hi>. (Published by Mason Brothers.) Composed by a distinguished
                    political exile of France, whom the troubles of his country compelled to seek
                    refuge in London, this volume is a genuine labor of love, and bears on every
                    page the enthusiasm in which it had its origin. The author learned to solace his
                    retirement in that city by listening to the oratorios of Handel&#8212;he had
                    already been impressed by their sublimity&#8212;but a further acquaintance
                    produced fresh admiration&#8212;and he at length conceived the wish to possess
                    all the works of the great master to whom he was so deeply indebted. In the
                    accomplishment of this purpose be was led to examine whatever had been written
                    concerning the life of Handel, and his researches finally grew into such
                    magnitude and importance that he decided to embody their results in a volume.
                    The present work is the fruit of that pains-taking diligence. It comprises a
                    great amount of facts and anecdotes relating to Handel with which the public is
                    not familiar, and at the same time throws much light on the musical history of
                    England, especially of the period of the introduction of the Italian Opera. The
                    American edition is arranged somewhat differently from the original, for the
                    sake of avoiding the confusion of method which impairs the London impression. It
                    contains, however, all the matter of Mr. Schoelcher‘s Work, and will be found an
                    instructive and entertaining biography.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Poems</hi>, by <hi rend="smallcaps">ROSA VERTUER JOHNSON</hi>.
                    (Published by Ticknor and Fields.) The chief recommendation of these poems is
                    their smoothness and frequent sweetness of versification, rather than any
                    remarkable boldness or originality of thought. They are evidently the
                    productions of a cultivated and refined mind, liberally endowed with poetical
                    instincts, but with no fervent saliency of imagination.</p>

                <p><hi rend="italic">First Book of Chemistry and the allied Sciences</hi>, by <hi rend="smallcaps">JOHN A. PORTER</hi>. (Published by A. S. Barnes and Co.)
                    The Professor of Chemistry in Yale College has performed a valuable service to
                    the cause of scientific education in the preparation of this elementary
                    treatise. It is founded on a thorough practical knowledge of the subject, and
                    displays a skill in brief and lucid exposition that is not common among men most
                    eminent for their scientific attainments. The main topics in the rudiments of
                    chemistry are presented in the natural order of succession, and illustrated by a
                    great variety of well-selected and apposite examples. Agricultural chemistry and
                    geology are briefly treated in separate chapters, forming an appropriate
                    conclusion t6 the main discussions of the work. Like most judicious manuals for
                    juvenile instruction, this volume may be used to great advantage as an authority
                    for current reference.</p>

                <p><hi rend="italic">Floral Home; or, First Years of Minnesota</hi> by <hi rend="smallcaps">HARRIET E. BISHOP</hi>. (Published by Sheldon, Blakeman,
                    and Co.) The progress of the portion of the great Northwest to which the present
                    volume is devoted, is vividly described in these personal recollections of a
                    lady connected with the Indian missions in that quarter. It is some ten years
                    since she commenced the work of religious benevolence among the natives, and
                    during that interval she has had ample opportunities of witnessing the rapid
                    development of the country. She relates her experience with a certain degree of
                    enthusiasm, but her narrative is highly interesting, full of information, and
                    apparently worthy of en‘ tire credence.</p>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="rut_nhg.00023.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <div1>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="top"><handShift new="#h1"/>This essay
                    explains a great deal in English Literature &#8212; illumines a great deal also
                    in English manners, politics, &amp;c &amp;c. </note>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="top right">8</note>
                <head>Editor's Table.</head>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">THE ENGLISH MIND</hi>.&#8212;It is hardly necessary for us
                    to say that a nation is not a mere aggregation of existing individuals, or
                    collection of provinces and colonies, but an organic living body of laws,
                    institutions, manners, and literature, whose present condition is the result of
                    the slow growth of ages, and whose roots stretch far back into the past life of
                    the people. By a national mind we mean the whole moral and mental life of a
                    nation, as embodied in its facts and latent in its sentiments and ideas. This
                        <hi rend="italic">body</hi> of mind, the organization of centuries,
                    exercises, in virtue of its mass, a positive attractive force on all individual
                    minds within the sphere of its influence, compelling them to be partakers of the
                    thoughts and passions of the national heart and brain, and receiving in return
                    their contributions of individual thoughts and passions. Now a national mind is
                    great according to the vitality and vigor at the centre of its being, the
                    fidelity with which it resists whatever is foreign to nature, and its consequent
                    perseverance in its own inherent laws of development. Tried by these tests, that
                    pyramidal organism, with John Bull at the base and <choice>
                        <orig>Shakspeare</orig>
                        <reg>Shakespeare</reg>
                    </choice> at the apex, which we call the English mind, is unexcelled, if not
                    unequalled, in modern times for its sturdy force of being, its muscular strength
                    of faculty, the variety of its directing sentiments, and its tough hold upon
                    existence. No other national mind combines such vast and various creativeness,
                    and presents so living a synthesis of seemingly elemental contradictions, which
                    is at the same time marked by such distinctness of individual features. That
                    imperial adjective, English, fits its sedition as well as its servility, its
                    radicalism as well as its conservatism, its squalor as well as its splendor, its
                    vice as well as its virtue, its morality and religion as well as its politics
                    and government. The unity of its nature is never lost in all the prodigious
                    variety of its manifestation. Prince, peasant, Cavalier, Roundhead, Whig, Tory,
                    poet, penny-a-liner, philanthropist, ruffian&#8212;William Wilberforce in
                    Parliament, Richard Turpin on the York road&#8212;all agree in being English,
                    all agree in a common contempt, blatant or latent, for everything not English.
                    Liberty is English, wisdom is English, philosophy is English, religion is
                    English, earth is English, air is English, heaven is English, hell is English.
                    And this imperious dogmatism, too, has none of the uneasy self-distrust which
                    peeps through the vociferous brag of corresponding American phenomena; but,
                    expressing its seated faith in egotism's most exquisite <hi rend="italic">non
                        sequiturs</hi>, it says stoutly, with Parson Adams, "A schoolmaster is the
                    greatest of men, and I am the greatest of schoolmasters;" and, moreover, it
                    believes what it says. The quality is not in the tongue, but in the character of
                    the nation.</p>
                <p>This solid self-confidence and pride of nationality, this extraordinary content
                    with the image reflected in the mirror of self-esteem, indicates that the
                    national mind is not tormented by the subtle sting of abstract opinions or the
                    rebuking glance of unrealized ideals, but that its reason and imagination work
                    on the level of its Will. The essential peculiarity, therefore, of the English
                    Mind is its basis in Character, and consequent hold upon facts and disregard of
                    abstractions. Coarse, strong,<cb/> massive, sturdy, practical,&#8212;organizing
                    its thoughts into faculties, and toughening its faculties into the consistency
                    of muscle and bone,&#8212;its whole soul is so embodied and embrained, that it
                    imprints on its most colossal mental labors the stern characteristics of sheer
                    physical strength. It not only has fire, but fuel enough to feed its fire. Its
                    thoughts are acts, its theories are institutions, its volitions are events. It
                    has no ideas not inherent in its own organization, or which it has not
                    assimilated and absorbed into its own nature by collision or communion with
                    other national minds. It is enriched but never overpowered by thoughts and
                    impulses from abroad, for whatever it receives it forces into harmony with its
                    own broadening processes of interior development. Thus the fiery, quick-witted,
                    wilful and unscrupulous Norman encamped in its domains, and being unable to
                    reject him, and its own stubborn vitality refusing to succumb, it slowly and
                    sullenly, through long centuries, absorbed him into itself, and blended fierce
                    Norman pride and swift Norman intelligence with its own solid substance of sense
                    and humor. By the same jealous and resisting, but assimilative method, it
                    gradually incorporated the principles of Roman law into its jurisprudence, and
                    the spirit of Italian, Spanish, and German thought into its literature,
                    receiving nothing, however, which it did not modify with its own individuality,
                    and scrawling "England, her mark," equally on what it borrowed and what it
                    created.</p>
                <p>A national mind thus rooted in character, with an organizing genius directed by
                    homely sentiments, and with its sympathies fastened on palpable aims and
                    objects, has all the strength which comes from ideas invigorated but narrowed by
                    facts. General maxims disturb it not, for it never acts from reason alone, or
                    passion alone, or understanding alone; but reason, passion, understanding,
                    conscience, religious sentiment, are all welded together in its thoughts and
                    actions, and pure reason, or pure conscience, or pure passion, it not only
                    neglects, but stigmatizes. Its principles are precedents buttressed by
                    prejudices, and these are obstinately asserted from force of character rather
                    than reasoned out by force of intellect. "Taffy," said swearing Lord Chancellor
                    Thurlow to Lord Kenyon, "you are obstinate, and give no reasons; now Scott is
                    obstinate, too, but he gives reasons&#8212;and d&#8212;d bad ones they are!"</p>
                <p>Indeed, the English mind believes what it practises, and practises what it
                    believes, and is rarely weakened in its active power by perceiving a law of
                    morality or intelligence higher than its own practical morality and
                    intelligence. It meets all emergencies with expedients, and gives to its reasons
                    the emphasis of its will. Bringing everything to the test of common sense and
                    fact, it is blind to the operation cf the great laws of rectitude and
                    retribution objective to itself, but trusts that the same practical sagacity and
                    practical energy which have heretofore met real dangers, will meet impending
                    dangers when they become real. It has no forecasting science of right, but when
                    self-preservation depends on its doing right, the most abstract requirements of
                    justice will be "done into English" in as coarse and as sensible a way as its
                    old hack-writers translated Juvenal and Plutarch.</p>
            </div1>




        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>