<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="rut.00019">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">"American Mind"</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
                <author xml:id="unk">Unknown</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="jyc">Jonathan Y. Cheng</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>University of Texas at Austin</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>rut.00019</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>kprice@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Ed-Folsom@uiowa.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>bbarney2@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability><p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain exceptions, public domain works may be freely copied or used in the creation of derivative works without permission, or authorization, of the former copyright owners.</p><p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and is governed by a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0).</p><p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Unknown</author>
                    <title>"American Mind"</title>
                    <!--<idno type="callno"></idno>-->
                    <date cert="high" when="1851-08">August 1851</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="rut">Special Collections and University Archives, Rutgers University
                        Libraries, Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey </orgName>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from our digital image of original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="h2" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#jyc" when="2014-11-07">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="marginalia">
        <body>
            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="rut_nhg.00016.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">691</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="smallcaps">LITERARY NOTICES.</hi></fw>
                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
                <delSpan rend="hashmark" spanTo="#d01"/>
                <p>-cial histories, treatises in different departments of science, and one or two
                    works on the general history of Brazil have made their appearance within the
                    last few years. French publications are to be found in abundance on the shelves
                    of the booksellers, especially on scientific, historical, and philosophical
                    subjects, many of the last often being of a skeptical character. A variety of
                    interesting books are produced under the authority of the Government, consisting
                    of the reports of the Ministers of the Empire&#8212;Finance, Justice, Foreign
                    Affairs, War, and the Navy. These are prepared with great care, and contain much
                    valuable matter for the statesman and the general reader. The periodical
                    literature of Rio includes a <hi rend="italic">Medical Review</hi> and a <hi rend="italic">Brazilian and Foreign Quarterly</hi>, the latter of which is
                    conducted with ability, and promises to be of national service, although it
                    relies too much on translations in comparison with the efforts of native talent.
                    Journalism flourishes in Rio, is respectably sustained in a literary point of
                    view, and pays well. The external appearance of the newspapers is like that of
                    the Parisian journals, except the Brazilian dailies are of a larger size and of
                    superior mechanical execution. The bottom of each sheet has its <hi rend="italic">feuilleton</hi> for light reading, and on every Sunday the
                    principal journal has several columns of local and personal gossip. The
                    newspaper press is very prolific, issuing four dailies, several tri-weeklies,
                    and from six to ten weeklies and irregular sheets. Verbatim reports of the
                    proceedings of the National Assembly are published at length on the morning
                    after their occurrence. Some of the journals take much pains to give full and
                    correct reports of commercial intelligence, while none of them are encumbered
                    with standing advertisements. On the contrary, the advertisements are renewed
                    almost every day, and by their piquancy and variety furnish matter for several
                    entertaining columns. There are also in Rio a number of public institutions for
                    the cultivation of literature and science and the diffusion of knowledge. The
                    National Library contains 100,000 volumes. The English, German, and Portuguese
                    residents have established subscription libraries for their own use
                    respectively. The National Museum has a valuable collection of mineralogical
                    specimens, and many curious aboriginal relics. Almost all the leading men of
                    Brazil belong to the learned professions. No high position in the state is
                    filled by either a merchant or mechanic. Other topics of great interest are
                    treated of in this instructive volume, which will at once take a high place
                    among our works of reference on the Brazilian empire. It is brought out in a
                    neat edition, with unexceptionable type and paper, and a variety of appropriate
                    illustrations.</p>

                <p><hi rend="italic">Souvenirs of Travel</hi>, by Madame <hi rend="smallcaps">OCTAVIA WALTON LE VERT</hi>. (Published by S. H. Goetzel and Co.) The
                    author of these European recollections is famed throughout the United States for
                    her personal accomplishments, attractive manners, and social popularity. A
                    favorite wherever she is known, and the idol of her intimate acquaintance, she
                    was received in European society with a genial cordiality which naturally
                    prevented her from seeing any thing but the brightest aspects of the brilliant
                    living panorama which passed before her admiring and enthusiastic gaze. Her
                    experience in the capitals of Europe appears to have been a succession of
                    triumphs. Courted, appreciated, and honored both in the gayest and the wisest
                    circles,<cb/> it was natural that she should bring away only the most
                    rose-colored impressions. Hence the tone of her book will strike indifferent
                    readers as too encomiastic, too jubilant, nor will they at once respond to the
                    facility with which she takes them into her most private confidences. The warm
                    expressions of gratification and delight with which she records the attentions
                    that she received from the paragons of English and Continental humanity, though
                    well suited to the temperature of a friendly correspondence, are rather too
                    personal in their nature for the bleaker and less hospitable atmosphere of the
                    world. They speak better for the kindliness of her disposition than for the
                    severity of her discretion. Her volumes are largely occupied with the details of
                    society. They present little new information on topics of important bearing, and
                    do not pretend to the authority of a guide-book or a treatise on statistics. Her
                    writing is most successful when she describes scenes of every-day social
                    interest in which she bore a prominent part. When she leaves the personal sphere
                    for the statement of more general facts, she often repeats well-known
                    circumstances, assuming too little information on the part of her readers. Her
                    reflections and comments always betray an amiable frame of mind, but are not
                    remarkable either for acuteness or originality. One can easily imagine the
                    delight with which such letters would be welcomed in the kindly family circle,
                    and if the outside reader is tempted to complain of their light and superficial
                    character, he should bear in mind that they were not originally intended for
                    publication. The introductory remarks by the publishers, urging the pretensions
                    of the authoress in the most extravagant manner, are in bad taste, and will tend
                    to damage her work in public estimation. </p>

                <p><hi rend="italic">Guy Livingstone</hi> (published by Harper and Brothers) is the
                    title of a racy English novel, written with a terse vigor of expression ; though
                    not without a dash of the melodramatic in certain situations, and remarkable for
                    the brilliant intensity of its character-drawing. The materials are drawn from
                    exceptional phases of human life, and are wrought up into a narrative of
                    uncommon power and interest.</p>

                <p><hi rend="italic">The Romance of Western History</hi>, by <hi rend="smallcaps">JAMES HALL</hi>, is a new collection of papers by that indefatigable
                    explorer of Western traditions, life, and history. It is not surpassed in
                    interest by his previous works on the same subject. (Published by Applegate and
                    Co., Cincinnati.)</p>

                <p><hi rend="italic">The Five Gateways of Knowledge</hi>, by <hi rend="smallcaps">GEORGE WILSON</hi>. (Published by Parry and M‘Millan.) A popular exposition
                    of the processes of the senses considered as the avenues to the intellect. It is
                    an ingenious and pleasing work, as well as a highly instructive one.</p>

                <p><hi rend="italic">A Manual of Business, and Guide to Success</hi>. (Published by
                    Fowler and Wells.) The closing number of the popular series entitled “
                    Hand-Books for Home Improvement." They comprise a variety of practical
                    directions on various important subjects, and are well adapted for general
                    utility.</p>

                <p>Ticknor and Fields have issued, in their uniform of blue-and-gold, an edition of
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">LEIGHT HUNT's</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi>, comprising all the acknowledged productions of
                    that honeyed hard, and collected under his own supervision and advice. It is
                    introduced by a neat preface from the pen of the American editor, Mr. S. Adams
                    Lee, and is embellished with a portrait of the author.</p>
                <anchor xml:id="d01"/>
            </div1>

            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="rut_nhg.00015.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="top"><handShift new="#h2"/><hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">American Mind</hi></note>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="top right">7</note>

            <div1>
                <head type="main-authorial">Editor's Table.</head>

                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">THE AMERICAN MIND</hi>.&#8212;In studying literature and
                    history, we are at first attracted by particular events and individual minds,
                    and we rise but gradually to the conception of nations and national
                    minds&#8212;including, of course, under the latter phrase, all the great moving,
                    vital powers expressed in the phenomena of a nation’s life. The external
                    history, the political institutions, the literature, laws, and manners of a
                    people, are but its thoughts in visible or audible expression, and ever carry us
                    back to the Mind whence they proceeded, and from which they received their
                    peculiar national character. “To can not form just notions even of individuals
                    without viewing them as related to their age and country&#8212;as expressions,
                    more or less emphatic, of the National Mind, in whose depths their personal
                    being bad its root, and from whose vitality they drew the pith and nerve of
                    character. Thus Pericles, Scipio, and Chatham lose much of their raciness and
                    genuineness if not considered as related in this way to Greece, Rome, and
                    England, who bore them, nurtured them, colored and directed their thoughts and
                    passions, clothed them with power as with a garment, so that Greece saw in
                    Pericles the mirror of her own supple strength and plastic intellect; and Rome
                    beheld in Scipio the image of her own fixed will and large reason; and England
                    recognized in Chatham's swift Norman energy and solid Saxon sense the child who
                    had drained honesty, intelligence, and imperious pride from her own arrogant
                    breast. It thus requires a great people to bear a breed of great men, for great
                    men require strong incitements; a field for action; courage, power, glory, and
                    virtue around as well as within them; and if powerful natures do not start
                    naturally up, to meet any terrible emergency of a nation's life, we may be sure
                    that the National Mind has become weak and corrupt, has “lost the breed of noble
                    bloods," and that external enemies, like empirics dealing with consumptive
                    patients, only accelerate a death already doomed by interior decay.</p>

                <p>Thus, when we would comprehend in one inclusive term the intellect and
                    individuality of Greece, or Rome, or England, we speak of the Greek, or Roman,
                    or English Mind. A national mind implies a nation, not a mere aggregation of
                    individuals or states; and we propose now to consider the question, Whether or
                    not there is such a thing as an American Mind; and if so, what are its
                    characteristics and tendencies; what is the inspiration, and what the direction
                    it gives to the individual man in America?</p>

                <p>In treating this subject, it is important that we avoid all that blatant and
                    bragging tone in which American conceit thinly <choice>
                        <orig>vails</orig>
                        <reg>veils</reg>
                    </choice> its self-distrust ; that a deaf ear be presented to the exulting
                    dissonance of the American chanticleer; that the Pilgrim Fathers be disturbed as
                    little as possible in their well-earned graves; and that the different parts of
                    the discourse be not found, like the compositions of certain eminent musicians,
                    to be but symphonious variations on the one tune of “ Yankee Doodle" or “ Hail
                    Columbia!"</p>

                <p>And, first, in view of the variety of races and interests included under our
                    government, can we assert the existence of an American Mind? We certainly can
                    not do this in the sense in which we say there was a Greek mind, whose birth,
                    growth, maturity, and decay we can take in at one grasp of <cb/>
                </p>

                <p> generalization; or in the sense in which we say there is an English mind,
                    full-grown and thoroughly organized in manners, institutions, and literature.
                    All that we can assert is that the thoughts, acts, and characters of Plymouth
                    Puritan and Virginia Cavalier, through two centuries of active existence, have
                    been fused into a mass of national thought, character, and life; and that this
                    national life has sufficient energy and pliancy to assimilate the foreign
                    natures incessantly pouring into it, and to grow, through this process of
                    assimilation, into a comprehensive national mind. At present we can discern
                    little more than tendencies, and the clash and conflict of the various elements;
                    but the strongest force&#8212;the force to which the other elements gravitate,
                    and by which they will all eventually be absorbed&#8212;is the Saxon-English
                    element, in its modified American form. The Celt, the German, the Englishman,
                    the Italian, can exist here only by parting with his national individuality; for
                    he is placed in a current of influences which inevitably melts him down into the
                    mass of American life. But while this absorption changes his character, it
                    modifies also the character of the absorbing force ; for the American Mind, with
                    every infusion of foreign mind, adds to its being an element which does not lie
                    as a mere novelty on its surface, but penetrates into its flexible and fluid
                    substance, mixes with its vital blood, and enriches or impoverishes, elevates or
                    depraves, its inmost nature; and so organic in its character is this seeming
                    abstraction of a nation, that for every such infusion of a foreign element each
                    citizen is either injured or benefited, and finds that he acts and thinks the
                    better or the worse for it. The balm or the poison steals mysteriously into him
                    from all surrounding circumstances: from the press, from politics, from trade,
                    from social communion, from the very air he breathes, come the currents of a new
                    life, to warm or to chill, to invigorate or deaden, his individual heart and
                    brain. This fact goes under the name of a change in public sentiment; and have
                    we not often witnessed its miracles of apostasy or conversion wrought on men
                    whose characters we fondly thought fixed as fate?</p>

                <p>The American Mind thus promises to be a composite mind&#8212;composite in the
                    sense of assimilation, not of mere aggregation. Its two original elements were
                    the Englishman who came here to found, repair, or increase his estate; and the
                    Englishman who was driven here by political and ecclesiastical oppression. Of
                    these, the stronger of the two is undoubtedly the latter; and the last probe of
                    historical and critical analysis touches him at the nation's centre and heart.
                    This Puritan Englishman was all character: strong in the energy, courage,
                    practical skill, and hard persistency of character: with a characteristic
                    religion, morality, and temper of mind; at once the most forcible and the most
                    exclusive man that the seventeenth century produced. Yet from this bigoted,
                    austere, iron-willed, resisting, and persisting Saxon religionist
                    &#8212;intolerant of other natures, from the very solidity and lowering might of
                    his own&#8212;has sprung the flexible, assimilative, compromising,
                    all-accomplished Yankee, who is neither Puritan nor Cavalier, Englishman,
                    Irishman, Frenchman, nor German, hut seems to have a touch of them all, and is
                    ready to receive and absorb them all. A Protean personage, he can accommodate
                    himself to any cir- <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="rut_nhg.00017.jpg" type="recto"/> -cumstances, to all forms of society, government, and religion. He is the
                    staid, sensible farmer, merchant, or mechanic of New England, with his
                    restlessness subdued into inveterate industry and power of rigid application;
                    but he is also Sam Slick in the provinces, and Nimrod Wildfire in Kentucky, and
                    Jefferson Brick on the frontier. Through all disguises, and in every clime
                    visited by sin and trade, peep the shrewd twinkle of his knowing eyes and the
                    multiform movements of his cunning fingers! Let him drop down in Siberia or
                    Japan, in England or Italy, in a Southern plantation or Western settlement, and
                    he seems to say, “Gentlemen, behold the smartest man in all creation! one who
                    will put your brain into his head, get at your secret, and beat you in the art
                    of being yourselves; so please fall into rank, deliver up your purses,
                    acknowledge your born lord and king !"</p>

                <p>We have not time to discuss here the question, how a national mind, which is
                    distinguished above all others for mental hospitality and general availableness,
                    had its root in a Puritanism as unaccommodating as it was powerful. It is,
                    perhaps, sufficient to say, in explanation, that the Puritan, narrow and
                    isolated as he seems, had one side of his nature wide open to liberal
                    influences. His religious creed, it is true, was authoritative ; he submitted to
                    it himself, he enforced it upon others; but in political speculation he was
                    audaciously independent. In the art and science of government he had no European
                    equal either among statesmen or philosophers, and his politics, constantly
                    connected as they were with his industrial enterprise, eventually undermined his
                    despotic theology. But our business here is with the American Mind as it now is,
                    and as it promises to be hereafter. This mind we must consider as having its
                    expression in the nation's life; and certainly the first survey of it reveals-a
                    confusion of qualities which apparently elude analysis, and defy generalization.
                    This confusion results, as in the individual mind, from the variety of
                    unassimilated elements in contact or collision with the national personality;
                    and accordingly its harmony is disturbed by a mob of noisy opinions, which never
                    have, and some of which we trust never will, become living ideas and active
                    forces. The consequence of this juxtaposition of mental organization with mental
                    anarchy, in a national mind hospitable to every thing, and now only visible to
                    us in its fierce, swift, devouring growth, is a lack of solidity, depth, and
                    tenacity in comparison with its nimbleness, and a disposition to combine a
                    superficial enthusiasm for theories with a shrewd hold upon things throughout
                    the broad field of its restless, curious, inventive, appropriative, scheming,
                    plausible, glorious, and vain-glorious activity. But the two grand leading
                    characteristics of its essential nature are energy and impressibility ;--an
                    impressibility all alive to the most various objects, and receptive of elements
                    conflicting with each other&#8212;and a primitive, inherent energy, too quick, fiery,
                    and buoyant to be submerged by the wealth of life which its impressibility pours
                    into it; an energy which whelms in its stream all slower and feebler natures
                    with whom it comes in contact, and rushes onward with the force of fate and the
                    intelligence of direction.</p>

                <p>In estimating the quantity and quality of this mental energy, we must ascertain
                    the different channels of work and production into which it is poured. Work of
                    some kind is the measure of its power and the test of its quality; but we
                    must<cb/>avoid the fallacy of supposing that art and literature are the only
                    expressions of a nation’s intellect. It would, indeed, be a grotesque libel on
                    some ten millions of educated people to declare, that American literature
                    represented more than a fraction of American intelligence. That intelligence has
                    received a practical direction, and is ex' pressed, not in Iliads and
                    æneids, not in Principals and Cartoons, but in commerce, in manufactures,
                    in the liberal professions, in the mechanic arts, in the arts of government and
                    legislation, in all those fields of labor where man grapples directly with
                    nature, or with social problems which perplex his practical activity. To
                    describe the miracles which American energy has wrought in these departments
                    would be to invade a domain sacred to caucus speeches and all kinds of
                    starred-and-striped bravado, and perhaps they speak for themselves with far more
                    emphasis than orators can speak for them, having hieroglyphed, as Carlyle would
                    say, “America, her mark,” over a whole continent; but it is not generally
                    admitted that mind, analytical, assimilative, constructive, creative mind, is as
                    much implied in these practical directions of intelligence as in abstract
                    science and the fine arts; so that, if a sudden upward ideal turn were given to
                    the national sentiment, the intellectual energy which would leave contriving
                    railroads, calculating markets, and creating capital, and rush into epics,
                    lyrics, and pastorals, would make Wall Street stare and totter, and our present
                    generation of poets strangle themselves with their own lines. Indeed
                    observation, reason, and imagination are powers which do not lose their nature
                    in their application to widely different objects. Thus Sir William Hamilton, the
                    acutest analyst of Aristotle's mental processes, declares that abstruse and
                    seemingly juiceless metaphysician to have had as great an imagination as Homer ;
                    and though we are prone to associate imagination with some elevation of
                    sentiment, <choice>
                        <orig>Shakspeare</orig>
                        <reg>Shakespeare</reg>
                    </choice> has given more of it to Iago, and Goethe has given more of it to
                    Mephistopheles, than Nature gave to Bishop Heber, the purest of England's minor
                    poets. Applying this principle to business, we shall find much to disturb the
                    self-content of second-rate <hi rend="italic">litterateura</hi> and canons, who
                    are accustomed to congratulate themselves that, if others have the money, they
                    at least have the brain, if we should sharply scrutinize the mental processes of
                    a first-rate merchant. Is it observation you demand? Behold with what keen
                    accuracy he perceives and discriminates facts. Is it understanding? Look at the
                    long trains of reasoning&#8212;the conclusion of each argument forming the
                    premises of the next&#8212;by which he moves, step by step, to an induction on
                    whose soundness he risks character and fortune. Is it will? Mark him when a
                    financial hurricane sweeps over the money-market, and observe how firm is his
                    grasp of principles, and how intelligently his cold eye surveys the future,
                    while croakers all around him are selling and sacrificing their property in
                    paroxysms of imbecile apprehension. Is it imagination? See how, to him, in his
                    dingy counting-house, the past becomes present, and the distant near; his mind
                    speeding from St. Petersburg to London, from Smyrna to Calcutta, on wings which
                    mock the swiftness of steamers and telegraphs; or, bridging over the spaces
                    which divide sensible realities from ideal possibilities, see him blend in one
                    consistent idea and purpose stray thoughts and separate facts, whose hidden
                    analogies the eye alone of <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="rut_nhg.00018.jpg" type="verso"/>
                    <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">694</fw>
                    <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="smallcaps">HARPER'S NEW MONTHLY
                            MAGAZINE</hi></fw>
                    <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/> imagination could divine. Is
                    it, in short, general force and refinement. of mind? Behold how comprehensive
                    and how cautious is his glance over that sensitive, quivering, ever-shifting sea
                    of commercial phenomena&#8212;so wide as to belt the globe, and so intimately
                    connected that a jar in any part sends a thrill through the whole&#8212;and note
                    with what subtle certainty of insight he penetrates beneath the seeming anarchy,
                    and clutches the slippery and elusive, but unvarying laws. There is, indeed, a
                    commercial genius, as well as a poetical and meta, physical genius&#8212;the
                    faculties the same, the sentiments and the direction different. Wealth may be,
                    if you please, often insolent and unfeeling; may scorn as visionary things more
                    important than wealth; but still it is less frequently blundered into than
                    artists and philosophers are inclined to believe.</p>
                <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="b001" from="#b001" to="#b002"/>
                <p>But though we can thus trace the same radical mental energy in industrial as in
                    artistical labors, the force and durability of a nation's mind still demand not
                    only diversity in its industrial occupations, but a diversity in the direction
                    of the mind itself, which shall answer to the various sentiments and capacities
                    of the soul. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">It is in this comprehension that
                        most nations fail, their activity being narrowed by the dominion of one
                        impulse and tendency, which leads them to the summit of <note xml:id="n001" target="u001" type="authorial" place="left" anchored="true">☞</note><hi rend="underline" hand="#h2" xml:id="u001">some
                            special excellence</hi>, and then surely precipitates them into decay
                        and ruin. Such narrowness is the death of mind, and national exclusiveness
                        is national suicide.</hi> Thus the genius and capital of Italy were
                    disproportionately directed to the fine arts; its wealth is now, accordingly,
                    too much in palaces and cathedrals, in pictures and statues; <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">and its worship of beauty, and disdain of the
                        practical, have resulted in an idle and impoverished people, without
                        persistency, without energy, without even artistical creativeness, and the
                        easy prey of insolent French and Austrian arms and diplomacy.</hi> Such a
                    country can not be made free by introducing acres of rant on the rights of man,
                        <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">but by establishing commerce, manufactures,
                        and a living industry</hi>. Again, the higher philosophy of Germany has been
                    directed too exclusively to abstract speculation, altogether removed from actual
                    life; and the reason is not to be sought in the assertion that the German mind
                    lacks solidity, but in the fact that an arbitrary government has heretofore
                    refused all freedom to German thought, unless it were exercised in a region
                    above the earth and beyond politics, and there it may be the chartered libertine
                    of chaos or atheism.<anchor xml:id="b002"/> By thus denying citizenship to the
                    thinker, the State has made him licentious in speculation. He may theorize
                    matter out of existence, Christ out of the Scriptures, and God out of the
                    universe, and the government nods in the very sleepiness of toleration; but the
                    moment he doubts the wisdom of some brazen and nonsensical lie embodied in a
                    law, or whispers aught against the meanest official underling, he does it with
                    the dungeon or the scaffold staring him in the face; and the grim headsman
                    reminds him that he lives under a paternal government, where he is free to
                    blaspheme God, but not to insult the House of Hapsburg. Now, as the German‘s
                    metaphysics have been vitiated by his lack of political rights, and as the
                    Italian‘s exclusive devotion to art has <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="b003" from="#b003" to="#b004"/>extinguished even the energy by which
                    art is produced, so there is danger that our extreme practical and political
                    turn will vulgarize and debase our national mind to that low point where the
                        energy<anchor xml:id="b004"/><note xml:id="n002" target="b003" type="authorial" place="left" anchored="true">☞</note><cb/>
                    <span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="b005" from="#b005" to="#b006"/>and
                    the motive to industrial production is lost. There can be no reasonable fear
                    that the beautiful in art or the transcendental in thought will overwhelm our
                    faculty of making bargains; but there is danger that the nation’s worship of
                    labors whose worth is measured by money will give a sordid character to its
                    mightiest exertions of power, eliminate heroism from its motives, destroy all
                    taste for lofty speculation, and all love for ideal beauty, and inflame
                    individuals with a devouring self-seeking, corrupting the very core of the
                    national life. The safety of the American from this gulf of selfishness and
                    avarice is to be looked for, partly in the prodigious moral, mental, and
                    benevolent agencies he has established all around him, and partly in that not
                    unamiable vanity by which he is impelled, not only to make money, but to do
                    something great or “ smart" in his way of making it.<anchor xml:id="b006"/>
                    <note xml:id="n003" target="b005" type="authorial" place="right" anchored="true">☜</note></p>
                <p>This living and restless mass of being which forms the organic body of American
                    life&#8212;decent, orderly, respectable, intelligent, and productive&#8212; with
                    Economics as the watchword of its onward movement, has, from the intensity of
                    its practical direction, roused the diseased opposition of <span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="b007" from="#b007" to="#b008"/><hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">two classes on the vanishing extremes of its
                        solid substance; namely, a class of violent reformers who scorn economics on
                        the ground of morality, and a class of violent radicals who scorn economics
                        on the ground of glory;</hi> and these are in irreconcilable enmity with
                    each other, as well as in distempered antagonism to the nation. The first class,
                    commonly passing under the name of “ Come-outers," have almost carried the
                    principle of free-will and personal responsibility to the extent of converting
                    themselves from individuals into individualisms, and they brand every man who
                    consents to stay in a wicked community like ours as a participant in the guilt
                    and profits of its sins.<anchor xml:id="b008"/><note xml:id="n004" target="b007" type="authorial" place="right" anchored="true">☜</note> The
                    Come-outer, when he thoroughly comes out, protests against the whole life of
                    society, from certain abstract propositions condemning all its concrete laws,
                    customs, morality, and religion, and strives to separate himself from the
                    national mind, and live morally and mentally apart from it. But this last is a
                    hopeless effort. To the community he is vitally bound, and he can no more escape
                    from it than he can escape from the grasp of the earth’s attraction should he
                    leap into the air for the purpose of establishing. himself away off in space.
                    The earth would say to him, as she hauled him back, “If you dislike my forests,
                    fell them; if my mountains trouble you, blast through them; plant in me what you
                    will, and, climate permitting, it shall grow; but as for your leaving me, and
                    speeding off into infinite space on a vagabond excursion round the sun on your
                    own account, that you shall not do, so help me&#8212;gravitation!"</p>
                <p>It is needless to say that the Come-outer, in his zeal for abstract morality,
                    glories in a heroic indifference to consequences, and conscientious blindness to
                    the mutual relations of rights and duties. Intrenched in some passionate
                    proposition, he exhibits a perfect mastery of <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">that logic of anarchy by which single virtues, detached from their
                        relations, are pushed into fanaticism and foam into vices. Virtue consists
                        in the harmony of virtues</hi>; but, divorcing moral insight from moral
                    sentiment, he ignores the complexity of the world‘s practical affairs, and would
                    go, in the spirit of Schiller's zealot,<q><p>“ Right onward like the lightning
                            and Tho cannon ball. opening with murderous crush His way to blast and
                            ruin." </p></q>
                    <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="rut_nhg.00019.jpg" type="recto"/>
                    <note xml:id="n005" type="authorial" place="top"><del type="overstrike" hand="#h2">yes a</del></note>
                    <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">695</fw>
                    <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="smallcaps">EDITOR'S TABLE.</hi></fw>
                    <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/> Indeed, he sometimes brings to
                    mind the story of that wise man who, when he desired to make a. cup of tea,
                    could hit upon no happier contrivance for boiling the kettle than by placing it
                    in the kitchen and setting his house on fire. Again, he is sometimes raised to
                    such a height of feverish indignation as to mistake his ruptures of moral rage
                    for prophetic fury, and anticipates the stern, sure, silent march of avenging
                    laws with a blast that splits the brazen throats of denunciation's hundred
                    trumpets. In view of the evils of the world he seems hungry for a fire from
                    heaven to smite and consume iniquity. His prayer seems continually to be, “ O
                    Lord, why so slow?" and though this discontent may be termed by some admiring
                    enthusiasts a divine impatience, it appears to be rather an impatience with
                    Divinity. It is the exact opposite of that sublime repose in the purposes of
                    Providence expressed by the philosophical historian, that “God moves through
                    history as the giants of 110mer through space: he takes a step&#8212;and ages
                    have rolled away!"</p>
                <p>Doubtless, in this class of extreme social protestants&#8212;a class whose
                    peculiarities we have doubtless heightened, in attempting to individualize its
                    ideal&#8212;there is much talent, much disinterestedness, much unflinching
                    courage, and if they would make a modest contribution of these to the nation‘s
                    moral life, they and society would both be gainers; but they are “
                    self-withdrawn into such wondrous depth" of hostile seclusion, that they are
                    only visible in their occasional incursions, or when they encamp in the
                    community during Anniversary Week. They are not, in fact, more narrow, more
                    ridden by their one idea of morals, than many of our practical men, who are
                    ridden by their one idea of money ; but their extravagance of phrase, almost
                    annihilating, as it does, the meaning of words considered as signs of things,
                    prevents their influencing the people they attack; and after beginning with a
                    resounding promise to reform the world, they too often end in a desperate
                    emulation among themselves to bear off the palm in vehemence of execration,
                    launched against all those organized institutions by which society is protected
                    from the worst consequences of its worldliness, selfishness, sensuality, and
                    crime.</p>
                <p>As the class of persons to which we have just referred push the principle of
                    individualism to the extent of forswearing allegiance to the community, so there
                    is another class, on the opposite extreme, who carry the doctrine of a
                    Providence in human affairs to a fatalistic conclusion, which they are pleased
                    to call Manifest Destiny ; a doctrine which baptizes robbery and murder as
                    providential phenomena&#8212;what kind and condescending patrons of Providence
                    these blackguards are, to be sure !&#8212;of inherent national tendencies; considers
                    national sins simply as necessary events in the nation's progress to glory; and
                    by treating every direction given to the public mind as inevitable, is sure to
                    inflame and pamper the worst. This dogma&#8212;the coinage of rogues, who find
                    it very convenient to call man’s guilt by the name of God's
                    providence&#8212;mostly obtains on the southern frontier of our country, where
                    the settlers, amidst their forests and swamps, have a delectable view of the
                    land flowing with milk and honey, which destiny manifestly intends they shall
                    occupy, on the clearest principles of the argumentation of rapine. It must be
                    admitted that this class of our fellow-sinners and citizens, by holding up
                    endless war and hectic glory <cb/> in the faces of our shrewd and prudent
                    worldlings, scare them much more than the hottest and heartiest invectives of
                    the reformers. We hear, it seems, with bland composure the charge of being
                    robbers and murderers, tyrants and liberticides; but our blood runs cold at the
                    vision of a bomb descending into Boston or New York, or the awful calamity
                    involved in the idea of United States sixes going below par!</p>
                <p>Manifest Destiny is, of course, a tempestuously furious patriot, whose
                    speech&#8212;ever under a high pressure of bombast&#8212;is plentifully
                    bedizened with metaphors of his country's stars and stripes, and rapturous
                    anticipations of the rascal‘s “good time coming." Among other satanic felicities
                    he has one, conned out of the devil's prayer-book, called, “Our country, right
                    or wrong!" a stupid fallacy at the best, when we consider that the activity of
                    every nation is bounded by inexorable moral laws as by walls of fire, to pass
                    which is to be withered up and consumed; but especially fallacious from his
                    lips, when we reflect that, practically, he inverts the maxim, and really means,
                    “Our country, wrong or right, “with a decided preference for the former." Spite
                    of all professions, we must doubt the fidelity of that sailor who, in a
                    hurricane, shows his devotion to his ship by assisting her tendency downward;
                    and, on the same principle, we may doubt Mr. Manifest Destiny‘s all-for-glory,
                    nothing-for-money, patriotism.</p>
                <p>The fallacy, indeed, of the fatalistic scheme, as applied to nations, is the same
                    as when applied to individuals; and its doctrine of inevitable tendencies comes
                    from considering mind as a blind force, not as an intelligent, responsible,
                    self-directing energy. <span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="b009" from="#b009" to="#b010"/>A plastic, fluid, impressible national mind, like
                    the American, receives a new impulse and direction for every grand sentiment,
                    every great thought, every heroic act, every honest life, contributed to it; and
                    that philosophy <anchor xml:id="b010"/> which screams out to reasonable
                    citizens, “The tendency of the nation is toward the edge of the bottomless pit,
                        <hi rend="italic">therefore</hi> patriotically assist the movement,” is the
                    insane climax of the <hi rend="italic">non sequitur</hi> in political logic.
                    Why, we can shield ourselves from such a conclusion, with no better reasoning
                    than that employed by the grave-digger in Hamlet, in discussing the question of
                    suicide: “Here lies the water; here stands the man: if the man go to the water
                    and drown himself, it is&#8212;will he, nil he&#8212;he goes; but if the water
                    come to him, and drown him, he drowns not himself: argal, he that is not guilty
                    of his own death, shortens not his own life." We may be sure that no nation,
                    which goes not to the fire, will ever have the tire come to it. leaven is
                    liberal of its blessings and benignities, but it practices a rigid economy in
                    dispensing its smiting curses, and lets loose its reluctant angels of calamity
                    and death only as they are drawn down by the impious prayers of fully and crime
                    i</p>
                <p>If the too exclusive direction of the American mind to industrial production has
                    not been much checked by the two antagonistic extremes of radicalism its
                    money-ocracy has provoked, and for whose excesses it is to a great degree
                    responsible, we must look for a healthier opposition to it in the various
                    classes of moderate dissentients and reformers, who are not so much disgusted
                    with the community as to lose all power of influencing it, and who are steadily
                    infusing into their own and the national character loftier ideas and more
                    liberalizing tastes. Our churches, collegiate institu-<cb/><pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="rut_nhg.00020.jpg" type="verso"/><fw type="pageNum" place="top left">696</fw>
                    <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="smallcaps">HARPER'S NEW MONTHLY
                            MAGAZINE.</hi></fw><milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>tions, and numerous societies established for moral and benevolent ends, are
                    connected with the national mind, and at the same time are inspired by
                    influences apart from it; but still, we must admit that, just in proportion as
                    the nation’s life circulates through them, is their tendency to temporize with
                    Mammon. The Church, for instance, exercises a vast and beneficent influence in
                    spreading moral and religious ideas; but do we not often hear sermons in which
                    industrial prosperity is unconsciously baptized with great pomp of sacred
                    rhetoric P and prayers, in which railroads and manufactories hold a place among
                    Divine favors altogether different from the estimate in which they are held
                    above? Do we, mad as we all are after riches, hear often enough from the pulpit
                    the spirit of those words in which Dean Swift, in his epitaph on the affluent
                    and profligate Colonel Chartres, announces the small esteem of wealth in the
                    eyes of God, from the fact of his thus lavishing it upon the meanest and basest
                    of his creatures?</p>
                <p>Our theology is closer to the public mind, both to act and to be acted upon, than
                    our literature. Indeed, if we take the representative men of those classes whose
                    productions, ethical, poetical, and artistical, we call American literature and
                    art, we shall find that the national life is not so much their inspiration as it
                    is the object they would inspire. Charming and Allston, for instance, have a
                    purified delicacy and refinement of nature, a constant reference to the
                    universal in morals and taste, and a want of ruddy and robust strength,
                    indicating that they have not risen genially out of the national mind, and
                    betraying, in all their words and colors, that surrounding influences were
                    hostile rather than sustaining to their genius. Their works, accordingly, have
                    neither the exclusiveness nor the raciness and gusto characteristic of genius
                    which is national. The same principle applies to our poetical literature, which
                    worships Beauty, but not beautiful America. If you observe the long line of the
                        <span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="b011" from="#b011" to="#b012"/> English poets, Chaucer, <choice>
                        <orig>Shakspeare</orig>
                        <reg>Shakespeare</reg>
                    </choice>, Ben Jonson, Dryden, Pope, Byron, with hardly the exceptions of
                    Spenser and Milton, you will find that, however heaven-high some of them are in
                    elevation, they all rest on the solid base of English character ; idealize,
                    realize, or satirize English history, customs, or scenery, English modes of
                    thought and forms of society, English manners or want of manners, English life
                    and English men&#8212;are full, in short, of English blood. But our most eminent
                    poets&#8212;Dana, Emerson, Bryant, Longfellow, Lowell&#8212;are more or less
                    idealists, from the necessity of their position. Though they may represent the
                    woods and streams of American nature, they commonly avoid the passions and
                    thoughts of American human nature. The “ haunt and main region of their song“ is
                    man rather than men; humanity in its simple elements, rather than complex
                    combinations; and their mission is to stand somewhat apart from the rushing
                    stream of American industrial life, and, assimilating new elements from other
                    literatures, or directly from visible nature, to pour into that stream, as rills
                    into a river, thought, fulness, and melody, and beauty. Their productions being
                    thus <hi rend="italic">contributions</hi>: to the national mind, rather than
                    offsprings of it, are contemplative rather than lyrical, didactic rather than
                    dramatic. And is it not better that it should be so? If our economics were sung
                    as well-as lived; if, instead of “The Humble Bee," and “Thanatopsis," and the
                    “Psalm of Life,” we had “Odes to the Brokers'<anchor xml:id="b012"/><cb/>
                    Board," and ' ‘ Lines on the Sudden Fall of Reading Stock," would we not be
                    giving stimulants where it would be better to give even morphine or chloroform?
                        <span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="b013" from="#b013" to="#b014"/>It is from this fact, that the ideal and romantic are elements of thought to
                    be introduced from abroad into the American mind, that we have not a strictly
                    national literature, and that so many of the clumsy attempts at purely American
                    poetry and romance remind one of the fraternizing Frenchman, who rushed up to a
                    ragged Indian in New Orleans, clasped him to his breast, and joyously exclaimed
                    that he had at last found the true native American&#8212;the real <hi rend="italic">red</hi> republican !<anchor xml:id="b014"/></p>
                <p>Perhaps the fairest and least flattering expression of our whole national life
                    may be found in our politics; for in limited monarchies and in democracies it is
                    in politics that all that there is in the public mind of servility, stupidity,
                    ferocity, and unreasoning prejudice is sure to come glaringly out; and certainly
                    our politics will compare favorably with those of Greece and Rome, of France and
                    England, in respect either to intelligence or morality. In no country is the
                    government more narrowly watched; in no country do large parties, bound together
                    by an interest, more readily fall apart on a principle: and when we consider
                    that, in practical politics, force and passion, not reason and judgment, are
                    predominant&#8212;that men vote with a storm of excitement hurrying them on&#8212;this fact
                    indicates that the minor moralities have to a great extent become instincts with
                    the people. It would be impossible to give here even a scanty view of this
                    political expression of our national mind, with its sectional contests, its
                    struggles of freedom with slavery, its war of abstract philosophies on concrete
                    interests, its impassioned moralities, and no less impassioned immoralities;
                    but, perhaps, a few remarks on three great statesmen, who are marked by
                    unmistakable local and national traits, and who were genuine products of
                    American life, may not be out of place even here. We refer to Webster, Clay, and
                    Calhoun. These, though “ dead, yet speak ;" and we shall allude to them as if
                    they still occupied bodily that position in our politics which they
                    unquestionably occupy mentally. Such men can only die with the movements they
                    originated.</p>
                <p>Of these three eminences of our politics, of late years, Webster may be called
                    the most comprehensive statesman, Clay the most accomplished politician, and
                    Calhoun the nimblest and the most tenacious sectional partisan. Webster, on the
                    first view, seems a kind of Roman-Englishman&#8212;a sort of cross between
                    Cincinnatus and Burke&#8212;but, examined more closely, he is found to be a
                    natural elevation in the progress of American life, a man such as New Hampshire
                    bore him, and such as Winthrop and Standish, Washington and Jay, Hamilton and
                    Madison, had made him; a man who drew the nutriment of character altogether from
                    American influences; and, especially, a man representing the iron of the
                    national character as distinguished from its quicksilver. The principal wealth
                    of New Hampshire is great men and water-power - bug instead of keeping them to
                    herself, she squanders them on Massachusetts, and Webster was one of these free
                    gifts.</p>
                <p>If we compare Webster with Calhoun, we shall find in both the same firm mental
                    grasp of principles, the same oversight of the means of popularity, and the same
                    ungraceful and almost sullen self-assertion, at periods when policy would have
                        dic-<pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="rut_nhg.00021.jpg" type="recto"/><fw type="pageNum" place="top right">697</fw>
                    <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="smallcaps">EDITOR'S
                        TALBLE.</hi></fw><milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>tated a
                    more facile accommodativeness. Their intellects, though both in some degree
                    entangled by local interests and opinions, have inherent differences, visible at
                    a glance. Webster’s mind has more massiveness than Calhoun’s, is richer in
                    culture and variety of faculty, and is gifted with a wider sweep of
                    argumentation; but it is not so completely compacted with character, and has,
                    accordingly, less inflexible and untiring persistence toward an object. Both are
                    comparatively unimpressible, but Webster's understanding recognizes and includes
                    facts which his imagination may refuse to assimilate; while Calhoun arrogantly
                    ignores every thing which contradicts his favorite opinions, and would be a
                    great reasoner did he not so often take paradoxes for his premises. The mind of
                    Webster, weighty, solid, and capacious, looks before and after; by its insight
                    reads principles in events, by its foresight reads events in principles; and,
                    arching gloriously over all the phenomena of a widely-complex subject of
                    contemplation, views things, not singly, but in their multitudinous relations;
                    yet the very comprehension of his vision makes him somewhat timid, and his
                    moderation, accordingly, lacks the crowning grace of moral audacity. Calhoun has
                    audacity, but lacks comprehensiveness.</p>
                <p>As Webster's mind, from its enlargement of view, has an instinctive intellectual
                    conscientiousness, the processes of his reasoning are principally inductive,
                    rising from facts to principles; while Calhoun's are principally deductive,
                    descending from principles to facts. Now deduction is doubtless sublime exercise
                    of logical genius, provided the principle be reached&#8212;as it is reached by
                    Webster, when he uses the process&#8212;by induction; for it gives the mind
                    power to divine the future, and converts prophecy into a science. Thus, from the
                    deductive law of gravitation we can predict the appearance of stellar phenomena
                    thousands of years hence. Edmund Burke is the greatest of European statesmen, in
                    virtue of his discovery and application of deductive laws applicable to society
                    and government. But the mischief of Calhoun‘s deductive method is, that, by
                    nature or position, his understanding is controlled by his will; and,
                    consequently, his principles are often arbitrarily or capriciously chosen, do
                    not rise out of the nature of things, but out of the nature of Mr. Calhoun; and
                    therefore it is frequently true of him, what Macaulay untruly declares of Burke,
                    that “he chooses his position like a fanatic, and defends it like a
                    philosopher"&#8212;as Clay chooses his like a tactician, and defends it like a
                    fanatic.</p>
                <p>If we carefully study the speeches of Webster and Calhoun, in one of those great
                    Congressional battles where they were fairly pitted against each other, we shall
                    find that Webster’s mind darts beneath the smooth and rapid stream of his
                    opponent‘s deductive argument at a certain point&#8212;fastens fatally on some
                    phrase, or fact, or admission, in which the fallacy lurks&#8212;and then devotes
                    his reply to a searching analysis and logical overthrow of that, without heeding
                    the rest. Calhoun, of course, has the ready rejoinder that the thing demolished
                    is twisted out of its relations; and then, with admirable control of his face,
                    proceeds to dip into Webster’s inductive argument, to extract some fact or
                    principle which is indissolubly related to what goes before and comes after, and
                    thus really misrepresents the reasoning he seemingly answers. To overthrow
                    Calhoun you have,<cb/> like Napoleon at Wagram, only to direct a tremendous blow
                    at the centre; to overthrow Webster, like Napoleon at Borodino, the whole line
                    must be routed.</p>
                <p><span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="b015" from="#b015" to="#b016"/>In
                    the style of the two men we have, perhaps, the best expression of their
                    character ; for style, it has been well said, “ is the measure of power&#8212;as
                    the waves of the sea answer to the winds that call them up.” Webster's style
                    varies with the moods of his mind&#8212;short, crisp, biting, in sarcasm;<anchor xml:id="b016"/><note xml:id="n006" target="b015" type="authorial" place="right" anchored="true"><handShift new="#h2"/>style</note> luminous
                    and even in statement; rigid, condensed, massive in argumentation; lofty and
                    resounding in feeling; fierce, hot, direct, overwhelming, in passion. Calhoun's
                    has the uniform vigor and clear precision of a spoken essay.</p>
                <p>Clay&#8212;the love of American economics, as Webster was the pride&#8212;had all
                    those captivating personal qualities which attract men's admiration, at the same
                    time that they enforce their respect; and was especially gifted with that
                    flexibility&#8212;that prompt, intuitive, heart-winning grace&#8212;which his
                    great contemporaries lacked. The secret of his influence must not be sought in
                    his printed speeches. We never go to them, as we go to Webster’s and Calhoun's,
                    for political philosophy and vehement logic. But if Webster as an orator was
                    inductive, and convinced the reason, and Calhoun deductive, and dazzled the
                    reason, Clay was most assuredly seductive, and carried the votes. The nature of
                    Clay, without being deficient in force, was plastic and fluid, readily
                    accommodating itself to the moment's exigency, and more solicitous to comprehend
                    all the elements of party power than all the elements of political thought. His
                    faculties and passions seem all to have united in one power of personal
                    impressiveness, and that personality once penetrated a whole party, bound
                    together discordant interests and antipathies, made itself felt as inspiration
                    equally in Maine and Louisiana, concentrated in itself the enthusiasm of sense
                    for principles, and of sensibility for men; and these, the qualities of a
                    powerful political leader, who makes all the demagogues work for him, without
                    being himself a demagogue, indicated his possession of something, at least, of
                    that <q><p>"Mystery of commanding; That birth-hour gift, that art-Napoleon, Of
                            winning, fettering, wielding, moulding, bonding The hearts of millions,
                            till they move as one."</p></q></p>
                <p>But the fact that Clay never reached the object of his ambition, proves that he
                    was not a perfect specimen of the kind of character to which he belonged; and
                    his personality&#8212;swift, fusing, potent as it was&#8212;alert, compromising,
                    supple as it was&#8212;still was not under thoroughly wise direction ; and a
                    sense of honor morbidly quick, and a resentment of slight nervously egotistic,
                    sometimes urged our most accomplished politician into impolitic acts, which
                    leveled the labors of years.</p>
                <p>Perhaps the best test even of a man‘s intellect is the way he demeans himself
                    when he is enraged; and in this Webster was pre-eminent above all orators, while
                    Calhoun was apt to lose his balance, and become petty and passionate, and Clay
                    to exhibit a kind of glorious recklessness. Most of the faults of Webster
                    proceeded from his comprehension of understanding not being ever accompanied by
                    a. corresponding impetus from sentiment and character; and some of his orations
                    are therefore unimpassioned statements and arguments, which, however much they
                    claim our assent as logicians, do not stir, and thrill, and move us as men. Com-
                        <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="rut_nhg.00022.jpg" type="verso"/>
                    <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">698</fw>
                    <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="smallcaps">HARPER'S NEW MONTHLY
                            MAGAZINE.</hi></fw>
                    <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/> -ing from but one portion of
                    his own nature, they touch only one portion of the nature of others, and wield
                    no dominion over the will. Such was his celebrated speech on the Slavery
                    question, which so many found difficult to answer, and impossible to accept. Not
                    so was it when passion and sentiment penetrated his understanding; for, in
                    Webster, passion was a fire which fused intellect and character into one
                    tremendous personal force, and then burst out that resistless eloquence in which
                    words have the might and meaning of things&#8212;that true mental electricity,
                    not seen in dazzling, zigzag flashes&#8212;not heard in a grand, reverberating
                    peal <hi rend="italic">over</hi> the head&#8212;but, mingling the qualities of
                    light and sound, the blue bright flame startles and stings the eye at the moment
                    the sharp crash pierces and stuns the ear. No brow smitten by that bolt, though
                    the brow of a Titan, could ever afterward lift itself above the crowd without
                    being marked by its enduring scar; and it was well that a great, and not easily
                    moved nature, abundantly tried by all that frets and teases the temper, should
                    thus have borne within himself such a terrible instrument of avenging justice,
                    when meanness presumed too far on the moderation of that large intellect, when
                    insolence goaded too sharply that sullen fortitude!</p>

                <p>The three great statesmen to which we have referred, taken together, cover three
                    all-important elements in every powerful national mind&#8212;resistance,
                    persistence, and impressibility ; and each, by representing at the same time
                    some engrossing industrial interest, indicates that practical direction of the
                    national energies to which we have all along referred. In this region of
                    industry the nation has been grandly creative; and by establishing the maxim
                    that the production of wealth is a matter secondary to its distribution, it
                    promises to be as grandly beneficent. But, perhaps, in the art and science of
                    government it has been more creative and more beneficent than in the province of
                    industry. T be elements of order and radicalism it embosoms are in a healthy
                    rather than destructive conflict, so that we may hope that even the problem of
                    Slavery will be settled without any widespread ruin and devastation. The
                    mischief of radicalism in other countries is, that it commences reformation by
                    abjuring law; accordingly, it opposes political power on the principles of
                    anarchy, and wields it on the principles of despotism. Here the toughest problem
                    in the science of government has been practically solved, by the expedient of
                    legalizing resistance; and thus, by providing legal inlets and outlets for
                    insurrection and revolution, we reap the benefits of rebellion, and avoid its
                    appalling evils. A nation which has done this can afford to bear some taunts on
                    its vices and defects, especially as its sensitive vanity impels it to
                    appropriate the truth contained in every sarcasm under which it winces.</p>

                <p>It now remains to ask how a national mind like the American, with its powers
                    generally directed by its sentiments to commerce, industrial production, law,
                    and politics&#8212;which are the most lucrative occupations&#8212;and but relatively
                    directed to reforms&#8212;which are the most unprofitable&#8212;how it appears
                    when tested by those virtues which are the conditions of a nation's durable
                    strength? The question is not one of particulars, because, in every social
                    system, no matter how for advanced in humans culture, there will always be
                    individuals and small classes representing the vices of every grade<cb/> of
                    civilization which history or tradition has recorded, from cannibals all the way
                    down to dandies life have our share of New Zealand and our share of Almacks; but
                    in viewing a national mind we must fasten on the strongest elements and the
                    average humanity. <span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="b017" from="#b017" to="#b018"/>Looked at from this liberal point, American life
                    would bear comparatively well the tests of prudence, moderation, and
                    benevolence; a little less confidently those of veracity, steadfastness, and
                    justice; and considerably less those of beauty, heroism, and
                        self-devotion.<anchor xml:id="b018"/><note xml:id="n007" target="b017" type="authorial" place="right" anchored="true">☜</note></p>

                <p>But it is not so much in the present as in the future that we have the grandest
                    vision of the American mind. We have seen that its organic substance, as
                    distinguished from the unassimilated elements in contact or conflict with it, is
                    solidly and productively practical ; and as it is a sleepless energy, resisting,
                    persisting, and impressible, <span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="b019" from="#b019" to="#b020"/>we may hope that it will transmute into itself the
                    best life of other national minds, without having its individuality overwhelmed;
                    that it will be strong and beautiful with their virtues and accomplishments,
                    without being weak with their vices and limitations; and that, continually
                    enriched by new and various mental life, it will result in being a comprehensive
                    national mind, harmoniously combining characteristics caught from all
                    nations&#8212;so that Greece might in it recognize beauty, and Rome will, and
                    Germany earnestness, and Italy art, and France vivacity, and Ireland impulse,
                    and England tenacity. It is in this contemplation of America as a conquering
                    Mind that we should most delight&#8212;a mind worthy of the broad continent it
                    is to overv-arch&#8212;a mind too sound at the core for ignorance to stupefy, or
                    avarice to harden, or lust of power to consume&#8212;a mind full in the line of
                    the historical progress of the race, holding wide relations with all communities
                    and all times, listening to every word of cheer or warning muttered from dead or
                    thundered from living lips, and moving down the solemn pathway of the ages, an
                    image of just, intelligent, beneficent Power!<anchor xml:id="b020"/></p>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
            </div1>

            <div1>
                <head type="main-authorial">Editor's Easy Chair.</head>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">WE</hi> in America had scarcely buried our foremost
                    practical statesman, England had barely turned from the grave of her brilliant
                    wit and satirist, when the note of national bereavement was caught up and
                    prolonged in the universal sorrow with which the French people followed to his
                    last home the most popular of poets. The death of Béranger revives all the
                    souvenirs of all the changing fortunes of France during its last fourscore years
                    of change. He was one of the rarest products of that strange convulsive epoch so
                    prodigal of great geniuses. The metaphorical sea of Time, like the veritable
                    ocean on which we gaze from Newport or Nahant, often sends to the shore, with
                    its burden of wreck and destruction, some gem of its own most fanciful creation.
                    The same dismal wave which broke over France in the horrors of Revolution and
                    the Reign of Terror, bore into being this bright child of song, with all his
                    overflowing wit and humor and genial human sympathies, like a gleam of sunlight
                    on the crest of some storm-lashed breaker just poised for the final desolating
                    sweep. <span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="b021" from="#b021" to="#b022"/>Nature, in Béranger, epitomized the French character in its sunniest
                    type, and avenged herself for such grand deformities as Danton, Robespierre, and
                    their colossal colleagues.<anchor xml:id="b022"/> He was revolutionary and democratic by instinct; but
                    he had no thirst for blood or plunder,</p>
                <note xml:id="n008" target="n007" type="authorial" place="bottom right" anchored="true"><handShift new="#h2"/>Beranger</note>
            </div1>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>