<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="rut.00014">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">"On Style"</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
                <author xml:id="unk">Unknown</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="jyc">Jonathan Y. Cheng</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>University of Texas at Austin</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>rut.00014</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>kprice@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Ed-Folsom@uiowa.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>bbarney2@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability><p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain exceptions, public domain works may be freely copied or used in the creation of derivative works without permission, or authorization, of the former copyright owners.</p><p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and is governed by a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0).</p><p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Unknown</author>
                    <title>"On Style"</title>
                    <!--<idno type="callno"></idno>-->
                    <date cert="high" when="1845-10">Oct 1845</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="rut">Special Collections and University Archives, Rutgers University
                        Libraries, Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey </orgName>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from our digital image of original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="h1" scribeRef="#unk" medium="type"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h2" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h3" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#jyc" when="2014-10-24">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="marginalia">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="rut_nhg.00007.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="top"><handShift new="#h2"/>Style. J.D.W.</note>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="top right"><handShift new="#h2"/>3</note>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h3" place="top left"><handShift new="#h3"/>+</note>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h3" place="top right"><handShift new="#h3"/>4)</note>
            <fw type="date" place="top left">1845.]</fw>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">357</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">The River.</hi></fw>
            <delSpan rend="hashmark" spanTo="#ds001" hand="#h2"/>
            <div1>
                <p><handShift new="#h1"/>with agitation and vehemence. I was informed that there was
                    no such city, town or village in the county! My hair fairly rose on end, like
                    "quills upon the fretful porcupine." I perused my deed of conveyance again and
                    again. There it was plainly, in black and white, "the city of
                    Franklin"&#8212;"lots 500 and 501 on National Avenue." I traversed the county in
                    all directions, wearied every traveler with my inquiries, disturbed the inmates
                    of every log hut, and got myself kicked out of one or two for my impetuosity of
                    manner. It was labor lost. In the language of that region, I was "done
                    for"&#8212;"diddled." Civic honors!&#8212;rent roll!&#8212;blocks of buildings!
                    Alas! My dreams has fled&#8212;so had my money. My obliging friend of the
                    steamboat was a man of imagination, as well as of profound morality; the city
                    existed <hi rend="italic">on his map</hi> "The scoundrel!" said<cb/> I, "let me
                    catch him again!"&#8212;But instead of my catching him he had evidently caught
                    me&#8212;something of a difference as I found. One thing I did catch&#8212;the
                    fever-and-ague. I took it at a log-house, in the vicinity of a slight
                    swamp"&#8212;as the owner of the shantee called a three mile morass&#8212;and
                    had it a trifle over nine weeks. The ghost of my father wouldn't have known
                    me!</p>
                <p>this was my <hi rend="italic">first speculation</hi>, It may be imagined in what
                    mood I traveled after this adventure, but it cannot well be imagined why, after
                    this lesson, I continued the pleasing game of getting rich without labor. The
                    result of my gains as a speculator may be expressed by a cipher, or any number
                    of them together, as $0,000, etc. I returned "a sadder, but a wiser man," the
                    owner of eighty acres of wild land, and in debt eleven thousand dollars!</p>
                <anchor xml:id="ds001"/>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>

                <lg>
                    <head type="main-authorial" rend="smallcaps"><handShift new="#h1"/><handShift new="#h1"/>THE RIVER.</head>
                    <head type="sub"><hi rend="smallcaps">FROM THE SWEDISH OF TEGNER.</hi></head>
                    <lg type="linegroup">
                        <l>Fast by the River's trickling source I sit</l>
                        <l>And view the new-born offspring of the skies;</l>
                        <l>Cradled on naked fell, a nursling yet,</l>
                        <l>Fed by his mother-cloud's soft breast, he lies.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="linegroup">
                        <l>But lo! the heaven-born streamlet swelling flows,</l>
                        <l>Dreaming e'en now of fame, the woods adown;</l>
                        <l>And, as his bosom heaves with longing throes,</l>
                        <l>His wavelets rock the mirrored sun and moon/</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="linegroup">
                        <l>And now he scorns beneath the first to creep,</l>
                        <l>Or hemmed by narrow mountain walls to flow,</l>
                        <l>But madly tumbles down the headlong steep,</l>
                        <l>And foams along the pebbly dell below.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="linegroup">
                        <l>"Come on! come on!" he every brookling hails,</l>
                        <l>"Here sands absorb, and suns exhaust, your force;</l>
                        <l>Ye brothers come! through smiling fields and vales,</l>
                        <l>I lead you down to our primeval source."</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="linegroup">
                        <l>Now to the plains in triumph he descends,</l>
                        <l>With dark blue train and state that homage claim;</l>
                        <l>Parched fields his breath revives as on he bends</l>
                        <l>His course, baptizing nations with his name.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="linegroup">
                        <l>And bards, in strains divine, his praises sing,</l>
                        <l>Tall ships are on his bosom borne away,</l>
                        <l>Proud cities court him, flowery meadows cling</l>
                        <l>Around his knees, and sue him to delay.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg type="linegroup">
                        <l>But they detain him not; with ceaseless haste</l>
                        <l>Fair fields and gilded towns he hurries by,</l>
                        <l>Nor slacks his tide impetuous, till at last</l>
                        <l>He on his father's bosom falls&#8212;to die!</l>
                    </lg>
                </lg>
            </div1>

            <fw type="footnote" place="bottom left">Vol II.&#8212;NO. IV.</fw>
            <fw type="footenote" place="bottom">25</fw>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="rut_nhg.00008.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="top"><handShift new="#h3"/>by J D. Whelpley (I
                    think)<handShift new="#h1"/></note>
            <fw type="date" place="top right">[Oct.,</fw>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">358</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">On Style.</hi></fw>
            <div1>
                <head type="main-authorial" rend="smallcaps"><handShift new="#h1"/>ON STYLE</head>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">THERE</hi> is a something in the compositions of a good
                    writer, that affects us more sensibly than either his manner of his style; and
                    which, in absence of a better word, may be named his <hi rend="italic">character:</hi> signifying, that as the taste of the writer appears in the
                        <hi rend="italic">style</hi>, and his genius in the <hi rend="italic">manner</hi>, so his natural disposition, as a man, is discovered in the <hi rend="italic">character</hi> of his writings. Since there is a character of
                    nations, as well as of individuals, this will appear in the prevalancy of a
                    certain spirit among a number of contemporary writers of the same nation.</p>
                <p><span rend="doubleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="dl001" from="#dl001" to="#dl002"/>It may be advanced without danger of contradiction, that <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">the value of an author to the world, is chiefly in the
                        "character" of what he says,</hi>&#8212;using that word in the sense just
                    now adopted for it;&#8212;and this is evident, upon the reflection that <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">that a great writer loses nothing essential by
                        translation;</hi><anchor xml:id="dl002"/> and that style and manner are
                    almost inappreciable by another age and nation. However much our taste and fancy
                    may be gratified by a perfect understanding of our own writers, what is truly
                    valuable in them may be as perfectly expressed in a coarser dialect. If we may
                    judge by the kind of works that have come down to us from antiquity, <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">the duration of a work, and the fame of an
                        author, depend almost exclusively upon the elevation of his sentiments</hi>;
                    and those elegances for which he is admired, are either such as flow directly
                    from this source, or they are artificial advantages proper to his language and
                    age, and of little moment to posterity</p>
                <p><note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="left"><handShift new="#h2"/>☞</note><handShift new="#h1"/><span rend="doubleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="dl003" from="#dl003" to="#dl004"/>Longinus, a critic of
                    exalted genius, and who has himself taken rank among the best writers, advises
                    that <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">an author who means to out-last his
                        century, shall imagine what judgement Homer or Plato would give upon his
                        work:</hi> but we can hardly think of these heroes in authorship, as
                    curiously commenting on the style or manner of a writer ; but rather fancy them
                        <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">weighing the substance of what he says, and
                        sounding the depth of his sentiment&#8212;for those were the points that
                        seem most to have occupied them in the composition of their own
                            works.<anchor xml:id="dl004"/></hi></p>
                <p>The English writer may place himself under as wise advisers, in the judgements of
                    the masters of his own tongue ; though none of these arrived ever at that
                    purity<cb/> and singleness, which made the older Greeks the unapproachable
                    models of <hi rend="italic">style</hi>. A generous emulation of antiquity has
                    kept alive the spirit of our literature; not to the exclusion of that free
                    manner and indulgence of fancy, which is proper to the moderns, nor to the
                    extinction or neglect of our proper idiom ; but by drawing attention continually
                    to the better parts of humanity, and favoring the indulgence of manly and
                    generous sentiments.</p>
                <p>No better example can be chosen of this kind of imitation, than appears in the
                    philosophical writings of Lord Bacon; wherein he emulates the design of Socrates
                    and his pupils, who bent their efforts to increase human happiness, not only by
                    a present entertainment, but by turning all speculation into the channels of
                    economy and morals. The prose style of English being at its formation when the
                    Lord Chancellor composed his treatises, a great deal of another kind of
                    imitation was prevalent. Not only the sentiments, but the idiom and manner of
                    Greek writers was often roughly adopted, and mingled in a blind confusion with
                    the Gothic prejudice and imagery of that age. In a history, composed by him, of
                    Henry Seventh, Lord Bacon reproduces the manner, but not the spirit of
                    Thucydides, rolling trains of polity and eulogy through periods of perilous
                    weight and involution : but the spirit of the work is altogether English and
                    monarchic.</p>
                <p>Perhaps there are no writings in the world, if we except Homer's, where character
                    appears with such a power and constancy as in <choice>
                        <orig>Shakspeare</orig>
                        <reg>Shakespeare</reg>
                    </choice>; yet in him, even, there is a great deal that is harsh and
                    displeasing. Now if it could be shown that his excellence is either
                    characteristic, or in emulation of the ancients, but that all his grossness and
                    extravagancy is either imitated from others, or belonged to the conversation of
                    his age, a perfect argument would have been found for this nobler kind of
                    imitation, and as perfect a caution against the inferior sort. Who can
                    contemplate, without delight, the idea of a writer who should unite classic
                    purity with English spirit and variety;&#8212;the splendid and fortunate
                    conjunction of the two master spirits of genius, the English and the Greek?</p>
                <p>We are the most fortunate people in <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="rut_nhg.00009.jpg" type="recto"/>
                    <fw type="date" place="top left">1845.]</fw>
                    <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">359</fw>
                    <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">On Style.</hi></fw> the world in
                    respect of examples; for, beside our own writers, from the age of Chaucer to
                    that of Addison, and many great instances since, we have possession of the
                    oldest and wisest of all books; and with a little diligence, can arrive at all
                    that is excellent of the Greeks and Romans. At this banquet of knowledge there
                    is so endless a profusion, and so exquisite a variety, an hundred lives could
                    not utterly exhaust it. It is a special happiness that no man need jostle or
                    rival his neighbor; but each, selecting for himself, may make a sweet of
                    peculiar flavor.</p>
                <p><span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="dl005" from="#dl005" to="#dl006"/>The great variety of style and manner to be found in English writing, offering
                    such a diversity of models, seems to make it impossible that the language should
                    ever attain a classic purity, or the manner of good writing be reduced to any
                    particular standard.<anchor xml:id="dl006"/>The Greeks had an advantage which no
                    modern nation possesses, of employing few foreign phrases, and of using no
                    compounded words whose meaning did not appear in the composition. But because
                    our language is taken partly from the Latin and Greek, its compounds of those
                    sources are loosely employed, without regard to their exact meaning : so that
                    none write or speak correctly but such as know the radical words of these,
                    beside those of their own tongue. Long and sounding words make the strongest
                    impression upon the ear, and are more easily employed than phrases of several
                    monosyllables. A feeble writer may hide the weakness of his meaning under a
                    crowd of sounding terminations, huddled together without attention to their
                    proper use: and this accident is alone sufficient to account for the difference
                    between good writing and good conversation in English. <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="dl007" from="#dl007" to="#dl008"/>A Greek who knew the exact meaning of a word at first hearing, because of his
                    familiarity with its radicals, might speak as perfectly as he wrote; and if he
                    used long words, his audience entered easily into his meaning. But a writer of
                    English must refrain from any but the simplest expressions, or his hearers are
                    as little likely to understand, as he is to speak, with exactness&#8212;a
                    serious hindrance to the perfection of our tongue, and one which it seems unable
                    ever to overcome.<anchor xml:id="dl008"/></p>
                <p>But from this apparent misfortune, a very positive advantage may be gathered. An
                    author who is pedantically or technically inclined, can make no popular display
                    with subtleties or false learning, and <cb/> must adhere closely to the
                    commonest notions and expressions; at the same time that an infinite variety of
                    phrase lies always within reach.</p>
                <p>Those writers of modern times who trusted solely to the excellence of their
                    sentiments, have preferred the popular phrase; so that all the best parts of
                    modern literature are in a dialect that all understand. But where the desire of
                    popularity prevails over the pride of learning, there may be a disposition to
                    debase a language, and fill it with barbarisms, which as certainly obscure the
                    sense as the most learned affectations; and with the greater disadvantage of
                    being forgotten in the next generation.</p>
                <p>Simplicity of style, and naturalness of manner, leave the reader free to receive
                    what is intrinsically good; so that in writing and speaking, as in manners, the
                    chief excellence seems to lie in the avoidance of every thing irrelevant or
                    superfluous, that every purer excellence, of thought or sentiment, may appear in
                    its natural light. Ingenuity and order must indeed be everywhere present, in a
                    work of entertainment; but flashes of character, at important moments, astonish
                    and take possession of the soul. In the simple words,</p>
                <l>"Wisdom is justified of her children,"</l>
                <p>we discover an exhaustless depth: all that is grand and imperishable in human
                    character appears in it. Such sayings have the miraculous power to bring a
                    century of experience within the compass of an instant. <span rend="doubleLine-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="dl009" from="#dl009" to="#dl010"/><hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">Since all that is sublime and the
                        sentiment of immortality, the grandeur of a composition increases, as it
                        draws nearer to the heights of contemplation.</hi><anchor xml:id="dl010"/>
                    <span rend="doubleLine-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="dl011" from="#dl011" to="#dl012"/>Works of character stand through all ages, not so much as
                    monuments to their authors, (for they seem rather to be the product of an age
                    than of a man,) as like mountains emulating the heavens, and sending down
                    fertilizing streams <anchor xml:id="dl012"/></p>
                <p>And yet, even in inspiration, there is logic; and a reason is concealed in every
                    mystery. What is so well done, must have been done deliberately. <span rend="doubleLine-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="dl013" from="#dl013" to="#dl014"/>"Nothing," says Longinus, "can be truly great, that is the result of
                    accident." The noblest works discover as much skill as vigor.<anchor xml:id="dl014"/><note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="right"><handShift new="#h2"/>☜</note><handShift new="#h1"/>
                    <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="dl015" from="#dl015" to="#dl016"/>If nature has given genius, it is a proof of wisdom to use it
                    with discretion. <anchor xml:id="dl016"/></p>
                <p>Nor will any reader be satisfied with images or thoughts, be they never so
                    admirable in themselves, unless they are <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="rut_nhg.00010.jpg" type="verso"/>
                    <fw type="date" place="top right">[Oct.,</fw>
                    <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">360</fw>
                    <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">On Style.</hi></fw> naturally
                    combined, and make an impression as a whole. Many writers, of inferior genius,
                    have secured a great popularity by the art of making a clear and strong
                    impression of some trivial matter; having such a regard for the reader's esteem
                    as to obtrude nothing upon him that is inappropriate, or fanciful. Those
                    licenses, as they are called, of poetry, seem not originally to have been the
                    freedoms of a drunken fancy, but strokes of judgment, that an idea or image may
                    reach us unimpeded by an unnecessary formality. There is a pleasure in congruity
                    alone, which reconciles us to an object that is unnatural in itself; and a
                    cultivated taste endures the marvelous only when it is consistent, or has a
                    meaning. Homer and <choice>
                        <orig>Shakspeare</orig>
                        <reg>Shakespeare</reg>
                    </choice>, though full of extravagances when compared with nature, yet make one
                    extravagance arise so naturally out of another, they satisfy the most exquisite
                    propriety.</p>
                <p><span rend="doubleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="dl017" from="#dl017" to="#dl018"/> If then there be any universal principle of art, it must be, that every
                    member of a composition agree in its intent and figure with some other member,
                    as well as with the whole; <anchor xml:id="dl018"/> just as, in architecture,
                    the parts and ornaments of the column repeat and illustrate those of the
                    entablature, and these again, those of the whole building; or better still, as,
                    to a practiced eye, each member of a human body seems to agree with and suggest
                    the whole. And this comparison will perfectly illustrate what is intended by the
                        <hi rend="italic">character</hi> to be discovered in a composition; for as
                    the form and proportion of the body harmonizes with the characteristics of the
                    mind which inspires it, so will every least member of a well composed work agree
                    with the idea that suggested and governs it. Human bodies discover an
                    inexhaustible variety of beauty, correspondent with as many shade of character;
                    works of artists and writers vary as remarkably with the disposition of their
                    authors. When the ornaments of a style are <hi rend="italic">added</hi> or
                    affixed to the subject matter, instead of growing out of it by suggestion of
                    fancy, the effect is like that of ornaments fixed upon a wooden mansion, without
                    regard to any real or apparent use. But if there be an art of adornment, it is
                    at least as critical as it is suggestive and rejects far more than it proposes.
                        <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="dl019" from="#dl019" to="#dl020"/> A poem or a picture is sometimes composed of exquisitely
                    finished parts, so pleasing in themselves that nothing prevents their author's
                    immortality of fame, but a want of unity or singleness of effect.<anchor xml:id="dl020"/> Even in the very <cb/> best works incongruities appear
                    which mar our pleasure. But the kind of consistency, whose want most effectually
                    prevents the reputation of a work, appears not so much in disregard of
                    probability as in violation of the spirit. Could we, for example, imagine Hamlet
                    indulging in vivacious gaiety, or Tom Jones moralizing in the manner of
                    Allworthy, we might think the author either had some design on our penetration,
                    or else had forgot himself. This kind of inconsistency appears in those popular <choice>
                        <orig>melo-dramas</orig>
                        <reg>melodramas</reg>
                    </choice>, where the hero, a person designedly painted as the victim of every
                    impulse, is made the mouthpiece of exalted and humane sentiments. Such pieces
                    may be very agreeable in the representation, but bear no inspection as wholes,
                    and are perishable accordingly. <span rend="doubleLine-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="dl021" from="#dl021" to="#dl022"/> A writer whose single design
                    appears clearly in all he says, may violate every other rule, and yet commands
                    entire respect: it seems to be enough that he discovers character and a purpose.
                        <anchor xml:id="dl022"/></p>
                <p>So essential is exaltation of sentiment in works of art, a landscape, even, gives
                    no pleasure to the taste, unless, in some manner, this quality is discovered in
                    it. Skilful painters, perceiving this necessity, avoid too close an imitation of
                    nature, and by certain extraordinary combinations produce impressions of
                    life=likeness in inanimate things, as though a spirit moved them. Animals are
                    represented expressing qualities that appear only in human beings, and images of
                    men seem inspired with a divine soul.</p>
                <p>Such works leave no impression of their detail, but are recollected as wholes, as
                    we remember a person. When, on the other hand, this quality is absent, the parts
                    make a deep impression as it happens with fanciful authors who say quotable
                    things, full of point and sense, but whose works are rather a magazine, than an
                    armament of wit.</p>
                <p>It is frequently observed that figures in some excellent landscapes serve only to
                    divert attention, though unworthy of notice in themselves; and contrariwise, an
                    indifferent landscape is often so managed as to obscure an admirable figure: the
                    character of the two discovering no congruity. The same may be observed in some
                    works of fiction, which their author intended should have a moral use; and to
                    that end, has given his proverbs and maxims in a dish by themselves; but a more
                    ingenious writer so blends hi moral with the story, it has the effect, like a
                    thread of gold, of strengthening and enli- <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="rut_nhg.00011.jpg" type="recto"/>
                    <fw type="date" place="top left">1845.]</fw>
                    <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">361</fw>
                    <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">On Style.</hi></fw> vening the
                    whole tissue. In Homer and Chaucer, the narrative invariably suggests the moral;
                    but in many celebrated modern works there is either no moral at all, (and
                    therefore no dignity,) or the author goes out of his way to lug one in. The most
                    trifling ornament of an ancient cathedral has a propriety, and would serve no
                    other design: but a skilless architect destroys the character of his fabric by
                    efforts to gratify the eye. the outside of a perfect mansion agrees with the
                    interior, and even suggests it. Every interspace in the walls tells of something
                    correspondent within&#8212;pilasters and buttresses remind of arches and party
                    walls&#8212;casements and fire-places typify the facade. But these
                    correspondences please the fancy only; and unless a design of solid use be
                    apparent in the whole, no one respects it.</p>
                <p>That the presence of a character is essential, appears in the transiency of even
                    the most admirable poems, where the whole excellence lies in the ingenious
                    expression of a passion, as of love or grief, repeated through a variety of
                    changes. Very little of this kind of writing, however exquisite in its kind,
                    outlasts the century in which it was composed. Artificial sentiments,
                    originating in the philosophy of the age or sect, or in social differences,
                    suffer the same fate. Nothing is found to be more dangerous to an esteem for a
                    writer, than the discovery in him of a respect for the cliques and opinions of
                    his day; as nothing is likelier to ensure it, than perceiving in him a
                    magnanimity which regards no difference or deficiency, either of intellect or
                    fortune. Indeed the critic himself as greatest need of such magnanimity to
                    refrain from insulting the want of it in his author.</p>
                <p>Authors who have outlived their century have been at great pains to qualify
                    everything with a meaning. Excesses of pure wit, melody, or sentiment, weary
                    upon the second reading, and are forgotten; but in the best works, this first
                    kind of pleasure is succeeded by another that is permanent; and what was enjoyed
                    at first for its agreeable impression, delights much more for the depth and
                    completeness of its meaning. There is an inexpressionable satisfaction to be
                    enjoyed in the consistency and good sense of a great writer. Whatever <choice>
                        <orig>Shakspeare</orig>
                        <reg>Shakespeare</reg>
                    </choice> says, in his best moods, though not elegant or witty in itself, has a
                    propriety in illustration of his moral, which makes it excellent and valuable;
                    but when such passages are quoted apart, they seem dwindled into mere <cb/>
                    conceits. Since there is a pleasure of discord and contrast, as well as of
                    harmony and propriety, we are wearied with a continual appearance of the same
                    kind of beauty or feeling. A single passion drawn out through a long poem,
                    without its natural contrasts, wearies and soon disgusts; for we feel that in
                    nature every sentiment, even the highest, has its proper cause and beginning,
                    and rises by opposition to its climax, and falls to the its ending, as naturally
                    as a piece of music. There is but little pleasure in a string of pearls, or a
                    dinner of sweets served in courses; or in a human figure divested of its natural
                    irregularities; <span rend="doubleLine-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="dl023" from="#dl023" to="#dl024"/>and the greatest masters of design, as well as of
                    poetry and music, mingle sharp turns and discords with their correspondent
                        melodies.<anchor xml:id="dl024"/>
                    <span rend="doubleLine-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="dl025" from="#dl025" to="#dl026"/> If there be a proof that a character or ruling principle is
                    the source of all that is excellent in art, it is in this necessity of a mixture
                    of rough and smooth; <anchor xml:id="dl026"/> for to present a plain truism
                    mystically, the character, or moral nature, rules over jarring elements, and
                    acts in the office of a mediator between good and ill. <span rend="doubleLine-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="dl027" from="#dl027" to="#dl028"/> In nature nothing is more obvious than the mixture of contrasts and discords;
                    signified in mythology by the endless conflict of good and evil angels.<anchor xml:id="dl028"/> When the poets have chosen to represent a paradise they
                    have invariably placed a hell near it, as though one could not be imagined but
                    in contrast with the other. Earthly paradises are found in islands dangerous of
                    access, or in a valley battlemented with snowy summits. Danger is the gate of
                    delight; pain the portal, or the postern, of pleasure. <span rend="doubleLine-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="dl029" from="#dl029" to="#dl030"/> Night precedes and follows day; for every light there is a shade, for every
                    sweet a bitter; even melody itself is a succession of discords and harmonies,
                    and a soft surface a field of minute asperities. <anchor xml:id="dl030"/></p>
                <p>Longinus makes exception in favor of eloquence, that it is given by nature, while
                    all other arts are imitative and acquired. He argues that the sublime of
                    eloquence, arising from natural character, can have nothing of artifice, and
                    that it prevails by force and not by skill. Quintilian, on the contrary,
                    inclining more to the use of rhetoric, advises the employment of every artifice,
                    and trusts less to nature. These two opinions, which neither of their authors
                    entertained to the degree of absurdity, are advocated by one and another class
                    of writers. Essayists of the light and brilliant manner, who find their account
                    in an excess of fancy and invention, to set off common-place mat- <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="rut_nhg.00012.jpg" type="verso"/>
                    <fw type="date" place="top right">[Oct.,</fw>
                    <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">362</fw>
                    <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">On Style.</hi></fw> ter in gay
                    and pleasant colors, contend for nature; while rhetoricians, critics, and
                    historians, feeling the weight of their topics, are willing to help their styles
                    with artificial props and rules. The few who have attained a happy union of art
                    and nature, seem to have trusted with a careless confidence to the worth of
                    their ideas; and used no art but to exclude what was improper: but to attain
                    such a self-reliance, it is evident a writer must have discharged all trivial
                    intentions, and be bent upon something intrinsically good and useful. His
                    solicitude will then constrain him to employ all those reserves and cautions
                    that are used in conversation on some important affair. </p>
                <p>Some writers, and these the best, seem to have taken a hint form the musicians:
                    beginning modestly and rising, upon occasion, to the height of grandeur,
                    yielding at intervals to softer impulses. Few passages of actual life, we expect
                    the grand and marvelous only at wide intervals, and are satisfied, for
                    intermediate portions, with ingenuity or good sense. <span rend="doubleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="dl031" from="#dl031" to="#dl032"/>Skilful artists subdue the body of their piece to a tone of mediocrity, the
                    better to set off principal figures taking care that the shadows on either hand,
                    like the collaterals of a poem, shall pass into obscurity of indefiniteness.</p>
                <anchor xml:id="dl032"/>
                <p>Historians sometimes observe an inverted order, and instead of making the
                    circumstance illustrate the characters, subject the characters to the
                    circumstances, as though the actors in their drama were introduced for
                    experiments' sake; or as if men had been created for the uses of philosophy. If
                    there be any philosophy of history, it must be a part of ethics, and not of
                    physiology or mechanics. To treat the characters of his nation as a chemist
                    employs his substances, for the purpose of a theory, discovers either a vast
                    superiority, or as great modesty, in the historian. A chronicle without
                    character is perhaps the dullest of human works; but in an interesting history,
                    human will appears, tending to success or ruin, in the degree of its virtue; and
                    this spirit in the story of each event, accomplishing or failing of its ends,
                    divides the narrative, like an epic poem, into books and episodes. The rise and
                    fall of a great chief, the pride and ruin of a wealthy city, marches of armies,
                    battles, revolutions, institutions seem but so many vents of human character,
                    subordinate themselves, and receiving all their <cb/> lustre from the purposes
                    discovered in their progress and accomplishment.</p>
                <p>In the Anabasis of Xenophon, an army of mercenary troops, led by a young
                    adventurer, and stimulated by no greater hope than that of safety, draw our
                    imagination after them in a series of adventures, remarkable only as they are
                    obstacles in the way of a human design. Their story is a narrative of the hopes
                    and virtuous acts of their leader, who inspired them with his own spirit. But
                    when the same leader attempts a civil narrative of many complicated parts, his
                    work becomes a mere chronicle, with only here and there a passage of interest.
                    The affairs which Thucydides described are but illustrations, in his hands, of
                    the Greek character, and the spirit of rival States; Xenophon's continuation of
                    them resembles a compilation from various authors, put together under no one
                    idea.</p>
                <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="dl033" from="#dl033" to="#dl034"/>
                <p>There is a power in some writers and speakers, which proceeds either from
                    singleness of idea, or from that versatile force which gives unity to the most
                    rambling efforts of fancy. Either nothing occurs but what is proper, or by sheer
                    wit they find the same meaning in all that appears. Milton is an example of the
                    first, and <choice>
                        <orig>Shakspeare</orig>
                        <reg>Shakespeare</reg>
                    </choice> of the second kind of power; for the one never says anything aside
                    from the point, and the other wrests every thing to bear upon it. Other writers,
                    though powerful, seem, like Hercules, to have no purpose of their own, but
                    rather obey the occasion, than make or master it.</p>
                <anchor xml:id="dl034"/>
                <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="dl035" from="#dl035" to="#dl036"/>
                <p>A great writer or speaker engages seriously with his topic, as with an enemy
                    which he must subdue, and brings against it every weapon if which he is master.
                    He relieves the intervals of declamation with serviceable wit or anecdote; but
                    all point one way and have one effect. His unity is real, his variety only
                    apparent; and his rhetoric is the art of a cannonier, which directs the missile,
                    not urges it. </p>
                <anchor xml:id="dl036"/>
                <span rend="doubleLine-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="dl037" from="#dl037" to="#dl038"/>
                <p>When the master of his own thought heaps epithet on epithet, each exceeds the
                    last, and doubles its force. In a complex narrative he is in no danger of losing
                    the connection, but goes on involving periods, till we are in fear for him and
                    anticipate the end; where, with a single word, he strikes all home.<anchor xml:id="dl038"/> There is a regular sell and flow in fancy, as it were a
                    sea, over which the soul breathes, and moves it. As the depth of this sea, so
                    are its waves; and under a great spirit they are raised and borne forward with a
                    slow and majestic motion&#8212;as in Milton, <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="rut_nhg.00013.jpg" type="recto"/>
                    <fw type="date" place="top left">1845.]</fw>
                    <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">363</fw>
                    <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">On Style.</hi></fw> whose vast
                    force moves the deepest depths and carries forward the whole mind.</p>
                <p>When the variety of a subject is very great, a greater degree of the
                    consolidating power must have been exerted to bind it in a whole. By this power,
                    the genius of a great writer is discovered&#8212;more than by any other. <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="dl039" from="#dl039" to="#dl040"/>In the tragedies of <choice>
                        <orig>Shakspeare</orig>
                        <reg>Shakespeare</reg>
                    </choice>, for example, the entire history of each character is expressed in a
                    few remarks, that seem dropped without design; and the fate of each is made to
                    hang upon some accident, so slight and natural, it would attract no attention
                    but for its consequences. The unity of <choice>
                        <orig>Shakspeare's</orig>
                        <reg>Shakespeare's</reg>
                    </choice> dramas, is a unity not of time, or place, or circumstance, but far
                    more profound, of character.<anchor xml:id="dl040"/> Each event, and the
                    catastrophe, are accomplished, not by a chain of natural and fatal necessities,
                    but by elements of character prevailing in the persons of the drama. <del rend="erasure"><span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="dl041" from="#dl041" to="#dl042"/></del> This writer, like Homer, seems to have
                    been inspired with that perfect generosity of sentiment, which takes nature and
                    human beings, without cavil, as they are. Under this feeling he unfolds, without
                    sarcasm, every variety and change of character; as the painter, with equal
                    sobriety represents either beauty of deformity. The least partiality or
                    prejudice, infects a writer's reputation with a mortal decline. Even delicate
                    sentiment, because it is conventional, has only a perishable excellence; a
                    mixture of innocent falsehood causes its decay. Graces and philosophies pass
                    away with fashions and superstitions, but the moral spirit breathes life into a
                    work, and enables it to endure. </p>
                <p>A great deal has been said in praise of eloquence, as the most powerful of all
                    instruments for guiding and controlling the multitude; but the orator is limited
                    to a topic and occasion, and cannot deal much in principles. An author on the
                    contrary may treat his subject as he likes, and is sure of a deliberate hearing.
                    As it is rather the conduct and character of an orator that persuades, so there
                    is a secret something in the spirit of a book, which influences the reader in a
                    manner of which he is for the most part unconscious. As the spirit of a proud
                    man affects everything he says and does, through all pretences of humility, we
                    feel his presence accordingly, and are swayed by it in a peculiar manner.<anchor xml:id="dl042"/> But this power is exercised at the best advantage behind
                    the mask of a novel or a history. The circumstances, are so chosen and
                    narrated,<cb/> and the whole arranged in such a method, (though, it may be, with
                    no deliberate design on the author's part,) as constantly to impress his
                    governing idea. The literature of an age may be so thoroughly tainted with the
                    moral obliquities of that age, as to ensure its oblivion; and, on the contrary,
                    certain ages have been fired with such a liberality and generosity of sentiment,
                    as had power to preserve a great number of their authors, even to the fifth in
                    rank. A reader, who understands his author's spirit, form an involuntary
                    judgement of him, be he never so charitable or cautious in expressing it. Nor is
                    the world altogether deceived by the finest pretences, brought forward with the
                    most delightful ingenuity. A rough honest writer full of sense and devoid of
                    vanity may outlive his century with no attractions of arty, while mellifluous
                    poets sink with all their elegances into contempt. <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="dl043" from="#dl043" to="#dl044"/> But there is a
                    something in works of true genius for which our language has no name, unless it
                    be misapplied one of inspiration: a spirit in so close alliance with freedom, it
                    has hitherto appeared only in ages of civil and religious liberty. To
                    characterize this admirable quality by saying that it excites love in us for him
                    in whom it appears, would be to do it great injustice; for we not only love but
                    venerate him, and are won to an admiration of all that he says and
                    does,&#8212;of his name, his nation, and his age; this spirit must be a rarer
                    essence of love, so universal as to embrace not only friends and country, but
                    all mankind, and even earth itself. Hence the universality of Homer and <choice>
                        <orig>Shakspeare</orig>
                        <reg>Shakespeare</reg>
                    </choice>; for, whatever they knew and loved&#8212;that they represented; but
                    they knew and loved all that could be known and approved.<anchor xml:id="dl044"/> There is a word, now almost disused, but anciently great and serious import,
                    which comes nearer to expressing the whole spirit of genius than any other and
                    that word is Honor: when it unites a feeling of deference and veneration with a
                    sentiment of liberal equality. It exercises the same justice in matters of the
                    heart, that conscience does in those of business. By valuable considerations men
                    of ability may be drawn into the defence of a bad cause; but their heart rebels
                    against their head, and their genius forsakes them; enlist, on the other hand, a
                    weak ability under the colors of Honor, at once every power comes in play, and
                    the whole man is aroused. The sentiment, in its purity, <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="rut_nhg.00014.jpg" type="verso"/>
                    <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="top right"><handShift new="#h2"/>x</note>
                    <fw type="date" place="top right">[Oct.,</fw>
                    <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">364</fw>
                    <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">On Style.</hi></fw>
                    <handShift new="#h1"/>falls almost exactly under Cicero's description of
                    friendship, "Est autem nihil aliud, nisi omnium divinarum humanarumque rerum,
                    cum benevolentia et coritatē, summa consensio:&#8212;quâ quidam haud
                    scio, an excepta sapientia quidquam melius homini sit a diis immortalibus
                    daturum." "It is nothing else than the exalted harmony of all things human and
                    divine; and I know not if heaven has given man anything more precious, if we
                    except wisdom." It is more than probable that Cicero, himself inspired with this
                    principle, intends it under the name, "amicitia;" since every degree of
                    friendship depends upon a sensibility to this more universal sentiment.</p>
                <p>If an author or an orator is bold enough to resolve upon outlasting his century,
                    he will perhaps be wise enough to search out the secret of fame; and once master
                    of it, and of its contraries, will cultivate the one and avoid the other. As
                    soon as the intermixture of invention and opinion, behind which a bad sentiment
                    has fortified itself, is perished by the effect of revolutions in taste, the
                    fame of it decline, and all its labored excellences are forgotten; but what is
                    intrinsically good, can fall only by the accidents of time.</p>
                <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="dl045" from="#dl045" to="#dl046"/>
                <p>In the writings of Bacon, there is a something that makes us feel continually,
                    and breeds in us a reverence for all that is excellent in nature and in man. It
                    discovers great consequences in little matters, and teaches to despise nothing;
                    so that this author, by reason of his spirit, more than of his invention, became
                    the patron of a new epoch in reason; having turned the wisest minds to observe
                    those common particulars, which were before contemptuously overlooked.<anchor xml:id="dl046"/> A profound but sagacious reverence appears in every action
                    of his life, and seems to have been the cause as much of his misfortunes as of
                    his prosperity. But there is a sentiment more delightful than this, (though it
                    be less the mark of intelligence,) which gives their peculiar charm to the
                    characters of <choice>
                        <orig>Shakspeare</orig>
                        <reg>Shakespeare</reg>
                    </choice>, and since his day to all the finer parts of our literature. It had
                    its rise in the national feeling of England, refined to a social virtue; a
                    sentiment of liberty and tolerance, the precursor and parent of civil and
                    religious freedom; and in no author are these so perfectly discovered as in <choice>
                        <orig>Shakspeare</orig>
                        <reg>Shakespeare</reg>
                    </choice>. Honor and liberty are the subject of his story: an honor not testy
                    nor finical, but original in the breast; and liberty that began <cb/> earlier
                    than revolutions. There is hardly a character in his dramas that fails, either
                    directly or by contrast, to impress these sentiments. As good proof may be drawn
                    Homer, that it is the moral spirit of a work which perpetuates its fame and
                    fixes its rank; for in him two virtues, prudence and the love of glory, shine in
                    rare union; so mingled and tempered by respect for every degree of worth, his
                    poem seems permeated with an ichor, that shines in it as in the bodies of the
                    gods. A prose version of Homer, in the common dialect, loses nothing of this
                    excellence; for these principles are but the more conspicuously grand, when
                    stripped of all ornaments&#8212;like the mountains, divested of their
                    forests.</p>
                <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="dl047" from="#dl047" to="#dl048"/>
                <p>With such examples to inspire him with that generous emulation which is the life
                    of literature, a man of letters who understands the liberty he enjoys, will
                    doubtless use it as becomes a man. It is his privilege to assume no disguises: a
                    free people delights in a free speech; for our freedom is of the heart as well
                    as of the hands, though all are not quick to claim their birthright. We are at
                    liberty to speak truth, the most difficult and dangerous of acts. To despise
                    violence, and the narrow heart; to venerate that ancient wisdom which raised us
                    to this height; to believe in the unalterable name of truth, and in the
                    permanency of those principles on which all literature, and indeed all human
                    arts, are a faint and broken comment; to avoid uncouth novelties, and to value
                    nothing that cannot be converted to an ethical use; above all, to cultivate the
                    liberal mind; these are the aim of letters in our own as they have been in all
                    free ages.</p>
                <anchor xml:id="dl048"/>
                <p>Republics seem to be governed, or at least guided, by writers and speakers; for
                    these alone, of professions, cultivate in themselves ideas which govern and
                    organize states. The spirit of a self educated moralist is of necessity one of
                    perfect liberty. Such a republican spirit we conceive to have animated the
                    heroes and patriots of old who knew no mode of policy but religion and virtue.
                    These they would have paramount to all constitutions; they would not suffer
                    monarchs, or senates, or popular assemblies, under pretences of dignity, or
                    authority, or freedom, to throw off those moral riders which reason has
                    appointed to govern every sort of rude power."* <hi rend="smallcaps">J.D.W.</hi></p>
                <fw type="footnote" place="bottom">*Burke, Letter to Wm. Elliot.</fw>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>