<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="rut.00015">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">"Words"</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
                <author xml:id="unk">Unknown</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="jyc">Jonathan Y. Cheng</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>University of Texas at Austin</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>rut.00015</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>kprice@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Ed-Folsom@uiowa.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>bbarney2@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability><p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain exceptions, public domain works may be freely copied or used in the creation of derivative works without permission, or authorization, of the former copyright owners.</p><p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and is governed by a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0).</p><p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Unknown</author>
                    <title>"Words"</title>
                    <!--<idno type="callno"></idno>-->
                    <date cert="high" when="1845-02">Feb 1845</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="rut">Special Collections and University Archives, Rutgers University
                        Libraries, Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey </orgName>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from our digital image of original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="h2" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h3" scribeRef="#ww" medium="ink"/>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#jyc" when="2014-10-24">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="marginalia">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="rut_nhg.00045.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="top"><handShift new="#h2"/>Words.</note>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="top left">+</note>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="top right">13)</note>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="top right">2</note>
            <fw type="date" place="top left">1845.]</fw>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">177</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">Sonnet.</hi></fw>
            <div1>
                <delSpan rend="hashmark" spanTo="#ds001" hand="#h2"/>
                <p>did also its share of good, in holding up before despots a mirror in which they
                    might read their own fate, and teaching the world that oppression has a limit,
                    and buried freedom its resurrection day; and that just so deep as human rights
                    and hopes are sunk, just so high will the tide of vengeance swell at last;</p>

                <l>"Truth crushed to earth will rise again;</l>
                <l>The eternal years of God are hers." </l>

                <p>The fate of our own republic, which Mr. Alison reads so prophetically, is by no
                    means yet decided; and even should we fall, we do not consider the question of
                    the durability of a republican government settled. Had our population been
                    suffered to increase, by the natural laws which govern it, and all those who
                    control our interests been educated in the principles of true freedom, and been
                    bound together by the common ties of kindred and country, and the whole glorious
                    fabric of our constitution steadily strengthened as bulwark after bulwark was
                    reared around it by the jealous watchfulness of an intelligent people, had we
                    been left to try out the experiment, by ourselves, on our own soil, then we
                    should consider the question of the expediency of a republican form of
                    government fixed for ever.</p>

                <p>But now we are compelled not only to struggle with the evils that gather
                    around<cb/> every new undertaking, but to blend and incorporate into the very
                    heart of our system the ignorance and degradation and crime of the despotisms of
                    Europe. From such materials as tyranny sends us we are asked to rear our
                    structure, and if it ever sways and totters, from the heterogeneous mass we are
                    compelled to pile so hastily into it, we are tauntingly asked&#8212;How goes the
                    doctrine of equality? The tens of thousands of hungry, half naked, and miserable
                    beings, that are precipitated yearly upon our bosom, and enter almost
                    immediately upon the work of reforming our system, come from a government where
                    all their sorrows have sprung from the oppression of the upper classes. Knowing
                    the " wormwood and the gall," and retaining the old hatred against the rich that
                    has strengthened with their sufferings, they are easily led, like the mobs of
                    Paris, by unscrupulous leaders, to act against their own permanent interests.
                    So, also, the convicts and famine-struck wretches, that the prisons and
                    almshouses of Europe disgorge yearly on our shores, swell the records of crime
                    and pauperism in our land, while the acts they commit and the sufferings they
                    engender, are charged over to republicanism. "<hi rend="italic">Laissez
                        faire</hi>" is a just request; and could the world but have granted it to us
                    we should have been content. </p>


                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>

                <lg>
                    <head type="main-authorial" rend="smallcaps">SONNET.</head>
                    <lg type="linegroup">
                        <l>Many I love to gaze on, or to hear</l>
                        <l>Carol melodious notes of young delight&#8212;</l>
                        <l>But there is One, with blue eye soft and clear,</l>
                        <l>Who haunts my thoughts by day, my dreams by night.</l>
                        <l>And her, I love: her face to me is fair</l>
                        <l>As early dawn; like a translucent veil</l>
                        <l>It overshades a soul&#8212;how pure and bright</l>
                        <l>And beautiful no features could declare,</l>
                        <l>Nor yet could any features half conceal!</l>
                        <l>A gentle spirit is thine, sweet maiden, thine</l>
                        <l>A timid, fawn-like nature, and we fear</l>
                        <l>Almost to love thee, lest a wreath we twine</l>
                        <l>Too heavy for they greatness to bear,</l>
                        <l>As for the gentlest flowers even dew-drops are!</l>
                    </lg>
                </lg>

                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">PENSEROSO.</hi></p>
                <anchor xml:id="ds001"/>
            </div1>
            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="rut_nhg.00046.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="date" place="top right">[Feb.,</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">178</fw>
                <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">Words.</hi></fw>
                <head type="main-authorial" rend="smallcaps">WORDS</head>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">WORDS</hi> we are told, are the signs of ideas. This
                    definition at best is faulty, and, in a majority of cases, untrue. Nothing is
                    more common than to see words without any sign of ideas at all. Besides, those
                    who understand the nature of language, and wield uncontrolled dominion over all
                    its powers, have been careful to tell us that the true use of words is not to
                    express but to conceal ideas. Words, moreover, are of such inherent value in
                    themselves, and in the concerns of the world exercise such untrammeled
                    influence, that it is unjust to degrade them from sovereigns into
                    representatives. It would be much more modest for lovers of definition to say,
                    not that words <hi rend="italic">are</hi>, but that they <hi rend="italic">should</hi> be the signs of ideas. The moralist is more philosophical. He
                    distinguishes carefully between qualities and their application. He defines the
                    laws of ethics, and informs us that men should obey them, not that they do.</p>
                <p> The true ruler of this big, bouncing world is the Lexicon. Every new word added
                    to its accumulated thousands, is a new element of servitude to mankind. We
                    should therefore look sharply at all axioms which seem to fix the signification
                    of these little substantives and sovereigns. The notion that they are the signs
                    of thought can be disposed of without any train of tedious argument; because the
                    originators and defenders of that notion are found instantly inconsistent, when
                    we unite any two of their propositions. For instance, the remark is often heard
                    that certain words in certain connections are "full of sound and fury,
                    signifying nothing." Now if words be full of sound, they must necessarily be
                    sound words, and if words are the signs of ideas, sound words must represent
                    sound thoughts. Here is a logical dilemma for these axiomatic gentlemen.</p>
                <p>Indeed words, in themselves, are nothing more than " mouthfuls of spoken wind,"
                    the sons and daughters of the tongue and lungs. They are hardened into
                    consistency by a process of pens, ink and paper. In this state they take form.
                    But naturally they are immaterial substances like thoughts. The sculptor
                    embodies an idea in marble, and we discriminate between the essence and the
                    form. Why should we not also distinguish between <cb/> a word printed or written
                    and a word spoken or conceived&#8212;between the body and the soul of an
                    expulsion of air? Words, in truth, are entities, real existences, immortal
                    beings; and though I would not go the whole length of Enthusiast Hazlitt, in
                    saying that they are the only things that live forever, I would vindicate their
                    title to a claim in the eternities of this world, and defend them from the
                    cavils of presumption and ignorance.</p>
                <p><choice>
                        <orig>Shakspeare</orig>
                        <reg>Shakespeare</reg>
                    </choice>, speaking through Lorenzo, regrets with much feeling the thickness of
                    ear which prevents us from drinking in the music of the spheres. But how much
                    more, in a moral and intellectual point of view, should we lament that hard
                    condition of our faculty of hearing, by which we are prevented from enjoying all
                    the sweet noises of the past and compelled to hear only the harsh <choice>
                        <orig>gutterals</orig>
                        <reg>gutturals</reg>
                    </choice>of the present. Every disturbance of the atmosphere, caused by the
                    ejection of a word, does not cease with our perception of it, but is
                    everlastingly active. All around us now are the words of Noah, and Moses, and
                    Plato, and Socrates, and <choice>
                        <orig>Shakspeare</orig>
                        <reg>Shakespeare</reg>
                    </choice>, and Milton; and if our ears were only delicate enough to convey the
                    sounds into our minds, we might hear, with our outward organ, Plato converse
                    with Phrædros on the soul's immortality, Socrates gravel a sophist with his
                    interrogative logic, <choice>
                        <orig>Shakspeare</orig>
                        <reg>Shakespeare</reg>
                    </choice> sting Ben Johnson or Master Dekkar with a joke worthy of Thersites,
                    and Milton ask quaker Ellwood to read Homer to him, or rebuke his daughters for
                    unkindness and inattention. The air is a more faithful chronicler of words than
                    books. Every whisper of wickedness, which has fallen from the white lips of a
                    tyrant or murderer, and which has never passed into but one human heart, is
                    still alive in the air, and circling the earth in company with the song of
                    Miriam, and the thunder of Luther, and the low prayer of Ridley, and the scoff
                    of D'Holbach, and the profaneness of Rochester, and the denunciations of Burke.
                    Truly are we surrounded with Voices. The sacredness and awful responsibilities
                    of speech&#8212;the latent importance of idle words&#8212;consist in ever
                    present existence. No sound that goes from the lip into the <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="rut_nhg.00047.jpg" type="recto"/>
                    <fw type="date" place="top left">1845.]</fw>
                    <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">179</fw>
                    <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">Words.</hi></fw> air, can ever
                    die, even in a sensual sense, until the atmosphere, which wraps our planet in
                    its huge embrace, has passed into nothingness. Words, then, have a being of
                    their own; they exist after death, or rather they continue to exist after all
                    memory of them has departed from the minds into which they originally
                    entered.</p>
                <p>Leaving, however, these logical and lofty notions of words, and coming down to
                    the everyday world of books and men, we observe many queer developments of the
                    cozenage of language. The most fluent man seems the most influential. All
                    classes appear to depend upon words. Principles are nothing in comparison with
                    speech. A politician is accused of corruption, inconsistency, and loving number
                    one more than number ten thousand. Straightway he floods the country with words,
                    and he is honorably acquitted. A gentleman of far-reaching and purse-reaching
                    intelligence concocts twenty millions of pills, and " works" them off to agents,
                    and, in the end, transfers the whole from his laboratory to the stomachs of an
                    injured and oppressed people, by means of&#8212;words. Miss A. stabs the
                    spotless name of Mrs. P. with a word-stiletto. The poisonous breath of a
                    venomous fanatic moulds itself into syllables, and, lo! a sect of christians is
                    struck with leprosy. An author wishes to be sublime, but has no fire in him to
                    give sparkle and heat to his compositions. His ideas are milk and
                    water-logged,&#8212; feeble, common-place, nerveless, witless, and soulless; or
                    his thoughts are ballasted with lead instead of being winged with inspiration.
                    "What shall I do!" he cries, in the most plaintive terms of aspiring stupidity.
                    Poor poetaster! do not despair! take to thy dictionary&#8212;drench thy thin
                    blood with gin&#8212;learn the power of words. Pile the Pelion of Rant on the
                    Ossa of Hyperbole, and thy small fraction of the Trite shall be exalted to the
                    heights of the Sublime and the admiring gaze of many people shall be fixed upon
                    it, and the coin shall jingle in thy pocket, and thou shalt be denominated
                    Great! But if thy poor pate be incapable of the daring, even in expression, then
                    grope dubiously in the dismal swamps of verbiage, and let thy mind's fingers
                    feel after <choice>
                        <orig>spungy</orig>
                        <reg>spongy</reg>
                    </choice> and dropsical words, out of which little sense can be squeezed, and
                    arrange the oozy epithets and unsubstantial substantives into lines, and out of
                    the very depths of Bathos, thou shalt arise a sort<cb/> of mud-Venus, and men
                    shall mistake thee for her that rose from the sea, and the coin shall still
                    clink in thy fob, and thou shalt be called Beautiful! Such is the omnipotence of
                    words! They can exalt the little; they can depress the high; a ponderous
                    polysyllable will break the chain of an argument, or crack the pate of a
                    thought, as a mace or a battle-axe could split the crown of a soldier in the
                    elder time.</p>
                <p>To cover a man with contempt or obloquy, it is only necessary to apply to him
                    some catchword of theology or politics. Society will say with the sagacious
                    Polonious, that such a word is good or bad, and judge of the living noun by the
                    character of verbal tin-pail, that wit or malice has appended to its tail. A man
                    or woman, who has had certain impertinent or degrading adjectives applied to his
                    or her name will feel their sting and rattle long after they have been proved
                    false and malignant. "A person with a bad name is already half hanged," saith
                    the old Proverb.</p>
                <p>Words are most effective when arranged in that order which is called style. The
                    great secret of a good style, we are told, is to have proper words in proper
                    places. To marshal one's verbal battalions in such order, that they may bear at
                    once upon all quarters of a subject, is certainly a great art. This is done in
                    different ways. Swift, Temple, Addison, Hume, Gibbon, Johnson, Burke, are all
                    great generals in the discipline of their verbal armies, and the conduct of
                    their paper wars. Each has a system of tactics of his own, and excels in the use
                    of some particular weapon. The tread of Johnson's style is heavy and sonorous,
                    resembling that of an elephant or a mail-clad warrior. He is fond of leveling an
                    obstacle by a polysyllabic battering-ram. Burke's words are continually
                    practicing the broad-sword exercise, and sweeping down adversaries with every
                    stroke. Arbuthnot "plays his weapon like a tongue of flame." Addison draws up
                    his light infantry in orderly array, and marches through sentence after
                    sentence, without having his ranks disordered or his line broken. Luther is
                    different. His words are "half battle;" " his smiting idiomatic phrases seem to
                    cleave into the very secret of the matter." Gibbon's legions are heavily armed,
                    and march with precision and dignity to the music of their own tramp. They are
                    splendidly equipped, but a nice eye can discern a little rust <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="rut_nhg.00048.jpg" type="verso"/>
                    <note type="authorial" resp="#h3" place="top left"><handShift new="#h3"/>Style
                        is not to be shackled by sweeping rules.</note>
                    <note type="authorial" resp="#h3" place="top right" target="#dl001" anchored="true">There is no model style ☟ </note>
                    <fw type="date" place="top right">[Feb.,</fw>
                    <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">180</fw>
                    <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">Words.</hi></fw> beneath their
                    fine apparel, and there are <choice>
                        <orig>suttlers</orig>
                        <reg>sutlers</reg>
                    </choice> in his camp who lie, cog and talk gross obscenity. Macauley, brisk,
                    lively, keen and energetic, runs his thoughts rapidly through his sentence, and
                    kicks out of the way every word which obstructs his passage. He reins in his
                    steed only when he has reached his goal, and then does it with such celerity
                    that he is nearly thrown backwards by the suddenness of his stoppage. Gifford's
                    words are moss-troopers, that waylay innocent travelers and murder them for
                    hire. Jeffrey is a fine "lance," with a sort of Arab swiftness in his movement,
                    and runs an iron-clad horseman through the eye before he has had time to close
                    his helmet. John Wilson's camp is a disorganized mass, who might do effectual
                    service under better discipline, but who under his lead are suffered to carry on
                    a rambling and predatory warfare, and disgrace their general by flagitious
                    excesses. Sometimes they steal, sometimes swear, sometimes drink and sometimes
                    pray. Swift's words are porcupine's quills, which he throws with unerring aim at
                    whoever approaches his lair. All of Ebenezer Elliot's words are gifted with huge
                    fists, to pummel and bruise. Chatham and Mirabeau throw hot shot into their
                    opponents' magazines. Talfourd's forces are orderly and disciplined, and march
                    to the music of the Dorian flute; those of Keats keep time to the tones of the
                    pipe of Phoebus; and the hard, harsh-featured battalions of Maginn, are always
                    preceded by a brass band. Hallam's word-infantry can do much execution, when
                    they are not in each other's way. Pope's phrases are either daggers or rapiers.
                    Willis's words are often tipsy with the champaign of the fancy, but even when
                    they reel and stagger they keep the line of grace and beauty, and though
                    scattered at first by a fierce onset from graver cohorts, soon reunite without
                    wound or loss. John Neal's forces are multitudinous and fire briskly at
                    everything. They occupy all the provinces of letters, and are nearly useless
                    from being spread over too much ground. Everett's weapons axe ever kept in good
                    order, and shine well in the sun, but they are little calculated for warfare,
                    and rarely kill when they strike. Webster's words are thunder-bolts, which
                    sometimes miss the Titans at whom they are hurled, but always leave ensuring
                    marks when they strike. Hazlitt's verbal army is sometimes drunk and surly,
                    sometimes foaming with passion,<cb/> sometimes cool and malignant, but drunk or
                    sober are ever dangerous to cope with. Some of Tom Moore's words are shining
                    dirt, which he flings with excellent aim. This list might be indefinitely
                    extended, and arranged with more regard to merit and chronology. My own words,
                    in this connection, might be compared to ragged, undisciplined militia, which
                    could be easily routed by a charge of horse, and which are apt to fire into each
                    other's faces.</p>
                <p><span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="dl001" from="#dl001" to="#dl002"/>There is a great amount of critical nonsense talked about style. One prim
                    Aristarchus in a stiff cravat, tells us that no manner of expression is so good
                    as that of Addison; another contends for Carlyle; and both would have words
                    arrayed according to their own models, without regard to individual mental bias
                    or <choice>
                        <orig>idiosyncracies</orig>
                        <reg>idiosyncrasies</reg>
                    </choice>. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">If style be good, just in proportion
                        as it enables an author to express his thoughts, it should be shackled by
                        few general rules. Every style formed elaborately on any model, must be
                        affected and strait-laced.</hi> Every imitator of Byron and Pope has been
                    damned and forgotten. The nature of a man can only squeal out, when it is
                    hampered by artificial environments. Some thoughts, in a cramped style, look
                    like Venus improved by the addition of busk and bustle. The selection and
                    arrangement of a writer's words should be as characteristic as his ideas and
                    feelings. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">There is no model style. What is
                        pleasing in the diction of one author disgusts us in a copyist. If a person
                        admires a particular method of arranging words, that arrangement will occur
                        naturally in his own diction,</hi> without malice aforethought. Some writers
                    unconsciously fall into the mode of expression adopted by others. This
                    illustrates a similarity of disposition, and is not imitation. As a style, when
                    it is natural, comes rather from the heart than the head; men of similar tastes
                    and feelings will be likely to fall into a similar form of expression. Leigh
                    Hunt's easy slip-shod is pleasant enough to read, as his nature is easy and
                    slip-shod; but only to think of Carlyle running into that way of writing? Sidney
                    Smith, concise, brisk and brilliant, has a manner of composition which exactly
                    corresponds to those qualities; but how could Lord Bacon look on Smith's
                    sentences? How grandly the soul of Milton rolls and winds through the arches and
                    labyrinths of his involved and magnificent diction, waking musical echoes at
                    every new turn and variation of <anchor xml:id="dl002"/><pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="rut_nhg.00049.jpg" type="recto"/>
                    <fw type="date" place="top left">1845.]</fw>
                    <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">181</fw>
                    <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">Words.</hi></fw>
                    <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h2" xml:id="dl003" from="#dl003" to="#dl004"/> its progress&#8212;but how could the thought of such a light
                    trifler as Cibber travel through so glorious a maze without being loot or
                    crushed in the journey? The plain, manly language of John Locke could hardly be
                    translated into the terminology of Kant&#8212;would look out of place in the
                    rapid and sparkling movement of Cousin's periods&#8212;and would appear mean in
                    the cadences of Dugald Stewart. Every writer, therefore, is his own standard.
                    The law by which we judge of his sentences must be deduced <hi rend="italic">from</hi> his sentences. If we can discover what the man is, we know what
                    his style ought to be. If it indicate his character, it is, relatively, good; if
                    it contradict his character, though its cadences are faultless, it is still bad
                    and not to be endured. To condemn Carlyle and Macauley because they do not run
                    their thoughts into the moulds of Addison or Burke, is equivalent to condemning
                    a bear because he does not digest stones like an ostrich, or a chicken, because
                    it goes on two legs instead of four. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">The alleged
                        faults belong to organization.</hi> We may quarrel with a writer if we
                    please, for possessing a bad or tasteless nature, but not with the style, which
                    takes from that nature its form and movement.</p>
                <p><span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="dl005" from="#dl005" to="#dl006"/>It is singular that Macauley and Carlyle, continually protesting against
                    affectation in the mode of expressing thought, should be themselves considered
                    the high priests at the shrine of affectation. In truth, no writers are less
                    open to the charge. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">Their styles are exact
                        mirrors of their minds.</hi> Any other form of expression, would in them, be
                    gross affectation.<anchor xml:id="dl006"/> When they change their dispositions
                    and modes of thinking, and preserve their way of writing, they will then be
                    justly liable to rebuke, and would be justly punished with neglect.</p>
                <anchor xml:id="dl004"/>
                <p>Words have generally been termed the dress of thought. We recollect of hearing a
                    lecturer on elocution give a minute description of the manner in which this
                    curious tailoring of ideas was effected. He appareled an abstract conception of
                    the Intellect in stockings, shirt, <choice>
                        <orig>trowsers</orig>
                        <reg>trousers</reg>
                    </choice>, vest, coat and bright buttons, and showed us those closets and
                    drawers in the brain's chamber, where such articles of clothing were deposited.
                    This notion of words being the dress of thought is indeed curious. Let us
                    suppose a case. An Imagination rises from the soft bed of Ideality, on hearing
                    the tinkle of Master Reason's or Master Volition's bell. Of course<cb/> it does
                    not desire to appear before company in a state of nudity, and it accordingly
                    trips lightly into the dressing-room of the Noddle, and overhauls the mind's
                    wardrobe. Now this wardrobe in some heads is scanty and poor, in others
                    overflowing with rich and costly apparel. At any rate our Imagination slips on
                    the most shining and flaring suit of clothes it can find, and then slides along
                    a number of nerves into the lungs, and sails out of the mouth on a stream of
                    sound, to delight the world with its presence. In the verbal wardrobe of
                    Wordsworth there would be few rich garments: consequently most of his thoughts
                    or fancies would be compelled to appear in peasants' frocks or suits of "homely
                    russet brown." All of Byron's ideas aspired to be clad in regal splendor; and,
                    as they were in the custom of crowding thick and fast into the dressing-room,
                    there must have been some jostling and fighting among them, for the most costly
                    and showy suits. Vice and Falsehood would crave fine apparel as well as Virtue
                    and Truth; and, in his case, they must often have succeeded in bullying the
                    latter out of their rights and "tights." There are a class of authors who have
                    rich garments but no thoughts to put into them. The garments, however, please
                    the eye of the multitude, and few discover that they are stuffed with brass
                    instead of brains. Some poets have nothing but ragged clothes in their wardrobe,
                    and their poor shivering Ideas go sneaking about the alleys of letters, ashamed
                    to be seen by their more richly-dressed relations. Others, though in rags, have
                    a certain quick impudence, like that of Robert Macaire, which enables them to
                    bustle about among their betters, and seem genteel though in rags. We sometimes
                    observe Thoughts in the prim coats and broad hats of quakers; but they are not
                    admitted to the " West End,"&#8212;excepting, of course, " the West End of the
                    Universe." Sir Charles Sedley was distinguished for writing poems of
                    considerable impurity of idea and considerable purity of language. His
                    biographer therefore is careful to inform us that though the sentiments of Sir
                    Charles were as foul as those of Rochester, they were not so immodest, because
                    they were covered with clean linen. Dryden's wardrobe, we are told, was like
                    that of a Russian noble,&#8212;" all filth and diamonds, dirty linen and
                    inestimable sables." To such speculations and fancies as these are we led, when
                    we acknowledge the <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="rut_nhg.00050.jpg" type="verso"/>
                    <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="top right"><handShift new="#h2"/>+</note>
                    <fw type="date" place="top right">[Feb.,</fw>
                    <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">182</fw>
                    <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">Words.</hi></fw> truth of the
                    maxim, that words are the dress of thought.</p>
                <p><span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h3" xml:id="dl007" from="#dl007" to="#dl008"/>Words, however, even in the common meaning, are not, when used by a
                    mastermind, the mere dress of thought. Such a definition degrades them below
                    their sphere, and misconceives their importance. They are, as Wordsworth has
                    happily said, the <hi rend="italic">incarnation</hi> of thought. They bear the
                    same relation to ideas, that the body bears to the soul. Take the most beautiful
                    and sincere poetry, which has ever been written, and its charm is broken as soon
                    as the words are disturbed or altered. If any expression can be employed except
                    that which is used, the poet is a bungling rhetorician or writes on the surface
                    of his theme. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">A Thought embodied and <hi rend="italic">embrained</hi> in fit words, walks the earth a living
                        being. No part of its body can be stricken from it, or injured, without
                        disfiguring the beauty of its form or spoiling its grace of motion.</hi>
                    Such Thoughts, perhaps, are few in number; but <choice>
                        <orig>wo</orig>
                        <reg>woe</reg>
                    </choice> upon those tasteless critics, who would meddle with those few, and
                    dare to alter their organization, on the plea of improvement!<anchor xml:id="dl008"/></p>

                <p>Words in a few " eminent hands" are servile ministers; but generally, even in
                    great writers, they are kings who rule, not subjects who obey. In some minds
                    they obtain "sovereign sway and masterdom" over the whole domain of thought and
                    emotion. <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h3" xml:id="dl009" from="#dl009" to="dl010"/><hi rend="underline" hand="#h3">This servitude</hi> to words <hi rend="underline" hand="#h3">often produces</hi> injurious results to the
                    writer. It is the parent of many fallacies and inconsistencies. For
                    instance&#8212;a reasoner desires to argue closely and logically; a word often
                    leads him astray into a sophism, or tempts him, by its winning looks, to slide
                    into episodes. A critic wishes to analyze a book; but instead of analysis he
                    gives his readers eulogy or denunciation; for certain words which sprang up,
                    like flowers or thistles, in his path, were too sweet or too sharp for him to
                    avoid. To give point to a period, some writers will throw in a word which will
                    stab innocence or mediocrity like a <choice>
                        <orig>poignard</orig>
                        <reg>poniard</reg>
                    </choice>; to make a sentence end harmoniously, others will <hi rend="italic">pad</hi> it with <anchor xml:id="dl010"/><cb/>
                    <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h3" xml:id="dl011" from="#dl011" to="#dl012"/> words, which are meaningless or out of place. In describing
                    characters or scenery, the general custom is to employ language which is
                    beautiful or strong, rather than what is applicable. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">Nothing is rarer than the use of a word in its exact
                        meaning.</hi> Amplitude of comprehension is a much finer phrase than good
                    reasoning powers; and consequently every respectable thinker is made a Bacon;
                    vivid imagination sounds better than moderate talent, and of course, every
                    rhyme-stringer is a Byron; miserable drivelling has a sharper edge than mediocre
                        merit,<anchor xml:id="dl012"/> and all common-place writers are therefore to
                    be fools or dunces. Lord Byron, in alluding to the supposed cause of Keats's
                    death, said&#8212;</p>

                <l>"Strange that the soul, that very fiery particle,<lb/> Should let itself be
                    snuffed out by an article."</l>

                <p>Hunt told him that Keats was not killed in this way. Byron promised to strike it
                    out. But the smartness and the rhyme, were temptations stronger than his
                    conscience, and he allowed the couplet to remain.</p>
                <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h3" xml:id="dl013" from="#dl013" to="#dl014"/>
                <p>It would be an easy matter to mention some words which have exercised greater
                    influence, and swayed with more absolute power, than Alexander or Napoleon. Any
                    one can pick up in a newspaper the sovereigns of our own country. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h2">A word often keeps its seat in the mind of a
                        people, after the thought to which originally it was nominally attached, has
                        disappeared. Words head armies, overthrow dynasties, man ships, separate
                        families, cozen cozeners, and steal hearts and purses.</hi> And if
                    physiologists and metaphysicians are driven into a corner, and are compelled to
                    give the real distinction between human beings and animals, they are almost sure
                    to say it consists in the power of speech&#8212;in the capacity to frame, use
                    and multiply at discretion, these omnipotent "mouthfuls of spoken wind."
                    Words&#8212;words&#8212;words!</p>
                <anchor xml:id="dl014"/>
                <milestone rend="horbar-short-center" unit="undeclared"/>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>