<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="rut.00016">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">"Journalism"</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
                <author xml:id="unk">Unknown</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="jyc">Jonathan Y. Cheng</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>University of Texas at Austin</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>rut.00016</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>kprice@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Ed-Folsom@uiowa.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>bbarney2@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability><p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain exceptions, public domain works may be freely copied or used in the creation of derivative works without permission, or authorization, of the former copyright owners.</p><p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and is governed by a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY 4.0).</p><p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p></availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Unknown</author>
                    <title>"Journalism"</title>
                    <!--<idno type="callno"></idno>-->
                    <date cert="high" when="1845-02">Sept 1846</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="rut">Special Collections and University Archives, Rutgers University
                        Libraries, Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey </orgName>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from our digital image of original.</note>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="h2" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#jyc" when="2014-10-24">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="marginalia">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="rut_nhg.00005.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="top"><handShift new="#h2"/>Newspapers</note>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="top left">+</note>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="top right">12)</note>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h2" place="top right">4</note>
            <fw type="date" place="top left">1846.]</fw>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">281</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">Journalism</hi></fw>
            <div1>
                <p>"'If matters proceed in the lively manner they have for
                    the last ten years, you'll hear of it often. Hitherto, the rich of Europe have
                    been in the habit of laying by a penny in America against an evil day; but the
                    time will soon come, unless there is a great change, when the rich of America
                    will return the compliment in kind. We are worse off than if we were in a state
                    of nature, in many respects; having our hands tied by the responsibility that
                    belongs to <hi rend="italic">our</hi> position and means, while those who choose
                    to assail us are under a mere nominal restraint.'"</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">COOPER'S RECEIPT FOR ANTI-RENTISM</hi> is, in substance,
                    simply to <hi rend="italic">disfranchise those counties which resist the
                        operation of law</hi>. When will our rul&#8212;our <hi rend="italic">servants</hi>, we mean, be men enough to use so efficacious a remedy?</p>
                <p>But our limits compel us to take <choice>
                        <sic>leaye</sic>
                        <corr>leave</corr>
                    </choice> for the present of this most valuable book. We say <hi rend="italic">for the present</hi>, for its themes are too momentous to be disposed of so
                    briefly. But one thing we must say in conclusion. The parts of this work which
                    might seem, to the inexperienced reader, the wildest, such as the hints at
                    emigration, suggestions of repelling force by force, &amp;c., <hi rend="italic">do not originate with Mr.<cb/> Cooper</hi>. The same thoughts have found a <choice>
                        <orig>lodgment</orig>
                        <reg>lodgement</reg>
                    </choice> in many a breast already, though they have never till now found so
                    open an utterance. More than one party of Americans in Europe (albeit it might
                    consist of more than a bachelor uncle and his nephew) has held such a
                    conversation as Hugh and Roger held in Paris. More than one American has given
                    his friends as grim a welcome home as Jack Dunning did the Littlepages.</p>
                <p>And finally (for there is room for a few more lines) if any one should blame us
                    for omitting the lesser duties of criticism&#8212;for having failed to observe
                    that Mr. Cooper's style is at times incurably wooden, and his sentences
                    frequently read the very opposite of what they mean, and his mottoes
                    occasionally have not the least earthly connection with the subjects of the
                    chapters to which they are prefixed&#8212;we have noticed these blemishes and
                    others, as who has not in every novel that Mr. Cooper ever wrote. But at present
                    we are in no frame of mind to carp at the spots on the face of the sun. If all
                    our authors would write as truthfully as the author of "Indian and Ingin" we
                    should be content to have them all write as clumsily.</p>
            </div1>

            <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>

            <div1>
                <head type="main-authorial" rend="smallcaps">JOURNALISM.</head>

                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">THE PRESS</hi>! what a moral and social power is comprised
                    in that term! The Press! a sceptre swayed by an invisible hand! <hi rend="smallcaps">THE PRESS</hi>! a throne on which a veiled prophet is
                    seated! <hi rend="smallcaps">THE PRESS</hi>! a sovereign whose mighty behests
                    are without appeal! a tribunal whose decrees, like those of Providence, execute
                    themselves! an impersonal despot, exercising without definite responsibility
                    self-created power!</p>

                <p>Is the press one estate of the realm? It is unrecognized and unacknowledged by
                    the technicalities of the Constitution. Its existence is only connived at! Some
                    that have felt its potency, have called it the fourth power. In practical truth,
                    and actuality, it is the first power of the state! </p>

                <p>Sovereign, Lords, Commons, and&#8212;<hi rend="smallcaps">THE PRESS</hi>!</p>

                <p>The order of formal announcement is the inverse of their actual importance. The
                    most insignificant takes the lead&#8212;the place of power is in the rear.</p>

                <p>To behold this mighty intellectual engine of human advancement surrounded with
                    all the accessories which can augment its efficiency, we must look there where
                    it is at once allied with unlimited power of capital, mental agencies of the
                    first order, enterprise which acknowledges no limits, and a perfect emancipation
                    from the trammels of censorship&#8212;we must, in a word, look to <hi rend="smallcaps">LONDON</hi>.</p>

                <p> The original object of a journal was the collection and circulation of "news."
                    News! that is to say, information of those current events in which the public
                    feels an interest. Hence a journal was called a "Newspaper." This is still, and
                    will ever continue to be, one of the chief, if not the most important, of its
                    functions. But besides being a register of passing events, it has become a
                    commentator upon them. It is a judge as well as a recorder. It is a
                    self-constituted tribunal, to whose sentence all are amenable. It is the most
                        <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="rut_nhg.00006.jpg" type="verso"/>
                    <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">282</fw>
                    <fw type="date" place="top right">[Sept.</fw>
                    <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="italic">Journalism.</hi></fw> efficient
                    of tribunals, because the sentence itself constitutes the punishment . Its
                    punishments are inevitable, so long as its decisions are in accordance with that
                    law of which it is the administrator. That law is <hi rend="smallcaps">PUBLIC
                        OPINION</hi>. It is, further, a prognosticator of approaching events. With
                    the character of the judge, it combines that of the prophet.</p>

                <p>Yet, like other prophets, it often appears to predict, when it only announces
                    that of which it has secret means of information. It often, therefore, seems to
                    lead public opinion when it really follows it.</p>

                <p>The light it sheds on public questions is sometimes only reflected. Its rays,
                    collected from innumerable scattered and unperceived sources among that very
                    public itself, are sent back in a condensed and concentrated state. The Press is
                    to the scattered and divergent rays of public intelligence what the
                    burning-glass is to those of the sun. It brings them to a definite focus, where
                    their concentrated power exercises a force to which the most obdurate substances
                    yield.</p>

                <p>But public opinion is divided on all questions of general interest, and
                    especially on political questions. Each great party finds its appropriate organ
                    in the Press; and sometimes, as in the case of the Parisian Press, every <hi rend="italic">nuance</hi> of opinion has its separate organ. This minute
                    division is more limited in the London Press, owing to the vast capital
                    necessary to establish and sustain a daily newspaper. Parties, also, in England
                    are more ready to compromise differences, for the sake of the strength gained by
                    cooperation. Newspapers are less multifarious, therefore; and more capital being
                    devoted to the management of each individual journal, and the paper being sold
                    at a higher price, there is a possibility of securing higher and more various
                    talent in its conduct and direction.</p>

                <p>The morning papers of London are the great organs and interpreters of public
                    opinion in England. Of these, the Host is the exponent of the high Tory
                    aristocracy, and eminently the organ of the <hi rend="italic">beau monde</hi>.
                    More than half its readers take it up without reference to its political
                    lucubrations. Its leading articles, or editorials, as we call them in America,
                    are characterized by a rabid spirit of bitter and<cb/> unscrupulous personality.
                    It is the unbending supporter of all those traditions of the aristocratical
                    oligarchy, which are so fast melting away under the rays of modern
                    enlightenment. The columns of this journal are open to the contributions of
                    those members of the rigid Conservative party, who think they can more
                    effectually give vent to their opinions and feelings in that way than in the
                    House; and these diatribes are issued by the fashionable journal under editorial
                    responsibility. Some of the most virulent of these personalities are understood
                    to proceed from the retired Secretary of the Admiralty of the Tories, the Right
                    Honorable John Wilson Croker.</p>

                <p>This gentleman, who is now enjoying the <hi rend="italic">otium cum
                        dignitate</hi> upon a large pension, to which he became entitled on
                    retiring, after above twenty years spent in the public service, belongs to that
                    class which, in England, are somewhat illiberally stigmatized by the title of
                    political adventurers, or trading politicians. He was originally at the Irish
                    bar. A practitioner at the Irish bar, was on the point of our pen; but, alas! we
                    forgot the wide and mournful distinction between <hi rend="italic">simply being
                        at the bar</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">practicing</hi> there. Mr. Croker was
                    at the bar, and further we cannot with truth say. He was known in Dublin chiefly
                    by the publication of a lively satirical criticism in verse on the drama called
                    "Familiar Epistles to George Frederick Jones," who was then proprietor of the
                    Dublin Theatre. Having succeeded in getting the favor of an aristocratic patron,
                    he was returned to the Imperial Parliament for one of the nomination boroughs,
                    where he soon signalized himself by his advocacy of his Royal Highness the Duke
                    of York, in the delicate investigation promoted by Colonel Wondle; which,
                    notwithstanding the clear truth and justice of the case, ended in the
                    discomfiture and ultimate ruin of that officer, and the promotion of the Irish
                    member to the office of Secretary of the Admiralty.</p>

                <p>The more serious of the political effusions from the pen of this writer, find a
                    place in the Quarterly Review; and those of mere temporary and passing interest,
                    appear in the columns of the Morning Post.* </p>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>

                <fw type="footnote" place="bottom">*Mr Croker is also known in literature by his edition of Boswell's Life of
                    Johnson; by which, however, he added very little to his literary reputation.</fw>

            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>