<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="rut.00021">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">"The Social Revolutionist"</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
                <author xml:id="unk">Unknown</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="jyc">Jonathan Y. Cheng</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="slg">Samantha L. Gilmore</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>University of Texas at Austin</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2014</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>rut.00021</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>kprice@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Ed-Folsom@uiowa.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>bbarney2@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain
                        exceptions, public domain works may be freely copied or used in the creation
                        of derivative works without permission, or authorization, of the former
                        copyright owners.</p>
                    <p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and
                        is governed by a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"
                            >Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</ref> (CC BY
                        4.0).</p>
                    <p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted
                        by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                <title><!-- check rut find aid--> </title>
                    <idno type="callno"><!--<idno type="callno"></idno>--></idno>
                <date notBefore="1857-07" notAfter="1892-03-26">After July 1857</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="rut">Special Collections and University Archives, Rutgers
                        University Libraries, Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey </orgName>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from our digital image of original.</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl type="base" xml:id="r1">
                    <author>Unknown</author>
                    <title level="j">"The Social Revolutionist"</title>
                    <publisher>The Rising Star Association</publisher>
                    <pubPlace cert="medium">Greenville, Ohio</pubPlace>
                    <biblScope type="vol">4</biblScope>
                    <biblScope type="num">1</biblScope>
                    <date when="1857-07">July 1857</date>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="h1" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h2" scribeRef="#unk" medium="typescript"/>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#slg" when="2019-10-08">proofed</change>
            <change who="#jyc" when="2014-11-18">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="marginalia">
        <body>
            <div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="rut_nhg.00031.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <note xml:id="n001" place="top right"><handShift new="#h1"/>9</note>
                <fw type="header" place="top left"><hi rend="underline">Vol. IV. No. 1.]</hi></fw>
                <fw type="date" place="top right"><hi rend="underline">[July, 1857.</hi></fw>
                <head type="main-authorial"><hi rend="smallcaps">THE SOCIAL
                    REVOLUTIONIST;</hi></head>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">A MEDIUM</hi></p>

                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">FOR THE FREE DISCUSSION OF GENERAL PRINCIPLES AND PRACTICAL
                        MEASURES,</hi></p>

                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">PERTAINING TO</hi></p>
                <note xml:id="n002" place="right"><handShift new="#h1"/><del rend="overstrike"
                        hand="#h1">30</del>
                    <list>
                        <item>30&#8212;</item>
                        <item> 40</item>
                        <item><milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short"/></item>
                        <item>1400</item>
                        <item> 8</item>
                        <item><milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short"/></item>
                        <item>1120.0</item>
                    </list></note>

                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">HUMAN PROGRESS AND GENERAL WELL-BEING.</hi></p>
                
                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>

                <p>The cause of truth is best promoted by free inquiry. Error
                        alone fears investigation.</p>
                
                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>

                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">CONDUCTED BY JOHN PATTERSON.</hi></p>

                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">CONTRIBUTORS</hi>.&#8212;A. Cridge, Anne Denton Cridge, Wm.
                    Denton, T.P. Wright, J.H Cook, J.W. Towner, W.A. Steere, Francis Barry, J.M.
                    Stahl, J.B. Wolff, J.P. Davis, Joseph Treat, Mary A. Chilton, Jennie G. Adams,
                    C. Sweet Towner, D. Colburn Bush, C.M. Overton, Lily White, P.I. Blacker, La Roy
                    Sunderland, J.K. Moore, J.R. Monroe.</p>
                
                <note xml:id="n003" place="right"><handShift new="#h1"/><list>
                        <item>28</item>
                        <item> 40</item>
                        <item><milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short"/></item>
                        <item>1120</item>
                    </list></note>

                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>

                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">PUBLISHED BY THE RISING STAR ASSOCIATION.</hi></p>

                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">FOR SALE BY M. BLY, 160 VINE STREET, CINCINNATI; BELA MARSH,
                        15 FRANKLIN ST., BOSTON; C. BLANCHARD, 76 NASSAU ST., AND S.T. MUNSON, NO. 5
                        GT. JONES ST., NEW YORK.</hi></p>

                <p>Terms, $1 a year in Advance, or five Copies for $4; Specimen Nos. 10 cts.</p>

                <p>☞ Our Post Office Address:&#8212;Greenville, Darke Co., Ohio.☜</p>



                <pb xml:id="leaf001v" facs="rut_nhg.00032.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <div2>
                    <head type="main-authorial"><hi rend="smallcaps">THE SOCIAL
                        REVOLUTIONIST;</hi></head>
                    <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
                    <lg type="letter">
                        <head type="main-authorial"><hi rend="smallcaps">MY MARRIED
                            LIFE.</hi></head>
                        <head type="sub"><hi rend="smallcaps">LETTER II.</hi></head>
                        <l>"O think not that my eyes are dry,</l>
                        <l rend="indented1">Because you mark no falling tears;</l>
                        <l>There flows a river deep and dark,</l>
                        <l rend="indented1">Whose waters ebb not with the years.</l>
                        <l>O think not that my lips are mute,</l>
                        <l rend="indented1">Because you hear no spoken word;</l>
                        <l>Full-freighted with the tones of grief,</l>
                        <l rend="indented1">I hear a voice you never heard."</l>
                    </lg>
                    
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">MY DEAR FRIEND:&#8212;</hi>You may have noticed how very
                        strong the <hi rend="smallcaps">AFFECTIONAL ELEMENT</hi> is the constitution
                        of my nature; but you may never know how much I have suffered during the
                        past thirty years, for the want of a conjugal, or as the New Churchmen would
                        say, a conjugal companion; not merely a wife, but a <hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >COMPANION FOR MY SOUL</hi>. The degree of <hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >LONELINESS</hi> desolation, and suffering, which each one must endure,
                        who finds himself thus conditioned for life, will depend upon the
                        temperament, education, and numerous constitutional susceptibilities over
                        which we can have but little control.&#8212; Hence, the object of each one
                        should be, to familiarize the mind with the laws of his own nature, and
                        arrange all eternal persons and things accordingly, as far as it may be in
                        our power to do so.</p>
                    
                    <p> The great desire I felt, to avoid all mistakes in my choice of a wife, kept
                        me from committing myself in matrimony until my twenty-sixth year. AT this
                        time, I was a clergyman in the service of a sectarian Church. In the summer
                        of 1828, meeting with an old minister at one of our Annual Conferences, whom
                        I had long known and confided in as a paternal friend, he put the following
                        question to me:&#8212;"Brother S.," said he, "have you found your rib
                        yet?"&#8212;referring to Gen. ii. 22. My answer being in the negative, he
                        then proceeded to give me a description of a beautiful young sister in his
                        parish who had expressed to him a preference for marrying a clergyman, and
                        he thought her personal attractions, piety, education, and parentage such as
                        would be highly gratifying to me, and so he invited me to make him a
                        ministerial visit, when he would have the pleasure of giving me and
                        introduction to her. His glowing account of the young lady, seemed to
                        approach very near to my <hi rend="smallcaps">IDEAL</hi>; and the thought
                        that there was a probability that I should find what I wanted, when
                        permitted to behold her face in the course of a few months, filled my heart
                        with emotions of joy unknown to me before. He was a good man, one in whom
                        I</p>
                </div2>

                <fw type="footer" place="bottom">VOL. IV. NO. I.&#8212;July 1857.</fw>
                <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="rut_nhg.00033.jpg" type="recto"/>
                <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="smallcaps">FREE LOVE.</hi></fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">7</fw>
                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
                <div2>
                    <p>If this is true Amativeness, it must also be true of all the other faculties.
                        We must live on hermit's fare, for Alimentiveness, too, must be equally
                        unfit to determine what food our bodies need. Reason must be "carnal," and
                        therefore unfit to be used in matters which concern the important mater of
                        the soul's salvation, and the only safety or truth must be found in
                        unconditional submission to the teachings of the Holy and Infallible
                        Catholic Church!</p>
                    <p>Thus reasoned our late co-workers, the Nichols. <hi rend="smallcaps">GRANTING
                            THE PREMISES</hi>, as regards the function of Amativeness, this
                        reasoning is without a flaw. It was an artful dodge, quite worthy of a
                        practiced and accomplished Jesuit, to begin by getting the notion well
                        grounded in the minds of the apostles of Individual Freedom, "destinies
                        proportioned to attractions," etc., before the could see where it ledl and
                        having them once fairly in the vortex of this deadly whirlpool, their
                        descent was rapid and certain.</p>
                    <p>Those who believe in <hi rend="smallcaps">CRUSHING</hi>, instead of <hi
                            rend="smallcaps">DIRECTING</hi> and admitting of a wholesome and
                        spontaneous activity, would confer a benefit to the cause of Reform by
                        leaving its ranks, and going where they belong, as Dr. and Mrs. N. have
                        done.</p>
                    <p>It maybe objected that I am advocating unlimited activity of the animal
                        faculties, irrespective of the dictates of reason and experience. This is,
                        however, not my position. I believe, however, that these latter means are
                        sufficiently competent to decide upon the amount of activity that each
                        faculty should be allowed. Reason would naturally infer that every faculty
                        of our nature should be called in to activity oftener that <hi
                            rend="smallcaps">ONCE IN THREE YEARS</hi>, which is as often as even <hi
                            rend="smallcaps">HEALTHY</hi> women can bear and nurse children with
                        impunity. <span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="b001" from="#b001"
                            to="#b002"/> Experience of evil resulting from its over activity would,
                        if attended to, prevent any serious harm. For one man to lay down iron,
                        arbitrary rules for another, either in respect to eating, sleeping, or the
                        amative function, is as absurd as to prescribe the size of a garment, or the
                        length to which we should be allowed to grow. There is an <hi
                            rend="smallcaps">INDIVIDUALITY</hi> about these things that should be
                        respected. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">True reformers might occupy
                            themselves more appropriately and usefully than in increasing the number
                            of <hi rend="smallcaps">STRAIGHT JACKETS</hi> for mankind, which are
                            already sufficiently numerous.</hi><anchor xml:id="b002"/> If they need
                        such things themselves, by all means let them use them; but excuse others
                        who have full (or even partial) possession of their faculties, from being
                        hampered in any such restraints. Such despotism, like that of religious
                        creeds, is far more insufferable and pernicious than that of the civil law.
                        I go for freedom in <hi rend="smallcaps">FACT</hi>. </p>
                </div2>
                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
                <div2>
                    <head type="main-authorial"><hi rend="smallcaps">EXCLUSIVENESS IN
                        LOVE.</hi></head>
                    <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">FRIEND PATTERSON</hi>:&#8212;As the list of Varietists
                        has been called for, and I feel a deep interest in all that is going on in
                        the world of reform, it has given rise in my mind to many serious
                        reflections of which I feel strongly impressed to speak.</p>
                    <p>In the March No. of the S. R. you say: "I did list those amongst Free Lovers
                        who believe in exclusive dual union, but ignore legal enactments&#8212;but I
                        did not mean by that to commit myself to this doctrine as real Free Lovers,"
                        &amp;c.</p>
                    <p>To which I will reply, for myself only, as I cannot speak for another, thus
                        far I have never loved but <hi rend="smallcaps">ONE</hi> individual at the
                        same time&#8212;and, although my name is on the list of Free Lovers, I
                        presume that you and many others consider me not one, though to me it looks
                        different. I am <hi rend="smallcaps">FREE</hi> to love the one, and cannot
                        be <hi rend="smallcaps">COMPELLED</hi> to love more.&#8212; <pb
                            xml:id="leaf002v" facs="rut_nhg.00034.jpg" type="verso"/>
                        <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="smallcaps">SOCIAL
                                REVOLUTIONIST.</hi></fw>
                        <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">8</fw>
                        <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/> Not but that I am free and
                        willing to love many, or any number, but as yet I have not been able to
                        discover within my own heart the principle of variety&#8212;not that I
                        object to the principle or sentiment. O, no! It is beautiful and truthful to
                        those who feel it in their souls to be a truth. But such in my estimation
                        are no more free than those of the one love, as they are compelled by their
                        very <hi rend="smallcaps">NECESSITY</hi> of their unfolding natures to love
                        the <hi rend="smallcaps">MANY</hi>. And now, which is free, the one that is
                        drawn and bound to the one love by the necessity of his own nature, growth,
                        and being, or the one that is compelled by the same principle to love the
                        many? To me, they are both bound and free, on one and the same
                        principle.</p>
                    <p>Were I now to send in my name as a Free Lover you might hesitate whether or
                        not to accept me as such with my one "little love." But as we are
                        progressive beings, by the time the list is fairly in circulation I may grow
                        into the truth of variety by meeting with individuals I never before
                        saw&#8212;the same is variety. By what we now are, we know not what we shall
                        be. Variety in love is a truth to those who feel its potency: the exclusive,
                        the same. We shall probably grow out of one into the other, and I have no
                        choice which. I am willing to leave it to nature and destiny. I have no <hi
                            rend="smallcaps">BELIEF</hi> to fasten to on <hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >THAT</hi>, or any other subject but leave my mind open and free to the
                        reception of truth as it presents itself to my understanding. I can
                        fellowship the variety love with the same warmth of soul as the exclusive or
                        one lover&#8212;so that you will discover that I am not a <hi
                            rend="smallcaps">CLOSE COMMUNIIONIST</hi>; nor do I feel like contending
                        about the <hi rend="smallcaps">TRINITY</hi>, <hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >DUALITY</hi>, or <hi rend="smallcaps">UNITY</hi> [one-ity] of the
                        Godhead, and care not whether persons worship "<hi rend="smallcaps">ONE OR
                            TWENTY GODS</hi>."</p>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">TOLERATION</hi> is the motto of all true and loving
                        souls, the only principle that can possibly save social bodies or societies
                        from plunging into the much dreaded vortex of Sectarianism. Yours for
                        toleration and faith in humanity,</p>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">WAUKEGAN, ILL., May 16, 1857. CHARLOTTE H.
                        BOWEN.</hi></p>
                </div2>
                <div2>
                    <head type="main-authorial"><hi rend="smallcaps">VARIETY IN LOVE.</hi></head>
                    <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">BY J. R. MONROE.</hi></p>
                    <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="b003" from="#b003" to="#b004"/>
                    <p>That variety in love is, or would be, natural and generally prevail, I have
                        not the least doubt. It seems to be a question with many whether new loves
                        would displace old ones, or whether the tendency would not be to enhance,
                        intensify, and purify the old ones.&#8212; As a general question, or as to
                        the general tendency of this, I have no doubts. There may be loves of some
                        character or extent that would be dropped or changed on finding new loves of
                        a higher, purer, and more <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">happyifying</hi>
                        character, some that are more <hi rend="smallcaps">REAL</hi>; for it must be
                        obvious to the close investigating socialist, that there are many that <hi
                            rend="smallcaps">APPEAR</hi> to be love-relations which are merely
                        accidental, or entered into from sinister motives, motives other than love
                        or real attraction. But in freedom, adaptation, attraction, is the thing to
                        bring the opposite sexes together. As far as my expereience and observation
                        extend, I am fully satisfied that where a great degree of freedom obtains,
                        the <hi rend="smallcaps">ONE LOVE</hi> will be the exception, and <hi
                            rend="smallcaps">VARIETY</hi> or <hi rend="smallcaps">MANY LOVES</hi>
                        will be the rule.</p>
                    <p>For various reasons I believe new loves will improve and intensify old ones,
                        and perpetuate or extend them. One obvious reason for this is the culture,
                        growth, and expansion of our love-nature, consequent on having a variety of
                        objects to love; and of course, all loves must be different to some extent
                        in degree and kind, as the organizations, surroundings, and influences of
                        all the different lovers will differ to some extent. Thus acting variously
                        upon us, all the activities of our whole love-nature will be drawn out, and
                        our <anchor xml:id="b004"/>
                        <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="rut_nhg.00035.jpg" type="recto"/>
                        <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="smallcaps">FREE LOVE.</hi></fw>
                        <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">9</fw>
                        <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>
                        <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="b005" from="#b005" to="#b006"
                        />capacity or capability to love will be enlarged, and at the same time our
                        attractiveness or lovableness will be increased. Another reason is, by
                        loving many our love-nature is not only strengthened, and so our capacity to
                        love more, but we are still becoming ourselves more lovable. But our loves
                        being more diffused, the points of attraction between any two would be less
                        likely to be absorbed, or at least, not so soon as though we had but the one
                        lover. But our time, attentions, and love-manifestations being divided
                        between many, the points of attraction between any two of course, to say the
                        least, will not so soon be absorbed. To illustrate; Suppose I love another
                        who loves me; in time I find another one to love, a dozen, or twenty, and
                        she finds as many more. Well, these loves all differing one from another, of
                        course by this means many points of attraction in my love-nature become
                        active, and hers in like manner; and now we come round together again. But
                        how is this, we still find each other more attractive that before? Now I am
                        so happy, I exclaim, I thought I knew you before, but I am continually
                        discovering something new, some still more attractive points in your
                        character, how fortunate that we ever came together! What a heaven it is, to
                        be thus continually finding something new, something still more attractive,
                        instructive, and intensely happifying in your nature! How beautifully we
                        seem to be adapted to help and happify each other! To all this, and more,
                        she readily and joyfully responds, exclaiming, this sis just as I feel
                        towards you; I find I am just beginning to appreciate you. What a world of
                        delights is ours! What mines of wealth are continually unfolding to our
                        enraptured gaze!</p>
                    <anchor xml:id="b006"/>
                    <p>But the secret of this is, we have both been students in this beautiful
                        school of freedom, we are being more integrally developed, we have been
                        following our attractions without hindrance; we are coming to a wholeness of
                        life that we knew not of, nor could we know only in freedom. We are now, as
                        it were, new beings, <hi rend="smallcaps">NEW LOVERS</hi>. In addition to
                        the former points of attraction that drew us together, there are now on both
                        sides many more attractive features that have been brought into activity by
                        our many and variously acting love-relations. So then all can see the sphere
                        of our love-activities, is widening, is expanding. The more we love, the
                        more we can love: the more we give, the more we have to give. The more our
                        love-nature is cultivated, the more active it is, the more capable, to give.
                        The more our love-nature is cultivated, the more active it is, the more
                        capable, the stronger, and more powerful it becomes. But on the other hand,
                        in marriage of whatever kind&#8212;<hi rend="smallcaps">LEGAL MATING</hi> or
                        what not, (for it is all about the same,) the tendency is to absorb the
                        points of attraction; and then repression comes in with all its chilling and
                        deadening influences&#8212;a coldness, an apathy, an indifference is
                        engendered between the two, thus shut out from the world; no chance for
                        growth or development for either. In more cases, their condition becomes
                        still more intolerable, when they might in freedom become still more
                        attractive to each other by the extending and widening growth of each, and
                        thus be enabled to bless each other and all as far as their influence may be
                        felt.</p>
                    <p>Marriage, mating, or the one love, hinders growth, development, and
                        happiness. And besides all this, it actually produces the positive hells
                        that are peculiar to marriage, the thousandth part of whose miseries and
                        damning curses have never been told. The thought of retaining a love that
                        blesses and happifies us is certainly a pleasing one, and the way to do this
                        most surely is <hi rend="smallcaps">VARIETY IN LOVE</hi> om freedom. For in
                        this way we are continually making ourselves more attractive to all we can
                        affinitize with, are adapted to, or can love. the points of attraction not
                        being fully absorbed, there is a life, a sprightliness, a vivacity, a
                        brilliancy, in our loves, that the really married, mated ones cannot know;
                        or if they happen to feel something of it when they first come together, it
                        soon flees from them. The rose is gone, but the thorn is left behind.</p>
                    <span rend="bracket-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="b007" from="#b007" to="#b008"/>
                    <span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="b009" from="#b009" to="#b010"/>
                    <p>But finally, it is not so very important whether we retain for a long or a
                        short time the love of others; so that we enjoy all that is for us in a
                        glorious and up-building freedom. <anchor xml:id="b008"/>
                        <anchor xml:id="b010"/>
                        <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="rut_nhg.00036.jpg" type="verso"/>
                        <fw type="header" place="top"><hi rend="smallcaps">SOCIAL
                                REVOLUTIONIST.</hi></fw>
                        <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">10</fw>
                        <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-full"/>For one, I am entirely of
                        the faith, that variety in love will bring to poor, crushed humanity a
                        thousand untold blessings; and that the whole tendency of the entire
                        activity of our whole love-nature, in <hi rend="smallcaps">FREEDOM</hi>,
                        will be purifying, refining, elevating, ennobling, and intensely happifying.
                        Let us have the conditions, and I fear not, but hope everything good. We
                        want Spontaneity, the broadest Freedom, and Toleration to match it.</p>
                </div2>
                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
                <div2>
                    <head><hi rend="smallcaps">CAUSTIC FOR FREE LOVERS.</hi></head>
                    <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">BY A. HUNTER.</hi></p>
                    <p>Many articles having appeared in the Social Revolutionist on the subject of
                        "Free Love" my object, in the present paper, is to make a few comments on
                        extracts from some of these articles.</p>
                    <p>A.S. Davis defines love to be an "involuntary action of the mind," and J.
                        Patterson (Vol. III., No.1., p.8) accepts the definition. He says, "I am
                        much pleased with your definition of love, I could no have made it better
                        myself." All love, according to this definition, as it is "involuntary,"
                        must not only be essentially free, but uncontrollable. All involuntary
                        action exhibited in the mental or physical phenomena of human beings are
                        beyond the control of the individual. We are not capable then of directing,
                        modifying, or extinguishing this purely mental attribute&#8212;this
                        sentiment, feeling or emotion. Peculiar organizations may limit it, but
                        conventionalities cannot enslave it. As organization varies among
                        individuals this "involuntary action" is more remarkable in some than
                        others. The natural instinct of a mother makes it peculiarly strong for her
                        offspring. How could you enslave this sentiment in the mother?&#8212;how
                        prevent its free action? Try to circumscribe it and it becomes the more
                        intense. So is it with all pure loves. I am taken with a severe "involuntary
                        action of the mind"&#8212;my other faculties tell me that it exists&#8212;I
                        know it does. Can I prevent its involuntary existence? And if I cannot, who
                        can? Then if it cannot be prevented, this is Free Love, and I enjoy it. Why?
                        Not because I have a right to it, but because I cannot help it.</p>
                    <p>If this "involuntary action" find its affinities among the higher attributes
                        of the mind then we have "Free Love" of a higher order, exhibiting a purely
                        moral aspect. If among the lower, or that which is common to all animated
                        creatures, then we have "Free Love" manifesting sexual symptoms. In the one
                        case our love is satisfied with reciprocal intellectual or moral enjoyment,
                        but in the other it demands the gratification of the sexual passion. The
                        latter love is an "involuntary" exaltation of venereal desires&#8212;an
                        instinctive sentiment. The former is a concentration of the nobler qualities
                        of the mind&#8212;an intellectual sentiment, peculiar to man.</p>
                    <p>There are various types of love just as there are various grades of
                        intellectual development, and various characteristics of organization. I
                        have said that peculiar organization limits the extent of love's action. It
                        does more it fixes its character. An idiot is capable of loving intensely,
                        but his organization is such that his love must necessarily be of the
                        instinctive or animal kind. Intellectuality is wanting, and therefore the
                        higher degrees of love are absent. The love of the savage is proportioned to
                        the development of his mind. and so in civilized society we find every
                        degree of love, from the lowest sensual to the highest spiritual. Love
                        demands in return love its kind. The sensualist cannot feel, and therefore
                        cannot enjoy the love of a highly cultivated and virtuous mind. He seeks
                        enjoyment among those of his class. He practices free sexual intercourse,
                        and wallows in the mire of lust without restraint. Talk to him of "Free
                        Love" and he will</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
