<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen
RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"
?>
<?oxygen
SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"
?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="bmr.00014">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">The Ruins, or, Meditation on the Revolutions of Empires</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
                <author xml:id="cv">C.F. Volney</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ano">Alejandro Omidsalar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mc">Matt Cohen</persName>
                <persName xml:id="as">Ashlyn Stewart</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>University of Texas at Austin</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>2015</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>bmr.00014</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>kprice@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Ed-Folsom@uiowa.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>bbarney2@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain exceptions, public domain works may be 
                        freely copied or used in the creation of derivative works without permission, or authorization, of the former copyright owners.</p>
                    <p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and is governed by a
                        <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                            Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License
                        </ref>
                        (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                    <p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted 
                        by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author sameAs="#ww">Whitman, Walt</author>
                    <title>Excerpt from Volney's Ruins</title>
                    <idno type="callno">RBR 901 V88rE</idno>
                    <date notBefore="1890-01-01" notAfter="1892-03-26">1890 or later</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="bmr">Bryn Mawr College Library Holdings of Whitman Books, Canady Library, Bryn Mawr College</orgName>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from digital images of the original item.</note>
                </bibl>
                <bibl type="base" xml:id="r1">
                    <author>C.F. Volney</author>
                    <title level="a">The Ruins, or, Meditation on the Revolutions of Empires: and the Law of Nature</title>
                    <date>1890</date>
                    <publisher>Peter Eckler</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                    <biblScope unit="pp">title page, 26, 35, 45, 53, 64, 66, 79, 93, 94, 97, 106, 107, 136, 166-168</biblScope>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
                <handNotes>
                    <handNote xml:id="h1" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
                    <handNote xml:id="h2" scribeRef="#ww" medium="ink"/>
                    <handNote xml:id="h3" scribeRef="#cv" medium="typescript"/>
                </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change when="2022-04-14" who="#as">Regularized Name</change>
                <change when="2015-10-24" who="#ano">Transcribed; encoded</change>
                <change when="2015-11-04" who="#mc">Proofed</change>
            </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="marginalia">
        <front>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="bmr_nhg.00363.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <titlePage>
            <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h2" xml:id="a1" from="#a1" to="#a2"/>
            <note type="authorial" place="top" resp="#h2">
                <hi rend="underline">Walt</hi> <hi rend="underline">Whitman</hi> 1890<lb/>
                This translation seems to have been either<lb/>
                made by Joel Barlow, or supervised by him, in<lb/>
                Paris, and favored by Volney.<lb/>
            </note><anchor xml:id="a2"/>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart type="main"><handShift new="#h3"/>THE RUINS,
                    OR, MEDITATION ON THE
                    REVOLUTIONS OF EMPIRES:
                    AND
                    THE LAW OF NATURE,</titlePart>
                </docTitle>
                <byline>BY<docAuthor> C.F. VOLNEY</docAuthor>,<lb/>
                    C<hi rend="smallcaps">OMTE ET</hi> P<hi rend="smallcaps">AIR DE</hi> F<hi rend="smallcaps">RANCE</hi>, C<hi rend="smallcaps">OMMANDEUR DE LA</hi> L<hi rend="smallcaps">&#201;GION D'</hi>H<hi rend="smallcaps">ONNEUR</hi>, M<hi rend="smallcaps">EMBRE 
                    DE L</hi>'A<hi rend="smallcaps">CAD&#201;MIE</hi> F<hi rend="smallcaps">RAN&#199;AISE, ET DE PLUSIEURS AUTRES</hi> S<hi rend="smallcaps">OCI&#201;T&#201;S SAVANTES.</hi> 
                    D<hi rend="smallcaps">EPUTY TO THE</hi> N<hi rend="smallcaps">ATIONAL</hi> A<hi rend="smallcaps">SSEMBLY OF 1789, AND AUTHOR OF</hi> "T<hi rend="smallcaps">RAVELS IN</hi> 
                    E<hi rend="smallcaps">GYPT AND</hi> S<hi rend="smallcaps">YRIA</hi>," " N<hi rend="smallcaps">EW</hi> R<hi rend="smallcaps">ESEARCHES ON</hi> A<hi rend="smallcaps">NCIENT</hi> H<hi rend="smallcaps">ISTORY," ETC.</hi></byline>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h3">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">TO WHICH IS ADDED</hi>
                    VOLNEY'S ANSWER TO DR. PRIESTLY, A BIOGRAPHICAL NOTICE
                    BY COUNT DARU, AND THE ZODIACAL SIGNS AND
                    CONSTELLATIONS BY THE EDITOR.
                </note>
                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short"/>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h3">I will cherish in remembrance the love of man, I will employ myself on
                the means of effecting good for him, and build my own happiness on
                the promotion of his.&#8212;<hi rend="italic">Volney</hi>.</note>
                <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short"/>
                <docImprint>
                    <pubPlace>NEW YORK:</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>PETER ECKLER, 35 F<hi rend="smallcaps">ULTON</hi> S<hi rend="smallcaps">TREET</hi>.</publisher><lb/>
                    <docDate>1890</docDate>.
                </docImprint>
            </titlePage>
        </front>
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="bmr_nhg.00353.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">26</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top">THE RUINS OF EMPIRES.</fw>
            <p>family against family, tribe against tribe; and the earth is 
            become a theatre of blood, of discord, and of rapine. By 
            ignorance and cupidity, a secret war, fermenting in the bosom 
            of every state, has separated citizen from citizen; and the 
            same society has divided itself into oppressors and oppressed, 
            into masters and slaves; by these, the heads of a nation, 
            sometimes insolent and audacious, have forged its chains 
            within its own bowels; and mercenary avarice has founded 
            political despotism. Sometimes, hypocritical and cunning, 
            they have called from heaven a lying power, and a sacrilegious 
            yoke; and credulous cupidity has founded religious despotism. 
            By these have been perverted the ideas of good and evil, just 
            and unjust, vice and virtue; and nations have wandered in a 
            labyrinth of errors and calamities.</p>
        <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="b1" from="#b1" to="#b2"/>
            <p>The cupidity of man and his ignorance,&#8212;these are the evil 
            genii which have wasted the earth! These are the decrees 
            of fate which have overthrown empires! These are the 
            celestial anathemas which have smitten these walls once so 
            glorious, and converted the splendor of a populous city into 
            a solitude of mourning and of ruins! But as in the bosom of 
            man have sprung all the evils which have afflicted his life, 
            there he also is to seek and to find their remedies.</p>
            <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short"/>
            <anchor xml:id="b2"/>
            <div1 type="chapter">
                <head>CHAPTER IX.<lb/><hi rend="smallcaps">ORIGIN OF GOVERNMENT AND LAWS</hi>.</head>
                <p>In fact, it soon happened that men, fatigued with the evils 
                they reciprocally inflicted, began to sigh for peace; and 
                reflecting on their misfortunes and the causes of them, 
                they said:</p>
                <p>"We are mutually injuring each other by our passions; 
                and, aiming to grasp every thing, we hold nothing. What 
                one seizes to-day, another takes to-morrow, and our cupidity 
                reacts upon ourselves. Let us establish judges, who shall 
                arbitrate our rights, and settle our differences. When the</p>
            </div1>
        <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="bmr_nhg.00354.jpg" type="recto"/>
        <div1>
        <fw type="header" place="top">THE RUINS OF EMPIRES.</fw>
        <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">35</fw>
            <p>name of <hi rend="italic">aristocracy</hi>, the state was tormented by the passions of the wealthy and the great.</p>
        <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="c1" from="#c1" to="#c2"/>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Sacred impostors</hi>, in other countries, tending by other 
        means to the same object, abused the credulity of the ignorant. 
        In the gloom of their temples, behind the curtain of the 
        altar, they made their gods act and speak; gave forth oracles, 
        worked miracles, ordered sacrifices, levied offerings, 
        prescribed endowments; and, under the names of theocracy and 
        of religion, the state became tormented by the passions of the 
        priests.</p>
            <p>Sometimes a nation, weary of its dissensions or of its 
        tyrants, to lessen the sources of evil, submitted to a single<anchor xml:id="c2"/> 
        master; but if it limited his powers, his sole aim was to 
        enlarge them; if it left them indefinite, he abused the trust 
        confided to him; and, under the name of monarchy, the state 
        was tormented by the passions of kings and princes.</p>
            <p>Then the factions, availing themselves of the general 
        discontent, flattered the people with the hope of a better master; 
        dealt out gifts and promises, deposed the despot to take his 
        place; and their contests for the succession, or its partition, 
        tormented the state with the disorders and devastations of 
        civil war.</p>
            <p>In fine, among these rivals, one more adroit, or more 
        fortunate, gained the ascendency, and concentrated all power 
        within himself. By a strange phenomenon, a single individual 
        mastered millions of his equals, against their will and without 
        their consent; and the art of tyranny sprung also from 
        cupidity.</p>
            <p>In fact, observing the spirit of egotism which incessantly 
        divides mankind, the ambitious man fomented it with dexterity, 
        flattered the vanity of one, excited the jealousy of another, 
        favored the avarice of this, inflamed the resentment of that, 
        and irritated the passions of all; then, placing in opposition 
        their interests and prejudices, he sowed divisions and hatreds, 
        promised to the poor the spoils of the rich, to the rich the 
        subjection of the poor; threatened one man by another, this 
        class by that; and insulating all by distrust, created his 
        strength out of their weakness, and imposed the yoke of 
        opinion, which they mutually riveted on each other. With the 
        army he levied contributions, and with contributions he disposed</p>
        </div1>
        <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="bmr_nhg.00355.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <div1>
                <fw type="header" place="top">THE RUINS OF EMPIRES.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">45</fw>
                <p>whimsical and capricious, is angered or appeased as a man: 
           that he loves and hates alternately; that he punishes or 
           favors; that, weak or wicked, he broods over his hatred; that, 
           contradictory or perfidious, he lays snares to entrap; that he 
           punishes the evils he permits; that he foresees but hinders 
           not crimes; that, like a corrupt judge, he is bribed by offerings; 
           like an ignorant despot, he makes laws and revokes 
           them; that, like a savage tyrant, he grants or resumes favors 
           without reason, and can only be appeased by servility. Ah! 
           now I know the lying spirit of man! Contemplating the 
           picture which he hath drawn of the Divinity: No, said I, it is not 
           God who hath made man after the image of God; but man 
           hath made God after the image of man; he hath given him 
           his own mind, clothed him with his own propensities; 
           ascribed to him his own judgments. And when in this 
           medley he finds the contradiction of his own principles, with 
           hypocritical humility, he imputes weakness to his reason, and 
           names the absurdities of his own mind the mysteries of God.</p>
                <p>He hath said, God is immutable, yet he offers prayers to 
           change him; he hath pronounced him incomprehensible, yet 
           he interprets him without ceasing.</p>
           <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="d1" from="#d1" to="#d2"/>
                <p>Imposters have arisen on the earth who have called themselves 
           the confidants of God; and, erecting themselves into 
           teachers of the people, have opened the ways of falsehood 
           and iniquity; they have ascribed merit to practices indifferent 
           or ridiculous; they have supposed a virtue in certain postures, 
           in pronouncing certain words, articulating certain names; 
           they have transformed into a crime the eating of certain 
           meats, the drinking of certain liquors, on one day rather than 
           another. The Jew would rather die than labor on the <anchor xml:id="d2"/>
           sabbath; the Persian would endure suffocation, before he 
           would blow the fire with his breath; the Indian places 
           supreme perfection in besmearing himself with cow-dung, and 
           pronouncing mysteriously the word A&#251;m; <ref target="#n1" xml:id="ref1">&#42;</ref> the Mussulman</p>
           <note xml:id="n1" target="#ref1" type="footnote" place="bottom">
              * This word is, in the religion of the Hindoos, a sacred emblem of the Divinity. 
           It is only to be pronounced in secret, without being heard by any one. It is 
           formed of three letters, of which the first, <hi rend="italic">a</hi>, signifies the principal of all, the 
           creator, Brama; the second, &#251;, the conservator, Vichenou; and the last, <hi rend="italic">m</hi>, the 
           destroyer, who puts an end to all, Chiven. It is pronounced like the monosyllable 
           &#244;m, and expresses the unity of those three Gods. The idea is precisely that 
           of the Alpha and Omega mentioned in the New Testament.</note>
            </div1>
            <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="bmr_nhg.00356.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <div1 type="chapter">
                <fw type="header" place="top">THE RUINS OF EMPIRES.</fw>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">53</fw>
                <head>CHAPTER XIII.<lb/><hi rend="smallcaps">WILL THE HUMAN RACE IMPROVE</hi>?</head>
                <p>At these words, oppressed with the painful sentiment with 
            which their severity overwhelmed me: Woe to the 
            nations! cried I, melting in tears; woe to myself! Ah! 
            now it is that I despair of the happiness of man! Since his 
            <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="f1" from="#f1" to="#f2"/>
            miseries proceed from his heart; since the remedy is in his 
            own power, woe for ever to his existence! Who, indeed will 
            ever be able to restrain the lust of wealth in the strong and 
            powerful? Who can enlighten the ignorance of the weak? 
            Who can teach the multitude to know their rights, and force 
            their chiefs to perform their duties? Thus the race of man is 
            always doomed to suffer! Thus the individual will not cease <anchor xml:id="f2"/>
            to oppress the individual, a nation to attack a nation; and 
            days of prosperity, of glory, for these regions, shall never 
            return. Alas! conquerors will come; they will drive out the 
            oppressors, and fix themselves in their place; but, inheriting 
            their power, they will inherit their rapacity; and the earth 
            will have changed tyrants, without changing the tyranny.</p>
                <p>Then, turning to the Genius, I exclaimed:</p>
                <p>O Genius, despair hath settled on my soul. Knowing the</p>
                <note xml:id="n2" type="footnote" place="bottom" resp="#h3">
                    engaging in a war for them, and that at a time when revolution in their own 
                    country was just at its commencement. A man, who perceived the true nature 
                    of the situation, wrote a book to dissuade them from the war: it was immediately 
                    pretended that he was paid by the government, which in reality wished the war, 
                    and which was upon the point of shutting him up in a state prison. Another man 
                    wrote to recommend the war: he was applauded, and his word taken for the 
                    science, the politeness, and importance of the Turks. It is true that he believed 
                    in his own thesis, for he has found among them people who cast a nativity, and 
                    alchymists who ruined his fortune; as he found Martinists at Paris, who enabled 
                    him to sup with Sesostris, and Magnetizers who concluded with destroying his 
                    existence. Notwithstanding this, the Turks were beaten by the Russians, and 
                    the man who then predicted the fall of their empire, persists in the prediction. 
                    The result of this fall will be a complete change of the political system, as far as it 
                    relates to the coast of the Mediterranean. If, however, the French become 
                    important in proportion as they become free, and if they make use of the advantage 
                    they will obtain, their progress may easily prove of the most honorable sort; 
                    inasmuch as, by the wise decrees of fate, the true interest of mankind evermore 
                    accords with their true morality.
                </note>    
            </div1>
            <pb xml:id="leaf006v" facs="bmr_nhg.00357.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <div1>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">64</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top">THE RUINS OF EMPIRES.</fw>
                <p>maintain and nourish mankind by useful labors gather round 
            it; and you will discover the enemy that preys upon you.</p>
                <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="i1" from="#i1" to="#i2"/>
                <p>The standard being raised, this nation divided itself at once 
            into two bodies of unequal magnitude and contrasted appearance. 
            The one, innumerable, and almost total, exhibited in 
            the poverty of its clothing, in its emaciated appearance and 
            sun-burnt faces, the marks of misery and labor; the other, 
            a little group, an insignificant faction, presented in its rich 
            attire embroidered with gold and silver, and in its sleek and 
            ruddy faces, the signs of leisure and abundance.</p>
                <p>Considering these men more attentively, I found that the 
            great body was composed of farmers, artificers, merchants, 
            all professions useful to society; and that the little group was<anchor xml:id="i2"/> 
            made up of priests of every order, of financiers, of nobles, of 
            men in livery, of commanders of armies; in a word, of the 
            civil, military, and religious agents of government.</p>
                <p>These two bodies being assembled face to face, and regarding 
            each other with astonishment, I saw indignation and rage 
            arising in one side, and a sort of panic in the other. And the 
            large body said to the little one: Why are you separated 
            from us? Are you not of our number?</p>
                <p>No, replied the group; you are the people; we are a 
            privileged class, who have our laws, customs, and rights, peculiar 
            to ourselves.</p>
                <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="j1" from="#j1" to="#j2"/>
                <p>P<hi rend="smallcaps">EOPLE</hi>.&#8212;And what labor do you perform in our society?</p>
                <p>P<hi rend="smallcaps">RIVILEGED</hi> C<hi rend="smallcaps">LASS</hi>.&#8212;None; we are not made to work.</p>
                <p>P<hi rend="smallcaps">EOPLE</hi>.&#8212;How, then, have you acquired these riches?</p>
                <p>P<hi rend="smallcaps">RIVILEGED</hi> C<hi rend="smallcaps">LASS</hi>&#8212;By taking the pains to govern you.</p>
                <p>P<hi rend="smallcaps">EOPLE</hi>.&#8212;What! is this what you call governing? We toil
            and you enjoy! we produce and you dissipate! Wealth proceeds
            from us, and you absorb it. Privileged men! class who
            are not the people; form a nation apart, and govern yourselves.<anchor xml:id="j2"/>
            <ref target="#3" xml:id="ref3">&#42;</ref></p>
                <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="k1" from="#k1" to="#k2"/>
                <note xml:id="n3" target="#ref3" type="footnote" place="bottom">
                  * This dialogue between the people and the indolent classes, is applicable to 
                every society; it contains the seeds of all the political vices and disorders that 
                prevail, and which may thus be defined: Men who do nothing, and who devour 
                the substance of others; and men who arrogate to themselves particular rights 
                and exclusive privileges of wealth and indolence. Compare the Mamlouks of 
                Egypt, the nobility of Europe, the Nairs of India, the Emirs of Arabia, the patricians 
                of Rome, the Christian clergy, the Imans, the Bramins, the Bonzes, the 
                Lamas, etc., etc., and you will find in all the same characteristic feature :&#8212;Men
                living in idleness at the expense of those who labor.<anchor xml:id="k2"/> 
                </note>
            </div1>
            <pb xml:id="leaf007v" facs="bmr_nhg.00358.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">66</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top">THE RUINS OF EMPIRES.</fw>
            <div1>
                <p>P<hi rend="smallcaps">EOPLE</hi>.&#8212;Kings are inseperable from their nations. Our 
            king cannot be with you; you possess only his phantom.</p>
                <p>And the military governors came forward. The people are 
            timorous, said they; we must threaten them; they will submit 
            only to force. Soldiers, chastise this insolent multitude.</p>
                <p>P<hi rend="smallcaps">EOPLE</hi>.&#8212;Soldiers, you are of our blood! Will you strike 
            your brothers, your relatives? If the people perish who will 
            nourish the army?</p>
                <p>And the soldiers, grounding their arms, said to the chiefs: 
            We are likewise the people; show us the enemy!</p>
                <p>Then the ecclesiastical governors said: There is but one 
            resource left. The people are superstitious; we must frighten 
            them with the names of God and religion.</p>
                <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="l1" from="#l1" to="#l2"/><p>Our dear brethren! our children! God has ordained us to 
                    govern you.</p>
                <p>P<hi rend="smallcaps">EOPLE</hi>.&#8212;Show us your credentials from God!</p>
                <p>P<hi rend="smallcaps">RIESTS</hi>&#8212;You must have faith; reason leads astray.</p>
                <p>P<hi rend="smallcaps">EOPLE</hi>.&#8212;Do you govern without reason?</p>
                <p>P<hi rend="smallcaps">RIESTS</hi>.&#8212;God commands peace! Religion prescribes
            obedience.</p>
                <p>P<hi rend="smallcaps">EOPLE</hi>.&#8212;Show us the example.</p>
                <p>P<hi rend="smallcaps">RIESTS</hi>.&#8212;Would you live without gods or kings?</p>
                <p>P<hi rend="smallcaps">EOPLE</hi>.&#8212;We would live without oppressors.</p>
                <p>P<hi rend="smallcaps">RIESTS</hi>.&#8212;You must have mediators, intercessors.</p>
                <p>P<hi rend="smallcaps">EOPLE</hi>.&#8212;Mediators with God and with the king! courtiers
            and priests, your services are too expensive : we will henceforth manage our own affairs.</p>
                <p>And the little group said : We are lost! the multitude are
            enlightened.</p>
                <p>And the people answered : You are safe; since we are 
            enlightened we will commit no violence; we only claim our
            rights. We feel resentments, but we will forget them. We<anchor xml:id="l2"/>
            were slaves, we might command; but we only wish to be free,
            and liberty is but justice.</p>
            </div1>
            <pb xml:id="leaf008r" facs="bmr_nhg.00359.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <fw type="header" place="top">THE RUINS OF EMPIRES.</fw>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">79</fw>
            <div1>
                <p>Mollas, and the Muftis; and near them are the Dervishes with 
            pointed bonnets, and the Santons with dishevelled hair. Behold 
            with what vehemence they recite their professions of 
            faith! They are now beginning a dispute about the greater 
            and lesser impurities,&#8212;about the matter and the manner of 
            ablutions,&#8212;about the attributes of God and his perfections,&#8212; 
            about the Chaitan, and the good and wicked angels,&#8212;about 
            death, the resurrection, the interrogatory in the tomb, the 
            judgment, the passage of the narrow bridge not broader than 
            a hair, the balance of works, the pains of hell, and the joys of 
            paradise.</p>
                <div2 type="section-break">
                    <p>Next to these, that second more numerous group, with 
                white banners intersected with crosses, are the followers of 
                Jesus. Acknowledging the same God with the Mussulmans, 
                founding their belief on the same books, admitting, like them, 
                a first man who lost the human race by eating an apple, they 
                hold them, however, in a holy abhorrence; and, out of pure 
                <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="m1" from="#m1" to="#m2"/>piety, they call each other impious blasphemers.</p>
                    <p>The great point of their dissension consists in this, that 
                after admitting a God <hi rend="italic">one and indivisible</hi>, the Christian divides 
                him into three persons, each of which he believes to be a 
                complete and entire God, without ceasing to constitute an 
                identical whole, by the indivisibility of the three. And he 
                adds, that this being, who fills the universe, has reduced 
                himself to the body of a man; and has assumed material, 
                perishable, and limited organs, without ceasing to be immaterial, 
                infinite, and eternal. The Mussulman, who does not 
                comprehend these mysteries, rejects them as follies, and the <anchor xml:id="m2"/>
                visions of a distempered brain; though he conceives perfectly 
                well the eternity of the Koran, and the mission of the prophet: 
                hence their implacable hatreds.</p>
                    <p>Again, the Christians, divided among themselves on many 
                points, have formed parties not less violent than the Mussulmans 
; and their quarrels are so much the more obstinate, as 
                the objects of them are inaccessible to the senses, and 
                incapable of demonstration: their opinions, therefore, have no 
                other basis but the will and caprice of the parties. Thus, 
                while they agree that God is a being incomprehensible and
                unknown, they dispute, nevertheless, about his essence, his</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            <pb xml:id="leaf009r" facs="bmr_nhg.00360.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <fw type="header" place="top">THE RUINS OF EMPIRES.</fw>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">93</fw>
            <div1>
                <p>compassionate morality, its affections altogether spiritual, 
            attest its emanation from God! Many of its doctrines, it is true, 
            soar above the reach of the understanding, and impose on 
            reason a respectful silence; but this more fully demonstrates 
            its revelation, since the human mind could never have 
            imagined such mysteries."</p>
                <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="o1" from="#o1" to="#o2"/>
                <p>Then, holding the Bible in one hand and the four Gospels 
            in the other, the doctor began to relate that, in the beginning, 
            God, after passing an eternity in idleness, took the resolution, 
            without any known cause, of making the world out of nothing; 
            that having created the whole universe in six days, he found 
            himself fatigued on the seventh; that having placed the first 
            human pair in a garden of delights, to make them completely 
            happy, he forbade their tasting a particular fruit which he 
            placed within their reach; that these first parents, having 
            yielded to the temptation, all their race (which were not yet 
            born) had been condemned to bear the penalty of a fault 
            which they had not committed; that, after having left the 
            human race to damn themselves for four or five thousand 
            years, this God of mercy ordered a well beloved son, whom 
            he had engendered without a mother, and who was as old as 
            himself, to go and be put to death on the earth; and this for 
            the salvation of mankind; of whom much the greater portion, 
            nevertheless, have ever since continued in the way of perdition; 
            that to remedy this new difficulty, this same God, born 
            of a virgin, having died and risen from the dead, assumes a 
            new existence every day, and in the form of a piece of bread, 
            multiplies himself by millions at the voice of one of the basest 
            of men. Then, passing on to the doctrine of the sacraments, 
            he was going to treat at large on the power of absolution 
            and reprobation, of the means of purging all sins by a little 
            water and a few words, when, uttering the words <hi rend="italic">indulgence,<anchor xml:id="o2"/> 
            power of the pope, sufficient grace, and efficacious grace,</hi> he 
            was interrupted by a thousand cries.</p>
                <p>"It is a horrible abuse," cried the Lutherans, "to pretend
            to remit sins for money."</p>
                <p>"The notion of the <hi rend="italic">real presence</hi>," cried the Calvinists, "is
            contrary to the text of the Gospel."</p>
                <p>"The pope has no right to decide anything of himself,"
            cried the Jansenists; and thirty other sects rising up, and</p>
            </div1>
            <pb xml:id="leaf010v" facs="bmr_nhg.00361.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">94</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top">THE RUINS OF EMPIRES.</fw>
            <div1>
                <p>accusing each other of heresies and errors, it was no longer 
            possible to hear anything distinctly.</p>
                <p>Silence being at last restored, the Mussulmans observed to
                    <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="y1" from="#y1" to="#y2"/>
            the legislator :</p>
                <p>"Since you have rejected our doctrine as containing things 
            incredible, can you admit that of the Christians? Is not theirs 
            still more contrary to common sense and justice? A God, 
            immaterial and infinite, to become a man! to have a son as 
            old as himself! This god-man to become bread, to be eaten 
            and digested! Have we any thing equal to that? Have the 
            Christians an exclusive right of setting up a blind faith? And 
            will you grant them privileges of belief to our detriment?"</p>
                <p>Some savage tribes then advanced: "What!" said they, 
            "because a man and woman ate an apple six thousand years 
            ago, all the human race are damned? And you call God 
            just? What tyrant ever rendered children responsible for 
            the faults of their fathers? What man can answer for the 
            actions of another? Does not this overturn every idea of <anchor xml:id="y2"/>
            justice and of reason?"</p>
                <p>Others exclaimed: "Where are the proofs, the witnesses 
            of these pretended facts? Can we receive them without examining 
            the evidence? The least action in a court of justice 
            requires two witnesses; and we are ordered to believe all this 
            on mere tradition and hearsay!"</p>
                <p>A Jewish Rabbin then addressing the assembly, said: "As 
            to the fundamental facts, we are sureties; but with regard to 
            their form and their application, the case is different, and the 
            Christians are here condemned by their own arguments. For 
            they cannot deny that we are the original source from which 
            they are derived&#8212;the primitive stock on which they are 
            grafted; and hence the reasoning is very short: Either our 
            law is from God, and then theirs is a heresy, since it differs 
            from ours, or our law is not from God, and then theirs falls at 
            the same time."</p>
                <p>"But you must make this distinction," replied the Christian: 
            "Your law is from God as <hi rend="italic">typical</hi> and <hi rend="italic">preparative</hi>, but not as 
            final and absolute: you are the image of which we are the 
            substance."</p>
                <p>"We know," replied the Rabbin, " that such are your pretensions; 
            but they are absolutely gratuitous and false. Your</p>
            </div1>
            <pb xml:id="leaf011r" facs="bmr_nhg.00362.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <fw type="header" place="top">THE RUINS OF EMPIRES.</fw>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">97</fw>
            <div1>
                <p>"Thus," continued the Mobed, turning to the Rabbins, "it 
                    was not till after that epoch, that is to say, in the time of your 
                    first kings, that these ideas began to appear in your writers; 
                    and then their appearance was obscure and gradual, according 
                    to the progress of the political relations between your ancestors 
                    and ours. It was especially when, having been conquered 
                    by the kings of Nineveh and Babylon and transported to the 
                    <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="p1" from="#p1" to="#p2"/>banks of the Tygris and the Euphrates, where they resided for 
                    three successive generations, that they imbibed manners and 
                    opinions which had been rejected as contrary to their law. 
                    When our king Cyrus had delivered them from slavery, their 
                    heart was won to us by gratitude; they became our disciples 
                    and imitators; and they admitted our dogmas in the revision 
                    of their books;<ref target="#4" xml:id="ref4">&#42;</ref> for your Genesis, in particular, was never the 
                    work of Moses, but a compilation drawn up after the return 
                    from the Babylonian captivity, in which are inserted the 
                    Chaldean opinions of the origin of the world.</p>
                <p>"At first the pure followers of the law, opposing to the 
                    emigrants the letter of the text and the absolute silence of the<anchor xml:id="p2"/> 
                    prophet, endeavored to repel these innovations; but they 
                    ultimately prevailed, and our doctrine, modified by your ideas, 
                    gave rise to a new sect.</p>
                <note xml:id="n4" target="#ref4" type="footnote" place="bottom">
                    <p>&#42; In the first periods of the Christian church, not only the most learned of those 
                        who have since been denominated heretics, but many of the orthodox conceived 
                        Moses to have written neither the law nor the Pentateuch, but that the work was 
                        a compilation made by the elders of the people and the Seventy, who, after the 
                        death of Moses, collected his scattered ordinances, and mixed with them things 
                        that were extraneous: similar to what happened as to the Koran of Mahomet. 
                        See <hi rend="italic">Les Clementines</hi>, Homel. 2. sect. 51. and Homel. 3. sect. 42.</p>
                    <p>Modern critics, more enlightened or more attentive than the ancients, have 
                        found in Genesis in particular, marks of its having been composed on the return 
                        from the captivity; but the principal proofs have escaped them. These I mean to 
                        exhibit in an analysis of the book of Genesis, in which I shall demonstrate that 
                        the tenth chapter, among others, which treats of the pretended generations of the 
                        man called Noah, is a real geographical picture of the world, as it was known to 
                        the Hebrews at the epoch of the captivity, which was bounded by Greece or 
                        Hellas at the West, mount Caucasus at the North, Persia at the East, and 
                        Arabia and Upper Egypt at the South. All the pretended personages from Adam 
                        to Abraham, or his father Terah, are mythological beings, stars, constellations, 
                        countries. Adam is Bootes: Noah is Osiris: Xisuthrus Janus, Saturn; that is to 
                        say Capricorn, or the celestial Genius that opened the year. The <hi rend="italic">Alexandrian 
                        Chronicle</hi> says expressly, page 85, that Nimrod was supposed by the Persians to 
                        be their first king, as having invented the art of hunting, and that he was translated 
                        into heaven, where he appears under the name of Orion.</p>
                </note></div1>
                <pb xml:id="leaf012v" facs="bmr_nhg.00347.jpg" type="verso"/>
                <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">106</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top">THE <choice><orig>RUIFS</orig><reg>RUINS</reg></choice> OF EMPIRES.</fw>
                <div1>
                    <p>Then, retorting the pretensions of the Christians against 
                        themselves: "Prove to us," said the Lama, "that you are not 
                        Samaneans degenerated, and that the man you make the 
                        author of your sect is not F&#244;t himself disguised. Prove to us 
                        by historical facts that he even existed at the epoch you 
                        pretend; for, it being destitute of authentic testimony,<ref target="#6" xml:id="ref6">&#42;</ref> we absolutely 
                        deny it; and we maintain that your very gospels are 
                        only the books of some Mithriacs of Persia, and the Essenians 
                        of Syria, who were a branch of reformed Samaneans."<ref target="#7" xml:id="ref7">&#8224;</ref></p>
                    <note xml:id="n5" type="footnote" place="bottom" resp="#h3">
                        <p>Chaman, still preserved in Tartary, China, and India. The interpretation given 
                        to it is, man of the woods, a hermit mortifying the flesh, such being the characteristic 
                        of this sect; but its literal meaning is, celestial (Sam&#226;oui) and explains the 
                        system of those who are called by it. &#8212; The system is the same as that of the 
                        sectaries of Orpheus, of the Essenians, of the ancient Anchorets of Persia, and the whole
                        eastern country. See Porphyry, de <hi rend="italic">Abstin</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Animal</hi>.</p>
                        <p>These celestial and penitent men carried in India their insanity to such an 
                            extreme as to wish not to touch the earth, and they accordingly lived in cages 
                            suspended from the trees, where the people, whose admiration was not less 
                            absurd, brought them provisions. During the night there were frequent robberies, 
                            rapes and murders, and it was at length discovered that they were committed 
                            by those men, who, descending from their cages, thus indemnified themselves for 
                            their restraint during the day. The Bramins, their rivals, embraced the opportunity 
                            of exterminating them; and from that time their name in India has been 
                            synonymous with hypocrite. See <hi rend="italic">Hist. de la Chine</hi>, in 5 vols, quarto, at the note 
                            page 30; <hi rend="italic">Hist. de Huns</hi>, 2 vols, and preface to the <hi rend="italic">Ezour-Vedam</hi>.</p>
                    </note>
                    <note xml:id="n6" target="#ref6" type="footnote" place="bottom">
                        <p>&#42; There are absolutely no other monuments of the existence of Jesus Christ 
                            as a human being, than a passage in Josephus (<hi rend="italic">Antiq. Jud. lib, 18, c.3</hi>,) a single 
                            phrase in Tacitus (<hi rend="italic">Annal. lib. 15, c. 44</hi>,) and the Gospels. But the passage in 
                            <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="q1" from="#q1" to="#q2"/>
                            Josephus is unanimously acknowledged to be apocryphal, and to have been interpolated 
                            towards the close of the third century, (See <hi rend="italic">Trad. de Joseph, par M. 
                                Gillet</hi>); and that of Tacitus <choice><orig>in</orig><reg>is</reg></choice> so vague and so evidently taken from the deposition
                             of the Christians before the tribunals, that it may be ranked in the class of 
                            evangelical records. It remains to enquire of what authority are these records. 
                            "All the world knows," says Faustus, who, though a Manichean, was one of the 
                            most learned men of the third century, "All the world knows that the gospels 
                            were neither written by Jesus Christ, nor his apostles, but by certain unknown 
                            persons, who rightly judging that they should not obtain belief respecting things 
                            which they had not seen, placed at the head of their recitals the names of 
                            contemporary apostles." See <hi rend="italic">Beausob</hi>. vol. i. and <hi rend="italic">Hist. des Apologistes de la Relig. 
                            Chret. par Burigni</hi>, a sagacious writer, who has demonstrated the absolute 
                            uncertainty of those foundations of the Christian religion; so that the existence of 
                            Jesus is no better proved than that of Osiris and Hercules, or that of F&#244;t or<anchor xml:id="q2"/> 
                            Beddou, with whom, says M. de Guignes, the Chinese continually confound him, 
                            for they never call Jesus by any other name than F&#244;t. <hi rend="italic">Hist. de Huns</hi>.</p>
                    </note>
                    <note xml:id="n7" target="#ref7" type="footnote" place="bottom">
                        <p>&#8224; That is to say, from the pious romances formed out of the sacred legends of 
                            the mysteries of Mithra, Ceres, Isis, etc., from whence are equally derived the 
                            books of the Hindoos and the Bonzes. Our missionaries have long remarked a 
                            striking resemblance between those books and the gospels. M. Wilkins expressly</p>
                    </note>
                </div1>
            <pb xml:id="leaf013r" facs="bmr_nhg.00348.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <fw type="header" place="top">THE RUINS OF EMPIRES.</fw>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">107</fw>
            <div1>
                <p>At these words, the Christians set up a general cry, 
                    and a new dispute was about to begin; when a number of 
                    Chinese Chamans, and Talapoins of Siam, came forward and 
                    said that they would settle the whole controversy. And one 
                    of them speaking for the whole exclaimed: "It is time to put 
                    an end to these frivolous contests by drawing aside the veil 
                    from the interior doctrine that F&#244;t himself revealed to 
                    his disciples on his death bed.<ref target="#8" xml:id="ref8">&#42;</ref></p>
                <p>"All these theological opinions," continued he, "are but 
                    chimeras. All the stories of the nature of the gods, of their 
                    actions and their lives, are but allegories and mythological 
                    emblems, under which are enveloped ingenious ideas of 
                    morals, and the knowledge of the operations of nature in the 
                    action of the elements and the movement of the planets.</p>
                <p>"The truth is, that all is reduced to nothing&#8212;that all is 
                    illusion, appearance, dream; that the moral metempsychosis 
                    is only the figurative sense of the physical metempsychosis, 
                    or the successive movement of the elements of bodies which 
                    perish not, but which, having composed one body, pass when 
                    that is dissolved, into other mediums and form other 
                    combinations. The soul is but the vital principle which results 
                    from the properties of matter, and from the action of the 
                    elements in those bodies where they create a spontaneous 
                    movement. To suppose that this product of the play of the 
                    organs, born with them, matured with them, and which sleeps 
                    with them, can subsist when they cease, is the romance of 
                    a wandering imagination, perhaps agreeable enough, but 
                    really chimerical.</p>
                <p>God itself is nothing more than the moving principle, the 
                    occult force inherent in all beings&#8212;the sum of their laws and</p>
                <!-- Below is a continued note from the previous page, 106. -->
                <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="z1" from="#z1" to="#z2"/>
                <note xml:id="n7a" target="#ref7" type="footnote" place="bottom">
                    mentions it in a note in the <hi rend="italic">Bhagvat Geeta</hi>. All agree that Krisna, F&#244;t, and Jesus 
                    have the same characteristic features: but religious prejudice has stood in 
                    the way of drawing from this circumstance the proper and natural inference. To 
                    time and reason must it be left to display the truth.<anchor xml:id="z2"/>
                </note>
                <note xml:id="n8" target="#ref8" type="footnote" place="bottom">
                    &#42;The Budsoists have two doctrines, the one public and ostensible, the other 
                    interior and secret, precisely like the Egyptian priests. It may be asked, why 
                    this distinction? It is, that as the public doctrine recommends offerings, expiations, 
                    endowments, etc., the priests find their profit in preaching it to the people; 
                    whereas the other, teaching the vanity of worldly things, and attended with no 
                    lucre, it is thought proper to make it known only to adepts. Can the teachers 
                    and followers of this religion be better classed than under the heads of knavery 
                    and credulity?
                </note>
            </div1>
            <pb xml:id="leaf014v" facs="bmr_nhg.00349.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">136</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top">THE RUINS OF EMPIRES.</fw>
            <div1>
                <p>You perceive the successive filiation of these ideas, and how, 
                    in proportion to their remoteness from their source, and as 
                    the minds of men became refined, their gross forms have been 
                    polished, and rendered less disgusting.</p>
                <p>"But in the same manner as you have seen the system of two 
                    opposite principles or gods arise from that of symbols, interwoven 
                    into its texture, your attention shall now be called to a 
                    new system which has grown out of this, and to which this 
                    has served in its turn as the basis and support.</p>
                <div2>
                    <p>V. <hi rend="italic">Moral and Mystical Worship, or System of a Future State</hi>.</p>
                    <p>"Indeed, when the vulgar <hi rend="underline" hand="#h1">heard</hi> speak of a new heaven and 
                        another world, they soon gave a body to these fictions; they 
                        erected therein a real theatre of action, and their notions of 
                        astronomy and geography served to strengthen, if not to 
                        originate, this illusion.</p>
                    <p>"On the one hand, the Ph&#339;nician navigators who passed 
                        the pillars of Hercules, to fetch the tin of Thule and the amber 
                        of the Baltic, related that at the extremity of the world, 
                        the end of the ocean (the Mediterranean), where the sun sets 
                        for the countries of Asia, were the Fortunate Islands, the 
                        abode of eternal spring; and beyond were the hyperborean 
                        regions, placed under the earth (relatively to the tropics) 
                        where reigned an eternal night.<ref target="#9" xml:id="ref9">&#42;</ref> From these stories, 
                        misunderstood, and no doubt confusedly related, the imagination of 
                        the people composed the Elysian fields,<ref target="#10" xml:id="ref10">&#8224;</ref> regions of delight, 
                        placed in a world below, having their heaven, their sun, and 
                        their stars; and Tartarus, a place of darkness, humidity, mire, 
                        and frost. Now, as man, inquisitive of that which he knows 
                        not, and desirous of protracting his existence, had already 
                        interrogated himself concerning what was to become of him 
                        after his death, as he had early reasoned on the principle of 
                        life which animates his body, and which leaves it without 
                        deforming it, and as he had imagined airy substances, phantoms, 
                        and shades, he fondly believed that he should continue, in the 
                        subterranean world, that life which it was too painful for him 
                        to lose; and these lower regions seemed commodious for the</p>
                    <note xml:id="n9" target="#ref9" type="footnote" place="bottom">
                        &#42; Nights of six months duration.
                    </note>
                    <note xml:id="n10" target="#ref10" type="footnote" place="bottom">
                        &#8224; <hi rend="italic">Aliz</hi>, in the Ph&#339;nician or Hebrew language signifies dancing and joyous.
                    </note>
                </div2>
            </div1>
            <pb xml:id="leaf015v" facs="bmr_nhg.00350.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">166</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top">THE RUINS OF EMPIRES.</fw>
            <div1>
                <p>are constantly galling your neighbors. When you criminate 
                    so severely the great man whom we revere, we might fairly 
                    retort on the conduct of him whom you adore; but we scorn 
                    such advantages, and confining ourselves to the real object in 
                    question, we maintain that the morals of your gospel have by 
                    <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h1" xml:id="t1" from="#t1" to="#t2"/>
                    no means that perfection which you ascribe to them; it is not 
                    true that they have introduced into the world new and 
                    unknown virtues: for example, the equality of men in the sight 
                    of God,&#8212;that fraternity and that benevolence which follow 
                    from it, were formal doctrines of the sect of the Hermatics or 
                    Samaneans,<ref target="#n11" xml:id="ref11">&#42;</ref> from whom you descend. As to the forgiveness 
                    of injuries, the Pagans themselves had taught it; but in the 
                    extent that you give it, far from being a virtue, it becomes an 
                    immorality, a vice. Your so much boasted precept of turning 
                    one cheek after the other, is not only contrary to every 
                    sentiment of man, but is opposed to all ideas of justice. It 
                    emboldens the wicked by impunity, debases the virtuous by 
                    servility, delivers up the world to despotism and tyranny, and 
                    dissolves all society. Such is the true spirit of your doctrines. 
                    Your gospels in their precepts and their parables, never represent 
                    God but as a despot without any rules of equity; a 
                    partial father treating a debauched and prodigal son with 
                    more favor than his respectful and virtuous children; a capricious 
                    master, who gives the same wages to workmen who 
                    had wrought but one hour, as to those who had labored 
                    through the whole day; one who prefers the last comers to
                    the first. The moral is everywhere misanthropic and anti-<anchor xml:id="t2"/>social; it disgusts men with life and with society; and tends 
                    only to encourage hermitism and celibacy.</p>
                <p>"As to the manner in which you have practised these 
                    morals, we appeal in our turn to the testimony of facts. We 
                    ask whether it is this evangelical meekness which has excited 
                    your interminable wars between your sects, your atrocious 
                    persecutions of pretended heretics, your crusades against 
                    Arianism, Manicheism, Protestantism, without speaking of 
                    your crusades against us, and of those sacrilegious associations, 
                    still subsisting, of men who take an oath to continue</p>
                <note xml:id="n11" target="#ref11" type="footnote" place="bottom">
                    &#42; The equity of mankind in a state of nature and in the eyes of God was one
                    of the principal tenets of the Samaneans, and they appear to be the only ancients
                    that entertained this opinion.
                </note>
            </div1>
            <pb xml:id="leaf016r" facs="bmr_nhg.00351.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <fw type="header" place="top">THE RUINS OF EMPIRES.</fw>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">167</fw>
            <div1>
                <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="u1" from="#u1" to="#u2"/>
                <p>them? <ref target="#n12" xml:id="ref12">&#42;</ref> We ask you whether it be gospel charity which has 
                    made you exterminate whole nations in America, to annihilate 
                    the empires of Mexico and Peru; which makes you 
                    continue to dispeople Africa and sell its inhabitants like 
                    cattle, notwithstanding your abolition of slavery; which 
                    makes you ravage India and usurp its dominions; and 
                    whether it be the same charity which, for three centuries past, 
                    has led you to harrass the habitations of the people of three 
                    continents, of whom the most prudent, the Chinese and 
                    Japanese, were constrained to drive you off, that they might 
                    escape your chains and recover their internal peace?"
                </p>
                <p>Here the Bramins, the Rabbins, the Bonzes, the Chamans, 
                    the Priests of the Molucca islands, and the coasts of Guinea,<anchor xml:id="u2"/> 
                    loading the Christian doctors with reproaches: "Yes!" 
                    cried they, "these men are robbers and hypocrites, who 
                    preach simplicity, to surprise confidence; humility, to enslave 
                    with more ease; poverty, to appropriate all riches to themselves. 
                    They promise another world, the better to usurp the 
                    <span rend="doubleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="v1" from="#v1" to="#v2"/>
                    present; and while they speak to you of tolerance and charity, 
                    they burn, in the name of God, the men who do not worship 
                    him in their manner."</p>
                <p>"Lying priests," retorted the missionaries," it is you who<anchor xml:id="v2"/>
                    abuse the credulity of ignorant nations to subjugate them. It 
                    is you who have made of your ministry an art of cheating 
                    and imposture; you have converted religion into a traffic of 
                    cupidity and avarice. You pretend to hold communications 
                    with spirits, and they give for oracles nothing but your wills. 
                    You feign to read the stars, and destiny decrees only your 
                    desires. You cause idols to speak, and the gods are but the 
                    instruments of your passions. You have invented sacrifices 
                    and libations, to collect for your own profit the milk of flocks, 
                    and the flesh and fat of victims; and under the cloak of piety 
                    you devour the offerings of the gods, who cannot eat, and 
                    the substance of the people who are forced to labor."</p>
                <p>"And you," replied the Bramins, the Bonzes, the Chamans, 
                    "you sell to the credulous living, your vain prayers for the 
                    souls of the dead. With your indulgences and your absolutions 
                    you have usurped the power of God himself; and</p>
            <note xml:id="n12" target="#ref12" type="footnote" place="bottom">
                &#42; The oath taken by the knights of the Order of Malta, is to kill, or make the 
                Mahometans prisoners, for the glory of God. 
            </note>
            </div1>
            <pb xml:id="leaf017v" facs="bmr_nhg.00352.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">168</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top">THE RUINS OF EMPIRES.</fw>
            <div1>
                <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="x1" from="#x1" to="#x2"/>
                <p>making a traffic of his favors and pardons, you have put 
                    heaven at auction; and by your system of expiations you 
                    have formed a tariff of crimes, which has perverted all 
                    consciences." <ref target="#n13" xml:id="ref13">&#42;</ref></p>
                <p>"Add to this," said the Imans, "that these men have 
                    invented the most insidious of all systems of wickedness,&#8212;the<anchor xml:id="x2"/> 
                    absurd and impious obligation of recounting to them the 
                    most intimate secrets of actions and of thoughts (confessions); 
                    so their insolent curiosity has carried their inquisition even 
                    into the sanctuary of the marriage bed,<ref target="#n14" xml:id="ref14">&#8224;</ref> and the inviolable 
                    recesses of the heart."</p>
                <p>Thus by mutual reproaches the doctors of the different sects 
                    began to reveal all the crimes of their ministry&#8212;all the vices 
                    of their craft; and it was found that among all nations the 
                    spirit of the priesthood, their system of conduct, their actions, 
                    their morals, were absolutely the same :</p>
                <p>That they had everywhere formed secret associations and corporations at enmity with the rest of society: <ref target="#n15" xml:id="ref15">&#8225;</ref></p>
                <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="w1" from="#w1" to="#w2"/>
                <note xml:id="n13" target="#ref13" type="footnote" place="bottom">
                    &#42; As long as it shall be possible to obtain purification from crimes and exemption 
                    from punishment by means of money or other frivolous practices; as long as 
                    kings and great men shall suppose that building temples or instituting foundations, 
                    will absolve them from the guilt of oppression and homicide; as long as 
                    individuals shall imagine that they may rob and cheat, provided they observe fast 
                    during Lent, go to confession, and receive extreme unction, it is impossible there 
                    should exist in society any morality or virtue; and it is from a deep conviction 
                    of truth, that a modern philosopher has called the doctrine of expiations <hi rend="italic">la v&#233;rola 
                    des soc&#237;&#233;t&#233;s</hi>.
                </note>
                <note xml:id="n14" target="#ref14" type="footnote" place="bottom">
                    <p>&#8224; Confession is a very ancient invention of the priests, who did not fail to avail<anchor xml:id="w2"/> 
                    themselves of that means of governing. It was practised in the Egyptian, Greek, 
                    Phrygian, Persian mysteries, etc. Plutarch has transmitted us the remarkable 
                    answer of a Spartan whom a priest wanted to confess. "Is it to you or to God 
                    I am to confess?" "To God," answered the priest: "In that case," replied the 
                    Spartan, "man, begone!" (<hi rend="italic">Remarkable Sayings of the Lacedemonians</hi>.) The first 
                    Christians confessed their faults publicly, like the Essenians. Afterwards, priests 
                    began to be established, with power of absolution from the sin of idolatry. In the 
                    time of Theodosius, a woman having publicly confessed an intrigue with a deacon, 
                    bishop Necterius, and his successor Chrysostom, granted communion without 
                    confession. It was not until the seventh century that the abbots of convents 
                    exacted from monks and nuns confession twice a year; and it was at a still later 
                    period that bishops of Rome generalized it.</p>
                    <p>The Mussulmen, who suppose women to have no souls, are shocked at 
                        the idea of confession; and say; How can an honest man think of listening to the 
                        recital of the actions or the secret thoughts of a woman? May we not also ask, 
                        on the other hand, how can an honest woman consent to reveal them?</p>
                </note>
                <note xml:id="n15" target="#ref15" type="footnote" place="bottom">
                    &#8225; That we may understand the general feelings of priests respecting the rest of 
                    mankind, whom they always call by the name of the people, let us hear one of the
                </note>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>