<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ASCII"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/wwa.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/namespace" xml:id="duk.00064">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main" rend="bracketed">This list of one week's</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="as">Ashlyn Stewart</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="clh">Christy Hyman</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2019</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno>duk.00064</idno>
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>P.O. Box 884100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright &#169; 2019 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights
                        reserved. Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use
                        provisions of U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other
                        terms, in any medium, requires express written consent from the editors and
                        advance notification of the publisher, Center for Digital Research in the
                        Humanities. Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has
                        been granted by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">At one point, this manuscript likely formed part of <ref target="../index-scrapbook.html">Whitman's cultural geography scrapbook</ref>.</note>             
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author sameAs="#ww">Whitman, Walt</author>
                    <title rend="bracketed">This list of one week's</title>
                    <idno type="callnumber">II-7A 182</idno>
                    <date xml:id="dat1" notBefore="1850" notAfter="1860" cert="high">Between 1850 and 1860</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="duk">Trent Collection of Whitmaniana, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book &amp; Manuscript Library, Duke University</orgName>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from digital images of the original item.</note>
                </bibl>
                
                <bibl xml:id="r1" type="pasteon">
                    <author>unknown</author>
                    <title level="a">List of patents issued from the United States Patent Office for the week ending May 12, 1857</title>
                    <title level="j">New York Sun</title>
                    <date when="1857-05-16">16 May 1857</date>
                    <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                    <biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
                </bibl>
                
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="h1" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h2" scribeRef="#unk" medium="typescript"><persName xml:id="unk">unknown</persName></handNote>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc><change when="2022-04-14" who="#as">Regularized Name</change>
            <change when="2019-10-02" who="#km">proofed</change>
            <change when="2019-08-19" who="#clh">first check</change>
            <change when="2019-07-25" who="#as">transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text type="manuscript">
        <body>
            <ab/>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="duk.00064.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <p><handShift new="#h1"/>This list of one week's issue of patents from the National Patent office at Washington illustrates America and American character about as much as any thing I know.&#8212;(Remember the show at the Crystal Palace, and the American Institute Fairs.)</p>
            
            <add rend="pasteon" place="top" source="#r1"><handShift new="#h2"/>
                <floatingText rend="flat">
                    <body>
                        <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="duk.00064.002.jpg" type="recto"/>
                        <p>List of Patents Issued from the United States Patent Office for the week ending May 12, 1857&#8212;each bearing that date:</p>
                        <list>
                            <item>Iron plate railroad car wheels: G. W. Alden, New York, N. Y.</item>
                            <item>Apparatus for heating and cooking by gas: R. Snowden Andrews, Baltimore, Md.</item>
                            <item>Self-indicating balance: Z. W. Avery and Otis Avery, Bethany, Pa.</item>
                            <item>Signal lamps: R. P. Bailey, Niagara, N. Y.</item>
                            <item>Rotary shingle cutter: Wm. Bevard, St. Louis, Mo.</item>
                            <item>Stitch for sewing machines: Chas. F. Bosworth, Petersham, Mass.</item>
                            <item>Portable barrack: Matthias F. Brantingham, Sangamon Co., Ill.</item>
                            <item>Bumper railroad car brakes: Louis Brauer, Sommerville, Tenn.</item>
                            <item>Corn planters: Jno. Broughton, New York, N. Y.</item>
                            <item>Apparatus for roasting meat: Jno. G. Brown and Jno. P. Derby, South Reading, Mass.</item>
                            <item>Seed planters: Jno. H. Bruen, Penn Yan, N. Y.</item>
                            <item>Mode of overcoming the windage in firearms: Ambrose E. Burnside, Bristol, Mass.</item>
                            <item>Machines for making lozenges: Oliver R. Chase, of Boston Mass., and Silas E. Chase, Charlestown, Mass</item>
                            <item>Machine for cutting match splints: Thomas Cook, New York, N. Y.</item>
                            <item>Artificial honey: Zenes Corbin and Gideon Marlett, Syracuse, N. Y.</item>
                            <item>Horse shoes: David Cumming, Sorrel Horse, Pa.</item>
                            <item>Hook temples for looms: Warren C. Dutcher, and George Draper, Milford, Mass.</item>
                            <item>Method of connecting the check piece to the mouth piece of bridle bits: Kesson Frazer, Syracuse, N. Y.</item>
                            <item>Corn hunkers: E F. French, Franklin, Vt.</item>
                            <item>Mode of constructing portable houses: Daniel Fitzgerald, New York, N. Y.</item>
                            <item>Semi-rotative steam engines: C. B. Gallegher, Alleghany City, Pa.</item>
                            <item>Needles for sewing: Benjamin Garvey, New York, N. Y.</item>
                            <item>Nail plate feeder: Jno. C. Gould, Boonton, N. J.</item>
                            <item>Hemp brakes: J. Locke Hardeman, Arrow Rock, Mo.</item>
                            <item>Seed planters: John Haselton, Orford, N. H.</item>
                            <item>Propeller blades: Geo. Hibsch, Buffalo, N. Y.</item>
                            <item>Harvesters: Moses G. Hubbard, Penn Yan, N. Y.</item>
                            <item>Presses for cottom, &#38;c.: Henry Hughes, Port Gibbon, Miss.</item>
                            <item>Process of treating raw cotton: Julius C. Hurd, Medway, Mass.</item>
                            <item>Folding bedsteads: James A. Johnson, Antrim, Ohio.</item>
                            <item>Bed bottoms: J. F. Keller, Cleveland, Ohio.</item>
                            <item>Coal stoves: John C Keller, Philadelphia, Pa.</item>
                            <item>Blacksmiths' strikers: Hartwell Kendall, East Dorset, Vt.</item>
                            <item>Mortising chisel: Geo. P. Ketchum, Bedford, Ind.</item>
                            <item>Joiner's plane: Benjamin J. Lane, Newburyport, Mass.</item>
                            <item>Cartridges: Edw'd Lindner, New York, N. Y.</item>
                            <item>Machine for boring flue sheets of steam boilers: Sylvanus V. Lowe, Reading, Pa.</item>
                            <item>Clearing guard of grain elevators: Geo. Mann, Jr., Ottawa, Ill.</item>
                            <item>Machines for engraving cylinders: Robt. Muckett and Wm. Rigby, Salford, England.</item>
                            <item>Blasting powder: Antoino Murtineddu, Marseilles, France</item>
                            <item>Joiner's bench trip: Chas. T. Pearson, Chelsea, Mass.</item>
                            <item>Locks: Stuart Perry, Newport, N. Y.</item>
                            <item>Coal cracker: Townsend Poore, Carbondale, Pa.</item>
                            <item>Devulcanizing India rubber; ante-dated April 1, 1857: Conrad Poppenhusen and Ludwig Held, Brooklyn, N. Y.</item>
                            <item>Piano-forte bridge: Thos, E, Power, Columbia, Mo.</item>
                            <item>Fountain pens: Chase. Adolphus Rosefield, Columbus, Ga.</item>
                            <item>Binding books: Archibald H. Rowand, Alleghany, Pa.</item>
                            <item>Machine for planing chair seats: Edward Q. Smith, Cincinnati, Ohio.</item>
                            <item>Heating soldering tools by gas: J. Henry Stimpson, Boston, Mass.</item>
                            <item>Field fence: Seth C. Tufts, Mainville, O.</item>
                            <item>Soap substitute for scouring woolens: Louis Wilman, Worcester, Mass.</item>
                            <item>Rock drills: John D. Hope, Niagara Falls, N. Y., assignor to G. Arthur Gardner, New York. N. Y.</item>
                            <item>Seed planter: Charles Ketchum, Penn Yan, N. assignor to Charles G Judd, same place.</item>
                            <item>Sub-marine excavator: William Kennish Brooklyn, N.Y., assignor to Andrew B. Gray, San Diego, Cal.</item>
                            <item>Copying preses: Wm. Morris Smith, Washington, D. C., assignor to himself and Peter Hannay.</item>
                            <item>Gas generators. James A. Bruce, Baltimore, Md., assignor to the Maryland Portable Gas Company, same place.</item>
                            <item>Method of preparing canvass for printing, painting &#38;c., Elisha Lee, Baltimore, Md.</item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Re-issue</hi>&#8212;Hanging shafts in mills.  Pantented October 9, 1849.  Jos. Bancroft, executor of Edward Bancroft, deceased, late of Philadelphia, Pa.</item>
                        </list>
                        <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
             </add>
           </body>                
</text>
</TEI>
