<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"
?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch"
?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="duk.00037">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Robert Chambers</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
                <author xml:id="lh">Ludwig Herrig</author>
                <author xml:id="rc">Robert Chambers</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ano">Alejandro Omidsalar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mc">Matt Cohen</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>University of Texas at Austin</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2015</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>kprice@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Ed-Folsom@uiowa.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>bbarney2@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain exceptions, public domain works may be 
                        freely copied or used in the creation of derivative works without permission, or authorization, of the former copyright owners.</p>
                    <p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and is governed by a
                        <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                            Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License
                        </ref>
                        (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                    <p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted 
                        by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>duk.00037</idno></publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt><note type="project">At one point, this manuscript likely formed part of <ref target="../index-scrapbook.html">Whitman's cultural geography scrapbook</ref>. This document comes from a collected volume, edited by Ludwig Herrig (see "Base Document Citation," above); the pages that Whitman has removed from the volume are an excerpt of a work by Robert Chambers.</note></notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc><bibl>
                <author sameAs="#ww">Whitman, Walt</author>
                <title>Excerpt from Herrig's The British Classical Authors</title>
                <idno type="callno">MS q 186</idno>
                <date notBefore="1850-01-01" notAfter="1860">Between 1850 and 1860</date>
                <orgName xml:id="duk">Trent Collection of Whitmaniana, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book &amp; Manuscript Library, Duke University</orgName>
                <note type="project">Transcribed from digital images of the original item.</note>
            </bibl>
                <bibl type="base" xml:id="r1">
                    <author>Ludwig Herrig</author>
                    <title level="a">The British Classical Authors: 
                        Select Specimens of the National Literature of England from G. Chaucer to the Present Time</title>
                    <date when="1850">1850</date>
                    <publisher>George Westermann</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Brunswick</pubPlace>
                    <biblScope unit="pp">672, 678-680</biblScope>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="h1" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h2" scribeRef="#lh" medium="typescript"/>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc> 
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#km" when="2020-02-06">edited editorial note</change>
            <change who="#km" when="2020-01-31">proofed</change>
            <change who="#mc" when="2015-09-21">Proofed.</change>
            <change who="#ano" when="2015-09-10">Transcribed and encoded.</change>               
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="marginalia">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="duk.00037.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <add rend="pasteon" source="#r2">
                <q who="#h1" type="written">
                    <floatingText rend="flat"><body><pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="duk.00037.001a.jpg" type="recto"/><p><handShift new="#h1"/>Resumé <lb/>
                        of <lb/>
                        Physical Great Britain <lb/>
                        of the date of about <lb/>
                        1840</p></body></floatingText>
                </q>
            </add>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left"><handShift new="#h2"/>672</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top">CHAMBERS.</fw> <!-- This is partially covered by the paste-on. -->
            <cb n="1"/>
            <p>land, Lord High <gap atLeast="15" atMost="20" unit="chars" reason="illegible"/>
                Cromwell, Earl of <gap atLeast="15" atMost="20" unit="chars" reason="illegible"/>
                surer. There, to <gap atLeast="15" atMost="20" unit="chars" reason="illegible"/>
                whom nature and <gap atLeast="15" atMost="20" unit="chars" reason="illegible"/>
                their bounties in <gap atLeast="15" atMost="20" unit="chars" reason="illegible"/>
                grace, genius, royal <gap atLeast="15" atMost="20" unit="chars" reason="illegible"/>
                conducted to an ear <gap atLeast="15" atMost="20" unit="chars" reason="illegible"/>
                Not far off sleep <gap atLeast="15" atMost="20" unit="chars" reason="illegible"/>
                house of Howard, <gap atLeast="15" atMost="20" unit="chars" reason="illegible"/></p>
            <cb n="2"/>
            <p><gap atLeast="10" atMost="15" unit="chars" reason="illegible"/>ilip, eleventh Earl of Arun-
                <gap atLeast="15" atMost="20" unit="chars" reason="illegible"/>ere, among the thick graves
                <gap atLeast="15" atMost="20" unit="chars" reason="illegible"/> aspiring statesmen, lie
                <gap atLeast="15" atMost="20" unit="chars" reason="illegible"/>ferers; Margaret of Salis-
                <gap atLeast="15" atMost="20" unit="chars" reason="illegible"/>se two fair Queens who
                <gap atLeast="15" atMost="20" unit="chars" reason="illegible"/>ealous rage of Henry. Such
                <gap atLeast="15" atMost="20" unit="chars" reason="illegible"/>h which the dust of Mon-
                <gap quantity="14" unit="chars" reason="illegible"/></p>
            <div1 type="section"><head>ROBERT CHAMBERS.</head>
            <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short"/>
            <cb n="3"/>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">PRESENT STATE OF THE BRITISH
                EMPIRE.</hi></p>
            <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short"/>
            <p>The British empire is acknowledged to be 
                one of the greatest which exist, or ever 
                existed, on the face of the earth. Its territories 
                are of vast extent; embracing England, 
                Ireland, and Scotland, which constitute what
                is termed the mother country, and a range 
                of colonies and dependencies in all quarters 
                of the world.</p>
            <p>England may be considered the central 
                and principal portion of the empire. With 
                Wales, it contains fifty-two counties, or thirty-seven millions of acres, and a population
                of about fifteen millions. Scotland, 
                which was incorporated with England in 1707, contains thirty three counties, or 
                twenty millions of acres and a population 
                of about two and a half millions. Ireland, 
                which was annexed to the English crown 
                at an early period, but not united under 
                the same legislative system till 1800, contains 
                thirty-two counties, or twenty millions 
                of acres, and a population of eight millions.</p>
            <p>The metropolis of the British empire is 
                London, and here are situated the palaces 
                of the Queen and royal family, the Houses 
                of Parliament, the chief law courts, and 
                numerous institutions of national importance. 
                Edinburgh, the capital of Scotland, and 
                Dublin, the capital of Ireland, have been 
                only of secondary importance since the 
                union of those countries with England.</p>
            <p>England is esteemed a beautiful country. 
                Excepting in the western parts, which are 
                mostly hilly, the surface is either level or 
                composed of gentle slopes, bearing rich crops, 
                and adorned with trees and hedgerows. The 
                country abounds in noblemen and gentlemen's 
                seats of handsome architecture, old castles, 
                cathedrals, and churches, and its cottages 
               <cb n="4"/>
                <span type="line" from="#a1" to="#a2">
                    <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="supralinear" xml:id="a1">The Press, the <lb/>
                        most important of the <lb/>
                        modern "estates", is <lb/>
                        left out—</note><anchor xml:id="a2"/></span>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="bottom" target="#a2">☝</note>
                    are more neat and attractive than those of 
                    any other nation. From the general absence
                    of hard stone near the surface, the towns 
                    are mostly built of brick.</p>
            <p>Scotland, or the northern part of Britain, 
                is more rugged and hilly than England, and 
                is much indented with arms of the sea. Its 
                naturally inferior soil has been prodigiously 
                improved by art in modern times, and the 
                surface greatly beautified by plantations and 
                the operations of the agriculturist. It is 
                allowed that Scotland, latterly, has advanced 
                in social and physical improvement at a 
                more rapid pace than any other part of the 
                civilised world, some of the states of the 
                North American Union alone excepted.</p>
            <p>Ireland, which, from the introduction of 
                steam-navigation, is now within a few hours' 
                sail of the west coast of Great Britain, is 
                a moderately hilly and beautiful green island. 
                It has many excellent harbours, and is finely 
                situated for trade, either with the continent 
                of Europe or America. Possessing all the 
                advantages of a connexion with Britain, 
                and going along with it in great commercial 
                undertakings, it cannot be doubted that Ireland 
                will ultimately enjoy a degree of prosperity 
                equal to that of any part of the empire.</p>
            <p>The oldest existing colonies of Britain 
                are those of the West Indies, chiefly consisting 
                of a series of islands stretching across 
                the great bay which nearly divides North 
                from South America. Jamaica, the largest 
                and most important of these islands, contains 
                about four hundred thousand inhabitants, of whom only about thirty-seven thousand 
                are white people, the rest being negroes, 
                most of whom were originally slave labourers. 
                Barbadoes, Trinidad, and the other 
                West India colonies, are less populous, the 
                full amount being in each case divided in the 
                same proportions between blacks and whites.</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf002v" facs="duk.00037.002.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left"><handShift new="#h2"/>678</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top">CHAMBERS.</fw>
            <cb n="1"/>
            <p>the Cabinet Ministers, and responsible for 
                the advice they give.</p>
            <p>The two Houses of Parliament usually 
                sit, during a considerable portion of every 
                year, in deliberation upon the affairs of the 
                country, and for the enactment of new, or 
                the repeal of old laws. Any member of 
                either house may propose a new law; but 
                this duty is chiefly undertaken by the king's 
                ministers, and it is to the Lower or Commons 
                House that new laws are usually first 
                proposed. When a proposed law has been 
                introduced in the shape of a bill, and sanctioned 
                in one House, it passes on to another, 
                which may receive, reject, or modify it. If 
                it passes both, it is submitted to the king, 
                who may give or withhold his approbation. 
                When it has received the sanction of all 
                the three branches of the legislature, it is 
                called an Act of Parliament, and becomes 
                part of the laws of the country. The bills 
                for the pecuniary supplies necessary for the 
                public service, are introduced exclusively by 
                the House of Commons: they may be rejected 
                by the House of Lords; but for that house 
                to alter them, or to introduce any bill which 
                involves pecuniary supply to the government, 
                is considered a breach of the privileges of 
                the Lower House.</p>
            <p>The public revenue of the United Kingdom 
                is derived principally from four sources, 
                namely—customs duties, excise duties, 
                stamp duties, and assessed taxes.</p>
            <p>Customs duties are charged on most articles 
                imported into, or exported from, the 
                country. Excise duties are charged on certain 
                commodities produced or manufactured 
                at home.</p>
            <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h1" xml:id="s1" from="#s1" to="#s2"/>
            <p>Stamp duties are mostly laid on the 
                parchment or paper on which certain deeds, 
                receipts, newspapers, etc., are written or 
                printed, and derive their name from the 
                parchment or paper being impressed with a 
                stamp, stating the amount of the duty.</p><anchor xml:id="s2"/>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="left">abrogated</note>
            <p>Assessed taxes include the duties on 
                windows, servants, horses, carriages, etc. 
                There are some other inferior sources of revenue, 
                such as the Post-office.</p>
            <p>The revenue of the United Kingdom 
                amounted in the year ending January 5, 
                1839, to upwards of 51,000,000 and the 
                expenditure to nearly the same.</p>
            <p>The public expenditure is made up of a 
                vast variety of items, the most important of 
                which is the interest of the National Debt. 
                The amount of the debt in 1839 was 
                L841,000,000, chiefly composed of various
                <cb n="2"/>stocks, or loans at certain rates of interest. 
                Lenders of money to the public are called 
                stock or fund holders. The interest payable 
                on the debt in 1839 was L29,000,000.</p>
            <p>The home territories of the empire are 
                alone concerned in maintaining and controlling 
                the government. It is known that an 
                attempt to raise taxes in the colonies of 
                North America, which sent no parliamentary 
                representatives to join in imposing them, 
                was the means of separating those colonies 
                from the parent state. Since then, no similar 
                attempt has been made in any other 
                colonies of Great Britain. The most important 
                of these, exclusive of India, are 
                managed under the supreme direction of the 
                British government, by governors appointed 
                by the king, and by legislative bodies, raised 
                within themselves, and resembling the British 
                Parliament. The revenue of the home 
                country is nevertheless employed in protecting 
                and fostering these dependencies, which 
                have been ascertained to cost considerably 
                more, year by year, than any direct profit 
                which can be derived from the commerce 
                which they carry on with British merchants.</p>
            <p>The army of Great Britain has always 
                maintained a high reputation for valour, 
                good conduct, and fortitude; and her navy, 
                unequalled in the annals of the world, has 
                afforded the means of protecting her commerce, 
                and securing her possessions in the 
                most distant quarters of the globe. The 
                number of land forces at home and abroad 
                during the year 1836—7 was 101,089; 
                and the charge for their maintenance was 
                L3,330,420. Of these forces, one fifih was 
                employed in the East Indies; and the rest 
                in the United Kingdom and foreign stations.</p>
            <p>The navy of Great Britain in 1835 consisted 
                of 443 ships of various descriptions, 
                namely, 15 ships of the first rate, 19 of the 
                second, 55 of the third, 22 of the fourth, 
                81 of the fifth, 26 of the sixth, and 225 
                small vessels. The number of seamen 
                and marines was 26,500, and the charge 
                4,245,723 pd. st.</p>
            <p>Ships of the first rate are all three-decked 
                and carry at least 100 guns, and 800 men; 
                those of the second rate carry at least 80 
                guns, and 700 men; the third, at least 70 guns, 
                and 600 men; the fourth, at least 50 
                guns, and 400 men; the fifth, at least 36 
                guns, and 250 men; and the sixth, at least 
                24 guns, and under 250 men.</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf003r" facs="duk.00037.003.jpg" type="recto"/>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left"><handShift new="#h2"/>679</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top">CHAMBERS.</fw>
            <cb n="1"/>
            <p>The navy employed in peace is composed 
                of only 10 or 12 ships of the line, and 
                twice as many frigates, sloops, and other 
                vessels.</p>
            <p>A distinguishing feature in the organisation 
                of the British army and navy, is the 
                care taken of the men. Few nations so generously 
                clothe, feed, pay, and otherwise 
                render comfortable their soldiers and sailors, 
                as the British.</p>
            <p>Justice, civil and criminal, is administered 
                in England and Ireland according to laws 
                and forms which took their rise in the former 
                country, and were in time extended to the 
                latter. The English law, as it is comprehensively 
                termed, is of two kinds-written 
                or statu<note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="inline">˄</note>e
                law, consisting of the laws established 
                by acts of Parliament—and consuetudinary 
                law, consisting of customs which 
                have existed from time immemorial, and 
                have received the sanction of the judges. 
                Consuetudinary law is again divided into 
                common law and equity; the former is administered 
                by courts which profess to adhere 
                strictly to the old laws of England, except 
                in as far as they are altered by statu<note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="inline">˄</note>e; 
                the latter was founded upon the principle that 
                the king, in cases of hardship, was entitled 
                to give relief from the strictness of the common 
                law. Equity, though thus originated, 
                has now become also a fixed kind of law, 
                and is administered in courts which decide 
                according to established rules.</p>
            <p>The principal court for civil suits, is the 
                Court of Common Pleas. The Court of 
                King's (or Queen’s) Bench, which was at 
                first only a criminal tribunal, and the Court 
                of Exchequer, which was designed only to 
                decide in cases concerning the revenue, have 
                become civil courts by means of fictions in 
                their respective modes of procedure. The 
                court of Chancery, presided over by the 
                Lord Chancellor, administers the law of 
                equity. Courts under these designations sit 
                both in Westminster and in Dublin: there 
                are also courts of assize, which, in England, 
                perform six provincial circuits, in some instances 
                once, and in others twice a-year. 
                Minor cases, criminal as well as civil, are 
                judged by bodies of provincial magistracy, 
                who meet in every county once every quarter 
                of a year. Besides the civil and criminal 
                tribunals, there are Ecclesiastical Courts, 
                which have jurisdiction in matters connected 
                with marriage, wills, etc. and adopt the 
                principles of the old canon law. There are 
                also Courts of Admiralty, which decide
                <cb n="2"/>questions between persons of different nations,
                according to the code of civil law recognised 
                throughout Europe.</p>
            <p>Guernsey, Jersey, Alderney, and other 
                small islands in the British Channel, which 
                politically belong to the United Kingdom, 
                possess a variety of peculiar privileges and 
                legal usages. The Isle of Man, situated in 
                the sea between England and Ireland, likewise 
                possesses certain peculiar privileges.</p>
            <p>In Scotland, laws peculiar to itself founded 
                upon the principles of the Roman and the 
                Feudal law, are administered by a supreme 
                civil tribunal, denominated the Court of 
                Session, which remains fixed at Edinburgh, 
                and by a criminal tribunal, named the Court 
                of Justiciary, which not only sits in the 
                same city, but makes circuits through the 
                provinces. Minor civil and criminal cases 
                are also judged in Scotland by the sheriffs 
                of the various counties, and the magistrates 
                of the boroughs.</p>
            <p>Scotland possesses the advantage of public 
                prosecution of offences, the injured party 
                being only a complainer to the public prosecutor. 
                The chief public prosecutor is the 
                Lord Advocate; the inferior public prosecutors, 
                in connexion with the various minor 
                courts, are termed procurators-fiscal. The 
                whole expense of prosecution is defrayed by 
                the national exchequer.</p>
            <p>The peculiar boast of the criminal law 
                of the British Empire, is the Jury. In 
                England and Ireland, where the principle 
                of the criminal law requires the injured 
                party or his representative to prosecute, he 
                can only do so by permission of a jury of 
                accusation, called the Grand Jury; another 
                jury sits for the purpose of deciding if the 
                evidence against the accused has established 
                the guilt. These juries consist in England 
                and Ireland of twelve men, whose verdict 
                must be unanimous; in Scotland, the jury 
                upon the charge consists of fifteen men, 
                who decide by a plurality of votes. 
                <hi rend="underline" hand="h1">The jury is an institution 
                    of Scandinavian origin, transmitted to Britain through 
                    the Saxons,</hi> and it is justly considered as a most 
                efficient protection of the subject from the vindictiveness
                of power.<!-- Looks like the remainder of this line ("and it is... vindictiveness of power") 
                    was once underlined, but then sloppily erased. 
                    Not sure if that counts as a deletion or an underline 
                    because the line can still somewhat be made out.--> 
                Civil cases, turning upon matters of fact, are also decided 
                in all parts of the United Kingdom by juries.</p>
            <p>The House of Lords, as the great council 
                of the king, acts as a court of last appeal 
                from the civil tribunals of Britain and Ireland. 
                Practically, the business of hearing 
                these appeals is undertaken by some law</p>
            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="duk.00037.004.jpg" type="verso"/>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">680</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top">CHAMBERS.</fw>
            <cb n="1"/>
            <p>lord, such as the Lord Chancellor, who, as 
                there must be three persons present, is 
                usually accompanied by a temporal peer and 
                a bishop. Before deciding, the House sometimes 
                demands the opinions of the English judges.</p>
            <p>The laws and judicial usages of England 
                and Ireland are extended to most of 
                the colonial possessions, along with all the 
                rights and privileges which are common to 
                British subjects. Hence, the inhabitants 
                of the most distant part of the empire, 
                whatever be their origin, rank, or colour, 
                are entitled by the constitution to enjoy the 
                same degree of civil and religous liberty, 
                and the same careful protection of life and 
                property, as their fellow-subjects in the 
                mother country. This is an invaluable boon, 
                for in no nation do the people practically 
                enjoy greater liberty of speech or action 
                (without licentiousness), and in none is the 
                press more unshackled. Next in point of 
                value to the privilege of trial by jury, the 
                British subject places the right of petition 
                to the Houses of Parliament, either for an 
                improvement in the laws or a redress of 
                grievances. As this involves the right of 
                assembling publicly in a peaceful manner, 
                or of meeting constitutionally, to discuss 
                measures of government and legislation, it 
                is allowed to form the impregnable bulwark 
                of British political freedom.</p>
            <p>All classes of religious thinkers receive 
                toleration from the British government, except 
                those who openly offend against public 
                decency and the public peace. In England 
                and Ireland, the Protestant Episcopalian 
                form of church government and worship is 
                established in intimate alliance with the 
                state, the king being its supreme head, 
                with a hierarchy composed of archbishops, 
                bishops, deans, and sub-deans; in Scotland, 
                the established religion is the Protestant 
                Presbyterian, the clergy of which are all 
                equal, and have no authorities but those 
                which they form collectively in their own courts.</p>
            <p>In England, the established church comprehends 
                nearly twelve thousand places of 
                worship. The church in Ireland numbers 
                thirteen hundred and eighty-five benefices, 
                distributed over two thousand three hundred 
                and forty-eight parishes; while the Scottish 
                Presbyterian establishment embraces eleven 
                hundred churches, in about one thousand 
                parishes. The established clergy of the 
                three kingdoms are supported by public <cb n="2"/> 
                funds, chiefly arising from the fruits of the 
                earth; and hence their congregations in 
                general enjoy their ministrations gratuitously. 
                Nevertheless, a large proportion of the 
                middle and lower classes of the people in 
                the three kingdoms prefer supporting, by 
                direct contribution, religious ministrations 
                more accordant with their peculiar opinions.</p>
            <p>In England and Scotland the dissenters 
                are chiefly Protestants, acknowledging the 
                same points of faith with the members of 
                the established churches, but disapproving 
                of their alliance with the state. The Protestant 
                Dissenters of England have nearly 
                eight thousand places of worship; those of 
                Scotland nearly eight hundred. In England 
                and Scotland, the Catholic places of 
                worship amount to about four hundred and 
                seventy. In Ireland, the population is 
                divided into seven hundred and fifty-two 
                thousand persons in connexion with the established 
                church, about a hundred thousand 
                Methodists, six hundred and forty-two thousand 
                Presbyterians, and nearly six millions 
                and a half of Catholics.</p>
            <p>According to the constitution, wherever 
                Britain establishes her civil authority, there 
                also is established the Protestant Episcopalian 
                form of church government and worship, 
                except in cases where provision to the 
                contrary has been made by terms of capitulation. 
                Practically , however, there is perfect 
                freedom in the exercise of religious belief 
                and worship in all parts of the empire. 
                In Lower Canada and Malta, Roman Catholicism; 
                in Hindustan, Brahminism and 
                Mahommedanism; and in Ceylon, the religion 
                of Buddha—prevail. The Protestant 
                Presbyterian form of church govement 
                and worship, similar to that of Scotland, 
                predominates in the Cape of Good Hope, 
                according to agreement with the former 
                Dutch occupants.</p>
            <p>The chief institutions for education in 
                England are the Universities of Oxford and 
                Cambridge, the London University, and 
                King’s College, in the metropolis; various 
                free grammar-schools of ancient date, and a 
                vast number of ordinary schools, supported 
                by endowments, by private charity, or by 
                the fees of the scholars.</p>
            <div2 type="section">
            <p>The chief educational establishment in 
                Ireland is Trinity College in Dublin. Ireland 
                has other important seminaries of 
                learning; and possesses a large variety of</p>
            <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="bottom">
                elementary schools.</note>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h1" place="bottom">Chief educational establishments <lb/>
                    in Scotland are the universities of Edinbu<gap reason="cut away"/><lb/>
                Glasgow, Aberdeen, &amp; St. Andrews—<lb/>
                    Every parish is also provided with an<lb/>
                elementary school supported by endowm<gap reason="cut away"/></note>
            </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>