<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.6.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml" ?><?oxygen SCHSchema="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/downloads/whitmanarchive_rules_mss.sch" ?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="duk.00038">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="m" type="main">Imagination and Fact</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">a machine readable transcription</title>
                <author xml:id="ww">Walt Whitman</author>
                <author xml:id="unk1">["W.D."]</author>
                <author xml:id="unk2">Anonymous</author>
                <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
                <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="ano">Alejandro Omidsalar</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="mc">Matt Cohen</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <sponsor>University of Texas at Austin</sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
                <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>2015</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                
                <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>kprice@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Ed-Folsom@uiowa.edu</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>bbarney2@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>The text of the original document is in the public domain. Subject to certain exceptions, public domain works may be 
                        freely copied or used in the creation of derivative works without permission, or authorization, of the former copyright owners.</p>
                    <p>The text encoding was created and/or prepared by the Walt Whitman Archive and is governed by a
                        <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                            Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License
                        </ref>
                        (CC BY 4.0).</p>
                    <p>Permission to reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted 
                        by the owners of the originals for this publication only.</p>
                </availability>
            <idno>duk.00038</idno></publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="project">At one point, this manuscript likely formed part of <ref target="../index-scrapbook.html">Whitman's cultural geography scrapbook</ref>.</note>             
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Walt Whitman</author>
                    <title>Excerpt from Graham's Illustrated Magazine of Literature, Romance, Art, and Fashion</title>
                    <idno type="callno">MS q 186</idno>
                    <date notBefore="1852-01-01" notAfter="1892-03-26">1852 or later</date>
                    <orgName xml:id="duk">Trent Collection of Whitmaniana, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book &amp; Manuscript Library, Duke University</orgName>
                    <note type="project">Transcribed from digital images of the original item. Floyd Stovall in <hi rend="italic">The Foreground of Leaves of Grass</hi> points out that this is a revised reprint of an article by the same title published by the <hi rend="italic">American Whig Review</hi> in November 1851 and signed "W. D."</note>
                </bibl>
                
                <bibl type="base" xml:id="r1">
                    <author>Anonymous ["W.D."]</author>
                    <title level="a">Imagination and Fact</title>
                    <title level="j">Graham's Illustrated Magazine of Literature, Romance, Art, and Fashion</title>
                    <date when="1852-01">January 1852</date>
                    <publisher>G.R. Graham</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                    <biblScope unit="pp">39–44</biblScope>
                </bibl>
                
                <bibl type="pasteon" xml:id="r2">
                    <author>Unknown</author>
                    <title level="a">Enquirer, De Soto</title>
                    <title level="j">Uknown</title>
                    <date>Unknown</date>
                    <publisher>Uknown</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Unknown</pubPlace>
                    <!--<biblScope unit="pp"></biblScope>-->
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <handNotes>
                <handNote xml:id="h1" scribeRef="#ww" medium="pencil"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h2" scribeRef="#unk1" medium="typescript"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h3" scribeRef="#ww" medium="brown-ink"/>
                <handNote xml:id="h4" scribeRef="#unk2" medium="typescript"/>
            </handNotes>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="#km" when="2019-10-15">proofed</change>
            <change who="#mc" when="2015-10-21">Proofed</change>
            <change who="#ano" when="2015-09-17">Transcribed and encoded</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text type="marginalia">
        <body>
            <div1>
            <pb xml:id="leaf001r" facs="duk.00038.001.jpg" type="recto"/>
            
            <add rend="pasteon" source="#r2"><handShift new="#h4"/><!-- need to find the source of this clipping and include it in <bibl> in header. KM -->
                <q type="written">
                    <floatingText rend="flat">
                        <body>
                            <pb xml:id="leaf002r" facs="duk.00038.001a.jpg" type="recto"/>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">ENQUIRER</hi>, De Soto.—<hi rend="italic">"What is meant by the Seven Wonders
                            of the World?".... The pyramids of Egypt, the walls
                            and hanging gardens of Babylon, the temple of Diana at
                            Ephesus, the statue of the Olympian Jupiter, the Mausoleum,
                            (a sumptuous sepulchre erected to King Mausolus
                            by his wife, B.C. 353,) and the Colossus of Rhodes</hi>.</p>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                </q>
            </add>
            
            <note type="authorial" place="top" resp="#h1">Of the truth in History</note>
            
            <head>IMAGINATION AND FACT.</head>
            
            <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
            
            <byline><hi rend="smallcaps">BY A NEW CONTRIBUTOR.</hi></byline>
            
            <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
            
                <epigraph>
                    <lg type="linegroup">
                        <l>Imagination's world of air,</l>
                        <l>And our own world. <hi rend="smallcaps">HALLECK.</hi></l>
                    </lg>
                    
                    <lg type="linegroup">
                        <l>The world is of such stuff</l>
                        <l>As dreams are made of, and our little life</l>
                        <l>Is bounded by a sleep. <hi rend="smallcaps"><choice><orig>SHAKSPEARE.</orig><reg>Shakespeare</reg></choice></hi></l>
                    </lg>
                    
                    <lg type="linegroup">
                        <l>S'ai che la corre il mondo ove piu versi</l>
                        <l>Di sue dolcezze il lusinghier Parnaso</l>
                        <l>E che 'l vero condito in molli versi,</l>
                        <l>I piu schivi allentando ha persuaso. <hi rend="smallcaps">TASSO.</hi></l>
                    </lg>
                </epigraph>
       
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">PEOPLE</hi> seem to have an idea that facts are every
            thing in the business of the world—the only 
            considerations in the philosophy of human progress.
            Opposed to what is merely imaginary, facts are
            allowed to have much dignity. Your practical
            reasoners look for facts; facts "are the jockies for 
            them"—such as they can see, hear, handle, or 
            demonstrate; while the imaginations are mostly held
            synonymous with the worthless, the unsubstantial
            and the ridiculous. They seem to say in the spirit
            of one of Congreve's characters—we forget which—
            "fiddle-faddle, don't tell me of this and that and
            every thing in the world; but give me mathematical demonstration; but we
            think "under leave of Brutus and the rest," that
            facts do not seem, and have not seemed to be so 
            exclusively essential to "the cosmogony of the 
            world," to the history and progress of mind and the
            general business of things, as some solid authorities
            think. Without troubling our heads, in this gossiping 
            paper, with the subtleties of Berkley and others,
            who knock all creation into the compass of a man's 
            perceptions—establish the column of the unsubstantial
            universe on the pentagonal base of the senses—
            we have an idea that a vast amount of the fictitious 
            and imaginary is blended with our regular business
            of being, doing, and suffering. Human nature has, in
            all times, contrived a little gilding, to make the bitter 
            pill of life go down. Tasso truly says—in his Invocation
            to the Virgin Mary for a muse—at the opening
            of his "Gerusalemme Liberata"—</p>
            
            <q who="Tasso" type="extract">
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <lg type="linegroup">
                            <l>For well thou knowest, the world more fondly turns</l>
                            <l>To old Parnassus' consecrated spot;</l>
                            <l>And truths which graceful poetry adorns</l>
                            <l>Win while they please us; and a spell is wrought</l>
                            <l>For the most subtle and reluctant thought.</l>
                            <l>Thus, for the sickly child, by friendly wile,</l>
                            <l>The cup's deceptive edge, with sweetness fraught,</l>
                            <l>Lures to the bitter potion—he the while</l>
                            <l>Drinks life and health from the judicious guile.</l>
                        </lg>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </q>
            
            <p>Not alone have the edges of the cup of life been
            touched in this way, but the contents of it have
            always been dashed with large doses of the same
            emollient. Reality is not such a delightful thing,
            after all. The false and the phantasmal have ever
            been considered the necessary complements, as it
            were, of our condition here.</p>
            
            <cb/>
            
            <p>If we take away from the amount of what the
            world possesses that which belongs and is due to the
            imagination merely—what is not authentic, and
            could not be sworn to in a court of justice—what
            will be left? Let us take it away—and what then?
            There is a sudden solitude in the world. The beautiful 
            is vanished, and the hard, blank remnant of 
            things is full of gaps, and desert places, disastrous
            flaws and a strange silence. There is nothing now,
            but facts in this macrocosm. But, believe us, 't is a
            very rude, cold place to live in—much worse than
            ever it was before; and that—in the opinion of the
            pale pessimist over the way there—was bad enough
            in all conscience. They who first found out this
            world, and roamed about on it, had scarcely called it
            very good when they began to make it better, by
            peopling its too extensive solitudes—creating phantasms
            and imaginations for it, where there were
            none before. The unclothed reality of things was
            too bare and blank, beautiful as it was, for the first
            human beings that walked the earth. They looked
            to the elements, and the infinite host of heaven, and
            following their unanswerable instincts, they began
            to make mysteries, airy fabrics and visions. They 
            imagined a god for the cope and the clouds of the
            firmament, and he wielded the thunderbolts from a
            high mountain; another, shaped after the most
            perfectly formed of men, resided in the sun
            
            <q type="extract">
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <lg type="linegroup">
                            <l>"The lord of life and poesy and light:"</l>
                        </lg>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </q>
                   
            His sister was the goddess of the earth's satellite—
            
            <q type="extract">
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <lg type="linegroup">
                            <l>"Astarte, queen of heaven, with crescent horns,</l>
                            <l>To whose bright image nightly by the moon,</l>
                            <l>Sidonian virgins paid their vows and songs."</l>
                        </lg>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </q>
            </p>
                
            <p>They heard gods in winds and in fire—and altars
                <span rend="wavyLine-right" hand="#h3" xml:id="s1" from="#s1" to="#s2"/>to these were among the earliest raised. They saw
            a terrible divinity in the vastness or angry billows of
            the sea, and imagined a crowd of lesser beings to
            haunt its caverns and depths. The forests were
            sacred to the universal Pan—his fauns, sylvans and
            satyrs; every oak had its hamadryad, every river
            its naiad or potamid; the oreads took charge of the
            flowery meadows, and the napææ wandered forever
            in the shady valleys. Impatient of mere
            reality, men filled the universe with phantasies and
            theories—
            
            <q type="extract">
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <lg>
                            <l>"The intelligible forms of ancient poets—</l>
                            <l>The fair humanities of old religion,</l>
                        </lg>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </q>
            <anchor xml:id="s2"/>
            
            <fw type="pageNum" place="bottom">39</fw>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf003v" facs="duk_ap_00161.jpg" type="verso" n="40"/>
                
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">40</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top">GRAHAM'S MAGAZINE.</fw>

            <q type="extract">
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <lg>
                            <l>The power, the beauty and the majesty</l>
                            <l>That had their haunts in dale or piny mountain,</l>
                            <l>Or forest, by slow stream, or pebbly spring,</l>
                            <l>Or chasms or watery depths."</l>
                        </lg>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </q>
            </p>
            
            <p>Suppose we demolish all these graceful fallacies, 
            and the poetry, also, in which they are embalmed. 
            What a throng of splendid deeds, of heroic and beautiful 
            figures—demigods, warriors, kings—bright 
            women and brave men, moving in gorgeous panorama 
            over the vast back-ground of antiquity—is 
            extinguished in the darkness! The creations of the 
            ancient poets and imaginative writers have filled up a 
            space in the earlier ages of the world, which without 
            them would be a blank and lost to the human mind, 
            as much as the pre-Adamite chaos is. What a 
            disinheritance it would be to take away the Iliad and 
            Odyssey! to obliterate Hector, the kind-hearted and 
            manly hero; and Priam with his mighty sorrows a 
            suppliant for his dead son; and the warring Achilles—

                <q type="extract">
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <lg type="linegroup">
                            <l>"Impiger, iracundus, inexorabilis, acer,"</l>
                        </lg>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </q>
            
            and the wandering Ulysses, seeing strange shores 
            and cities, and the varying manners of men! Not 
            alone would much be wanted in the want of these 
            venerable works, but in the want of all that literature 
            which they inspired and gave rise to in after 
            time. The succeeding poets and dramatists of 
            Greece and Rome drew light from Homer, as Milton's 
            stars did in their golden urns from the sun. 
            They took his historic imaginations and characters 
            as their models, and reproduced them in forms which 
            the world will not willingly let die, and which it 
            prizes nearly as much as the Institutes and Pandects 
            of Justinian, or any thing else of that authentic and 
            substantial kind.</p>
            
            <p>To come to our own familiar literature, the 
            fictions of our insular or continental writers are as 
            favorably and generally remembered as the historic 
            facts of the English-speaking peoples. In our genial 
            moments, when the mind desires to be refreshed or 
            pleased it will revert, with an almost universal 
            preference, to what is imaginary, or adorned with the 
            graces of imaginative literature; and half the world 
            regard with as much attention the men and women 
            of <choice><orig>Shakspeare</orig><reg>Shakespeare</reg></choice> and Scott as those of Hume and Prescott. 
            And how intimately and lovingly we give our 
            interest to the words and actions of these imaginary 
            beings! What a world of thought and life is in the 
            dramas of <choice><orig>Shakspeare</orig><reg>Shakespeare</reg></choice>! There is the venerable 
            Lear, driven out into the storm, and talking the 
            finest philosophy to the wild elements, that so feelingly 
            persuade him what he is; and Hamlet, so 
            sententious in his antic disposition; the fair Ophelia, and 
            the prosy old courtier, Polonius; and the immortal 
            bed-presser, and huge hill of flesh—the greatest liar 
            and the greatest favorite in the world; and Macbeth, 
            with his terrible hags on the heath, and his more 
            terrible wife; and Richard, wooing Lady Anne, or 
            fighting desperately his last battle. Then there are 
            the witty and adventurous Rosalind, and

            <q type="extract">
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <lg type="linegroup">
                            <l>"The gentle lady wedded to the Moor;"</l>
                        </lg>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </q>
  
            and Portia, the beautiful, wise young judge; and the<cb/>
            impassioned Juliet, with the southern lightnings in 
            her veins; and Miranda, the enchantress, of an 
            enchanted island—and all that magnificent array of 
            womanhood which reflects for ever the unequaled genius of 
            <choice><orig>Shakspeare</orig><reg>Shakespeare</reg></choice>.</p>
            
            <p>We have also the creations of Scott—coming 
            nearest of any to those of the great dramatic poet, 
            and enjoying even a more general popularity. 
            Successive generations prize them as an imperishable 
            legacy, and the memory has a pleasure in conjuring 
            them up—so vivid and picturesque in their colors 
            and outlines: The hall of Cedric, the Saxon—the 
            swineherd, the templar, the gorgeous tournament at 
            Ashby de la Zouche, Friar Tuck, the storming of 
            Torquilstone, the Black Knight, fighting as if ten 
            men's strength were in his single arm; and the beautiful 
            Jewess—what splendid series of images—
            bringing back so vividly the old pomp and circumstance 
            of the feudal times! We shall never forget 
            the feelings with which we first read Ivanhoe, and 
            there found all our vague feelings of romance and 
            dreams of knightly doings put into such spirit-stirring 
            expression. Then how true is the picturesque 
            bravery of Fergus McIvor—
            
            
            <q type="extract">
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <lg type="linegroup">
                            <l>"All plaided and plumed in his tartan array;"</l>
                        </lg>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </q>
                
            and the marching of the Scottish clans; the fine old 
            Baron Bradwardine, the high-spirited Flora, and the 
            tender Rose. We see the fierce Balfour of Burley, 
            slaying the guardsman at Drumclog, or raving in his 
            cave; and the swords of the Solemn League and 
            Covenant waving in desperate tumult on Bothwell 
            Bridge. Edgar and Lucy walk to the haunted 
            spring, Caleb Balderstone performs laughable 
            prodigies of cunning to save the credit of Wolf's Crag, 
            and the last Lord of Ravenswood disappears awfully 
            into the "Kelpie's flow,"
            
            <q type="extract">
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <lg type="single-line">
                            <l>"And his name is lost for ever moe."</l>
                        </lg>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </q>
            </p>
                
            <p>Norna of the Fitful-Head, speaks her wild rune of 
            the <hi rend="italic">reimkennar</hi> to the spirits of the North wind; 
            "bold Magnus, the son of the earl;" Minna, Brenda, 
            Cleveland, Claude Halcro, feast, love, fight and 
            rhyme in the Udaller's charmed isle. Diana Vernon, 
            on horseback, clears her five-barred gate and gallops 
            by; Rob Roy cries "claymore," and Bailie Nichol 
            Jarvie fights his highlandman with a hot coulter, and 
            goes up perilously to the Clachan of Aberfoil; 
            Jeannie Deans stands in the presence of Queen Caroline, 
            pleading for the life of her sister, while the 
            Duke of Argyle puts his hand to his chin whenever 
            her Majesty or the Duchess of Suffolk are in danger 
            of a random hit from the lips of the unconscious 
            advocate; Monkbarn's discovers the remains of a 
            Roman <hi rend="italic">prŀtorium</hi>, and Edie Ochiltree comes up 
            and says: "Prætorium here, prætorium there; I 
            mind the bigging o't!" The Knight of the Leopard 
            and the disguised Soldan fight their chivalrous duel 
            in the desert, and then feast together at the spring, 
            and Richard Plantagenet, leaping from his sick-bed, 
            in spite of the Hakim, tears down the standard of 
            Austria from the mound at Acre, and hurls the giant 
            Wallenrode from the top to the bottom of it. Dominic
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf004r" facs="duk.00038.002.jpg" type="recto" n="41"/>
            
            <fw type="header" place="top">IMAGINATION AND FACT.</fw>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">41</fw>
         
            
            Sampson exclaims "prodigious!"—Dirk 
            Hatterick strangles Glossin and shoots Charlotte 
            Cushman—Meg Merrilies we should say, but it is all one
            —who recognizes young Bertram and dies hard.
            Hal o' the Wynd "fights for his own band" on the
            Inch of Perth, in the melée of the clans Chattan and
            Quhule. Tristram l' Hermit, hangs the trees around
            Plessis les Tours with Zingaris, like acorns. Louis
            and Charles the Bold ride together into Liege by a 
            breach in the walls, and the head of the savage De
            Lamarek secures to the Scottish soldier the hand of
            Isable Croye. The Highland Widow mourns over
            her condemned son with all the tragic truth of 
            Æschylus or nature; the Last Minstrel sings a wild
            epic of goblin gramarye—the Leaguer of Branksome
            —knights and ladies—the lists and the festival.
            Roderick and the Knight of Snowdon fight by the 
            ford of Coilantogle; Constance perishes awfully in
            her convent cell, and Marmion dies like a courageous
            knight, at Flodden
            
                <q type="extract">
                    <floatingText>
                        <body>
                            <lg type="linegroup">
                                <l>"Charge, Chester, charge; on Stanley, on—</l>
                                <l>Where the last words of Marmion!"</l>
                            </lg>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                </q>
            </p>
                
            <p>All these, and more, come thronging at the call of
            the wizard And with them will also pass before the
            reader's or muser's eye the extravagant hero of
            him who "smiled Spain's chivalry away;" Doctor
            Primrose and his delightful family, Parson Adams, 
            Sir Roger de Coverley, Evangeline, Ichabod Crane,
            and a thousand others, which every body's memory
            will distinguish for itself—just as every eye shapes 
            its proper rainbow. They have all the distinctness
            of reality, and it is by an effort that we draw the
            line between them and <hi rend="italic">bona fide</hi> characters.</p>
            
            <p>Many of these last, in fact, are little better than the 
            fictions of poets, dramatists and romancers. The
            histories of the venerable Bede, Geoffrey of Monmouth,
            etc. are half imaginative. There are outlines 
            of truth in them—
            
            <q type="extract">
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <lg type="linegroup">
                            <l>"The truth is there; but dashed and brewed with lies."</l>
                        </lg>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </q>
            </p>
            
            <p>The history of Scotland, for ages, from the reign of 
                Fergus, and of Ireland from the days of Heber, Heremon 
            and Ith, down to the conquest of the country by
            Strongbow, are just as fanciful as the metrical
            romances of Scott and Moore. Then, for the annals 
            of Greece; Herodotus, the patriarch of history, sets
            down almost every thing he hears from the lying 
            priests of Egypt, or that he can gather from vague
            tradition; and people don't exactly know whether 
            to call the Cyropædia of Xenophon a romance or an
            authentic narration. Plutarch romances at times
            like the Scuderis. An old English author, Taylor,
            says, of his fallacies and blunders in the lives of the
            orators—<hi rend="italic">mendaxille Plutarchus qui vitas oratorum
            dolis et erroribus consutas, olim conscribillavit</hi>.
            Neibuhr has got into our old history of Rome and
            laid about him like an iconoclast. He destroys a
            crowd of our beliefs, and makes a solitude in the first 
            ages of Rome—so wonderful and picturesque in our 
            school-boy days. He makes a solitude and calls it 
            truth. He demolishes Mars, Rhea Sylvia, Romulus
            and Remus and the Wolf—Numitor, Evander, and so
            forth. Under the flourishing of his pen they make
            <cb/>
            themselves into thin air in which they vanish. Then
            the Tarquins, their insolence and expulsion; Lars
            Porsenna of Clusium, the siege of Rome, Cocles on
            the Bridge and Scævola at the flaming Altar—all are
            inventions of Fabius Pictor, Ennius, Nævius, and
            others. This portion of the history of Rome, says
            the German, should be called the Lay of the Tarquins,
            and is just as authentic as the Lay of the Nibelungen!
            "Livy's <hi rend="italic">pictored</hi> page," (if we may be
            permitted to make a critical emendation of Byron's
            phrase in the spirit of Bishop Warburton's Notes on
                <choice>
                    <orig>Shakspeare.</orig>
                    <reg>Shakespeare</reg>
                </choice>,) is allowed to be just as fallible as it is
            brilliant. Thus we have a vast amount of what is 
            called ancient history confounded with the professed
            creations of fanciful minds; and there does not seem
            to be any very marked difference between Agamemnon
            or Ajax, and Cecrops or Codrus; between
            Æneas or Dido, and Numa or Clelia—they are all
            equally distinct or indistinct. Scott's King Richard,
            singing a roundelay and exchanging a buffet with the 
            Clerk of Copmanhurst, is as firm on the canvas as
            Alfred baking his cakes, or Canute sitting on a chair
            to rebuke his flatterers on the sea-shore.</p>
            
            <p>And even as regards the more modern and authentic
            annals of history, we do not think they have
            paid much more respect to the actual truth of things
                <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h3" xml:id="s3" from="#s3" to="#s4"/>
                than do the fictionists. Sir Robert Walpole used to
            say to his friends, "Don't read history; that <hi rend="underline" hand="#h3">must</hi> 
            be false." And Sir Walter Raleigh, looking from the
            window of his prison in the Tower, and witnessing<anchor xml:id="s4"/>
            a quarrel in the court-yard or the street, and the after-
            testimony of the by-standers respecting it, was
            tempted, it is said, to throw his History of the 
            World into the fire, in despair of ever being able to
            gather any thing like truth from conflicting authorities.
            And, certainly, the differences of historians—
            their doubts concerning motives, and their disagreements
            concerning facts, tend to give us very unsettled 
            ideas of history in general. Writers have 
            sent Col. Kirke down to us from James the Second's
            reign with a very black and bloody renown. But
            he was not half so black as he was painted by the
            whigs; and the story of the poor girl whose husband
            he hanged before her eyes, in the morning, though she
            dearly purchased his life on Kirke's own terms, is
            pronounced by Ritson to be an impudent and bare-faced
                <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h3" xml:id="s5" from="#s5" to="#s6"/>
                lie. The story is much older than Kirke.
            Richard the Third is also one of the historical
            reprobates; though it is not unlikely that the young
            princes were not murdered in the Tower, and that
            Perkin Warbeck was really the prince after all; as
            truly as the surreptitious, warming-pan prince is
            known to have been the true son of James the<anchor xml:id="s6"/> 
                <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h3" xml:id="s7" from="#s7" to="#s8"/>
                Second, in spite of the Protestant historians. Then
                there are Jack Cade and Wat Tyler; these have
                been receiving cruel wrong at the hands of the 
                annalists. They dared, in an age when the rights of
                the people were imperfectly understood, and the influence
                of the feudal system still strong in the nation,
                to take up arms and go to war with the king and the
                nobles for liberty! Their sufferings and and provocations<anchor xml:id="s8"/>
                were undeniable, and their spirit was certainly heroic
                —kindred to that which glowed in the bosoms of
                
            <pb xml:id="leaf004v" facs="duk.00038.003.jpg" type="verso"/>
                
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">42</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top">GRAHAM'S MAGAZINE.</fw>
            <cb/>
            
            Melchthal, Furst, and Stauffacher, at the Brunnens
            of Grutli. The Swiss peasants were successful, and
            are held in honorable remembrance forever. But the
            Englishmen failed, and are set up as scarecrows and
            <hi rend="italic">ludibria</hi>, upon the field of history. Poor Tyler and
            Cade were animated by the same kind of blood
            which boiled in the face of a tyrant at Naseby,
                <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h3" xml:id="s9" from="#s9" to="#s10"/>Marston Moor, Dunbar, and elsewhere—which
            warmed the hearts of the exiles on the cold rock
            of Plymouth, and flowed so freely at Lexington and
            Bunker Hill. We should honor these English rebels
            —in spite of history, and in spite of <choice>
                <orig>Shakspeare.</orig>
                <reg>Shakespeare.</reg>
            </choice> It
            is remarkable to see this myriad-minded man, so full of the finer humanities of our nature, yet incapable
            of sympathizing with the cause and feelings of the
            mass of the lower classes. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h3">But <choice>
                <orig>Shakspeare</orig>
                <reg>Shakespeare</reg>
            </choice> was a man of his era—to which, with an astonishing and
            happy wizardry, he obliged chronology and human
            nature to conform; he dreamed as little of the later
            evangils of democracy as he did of the Daguerreotype
            and the electric telegraph.</hi> In this way Cade,
            Richard, and a thousand others are in the hands of 
            the historians, tricked out as much in the colors of
            imagination as in those of fact.</p>
            
            <p>No man can be sure of the lesser details of the
            annals, though he may put faith in some of their
            great facts. We are not indisposed to allow that
            there was a man named Julius Cæsar; though
            whether he ever said, <hi rend="italic">Quid times? vehis Cæzarem</hi>,
                in the boat, or <hi rend="italic">Et tu Brute!</hi><anchor xml:id="s10"/> when the republicans
            set upon him in the senate-house, is not quite so
            credible. Most of these picturesque properties of
            character or fact, so to speak, are furnished by the
            fancies and after-thoughts of the narrators, or fabricated
            wilfully for a purpose. We need not go very
            far back in history to discover the truth of this. In a
                <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h3" xml:id="s11" from="#s11" to="#s12"/>late memoir (Achille de Vaulabelle's) of the "Two
            Restorations," we are told that an old story of the 
            consternation of the members of the Directory, on its
            violent dissolution by Bonaparte, in 1800, was a false 
            one. There was no hurry-skurry, nor jumping out
            of windows, any more than when Oliver Cromwell
            put an end to the Long Parliament. Again, that
            glorification made on the sinking of the <hi rend="italic">Vengeur</hi>, in<anchor xml:id="s12"/>
            an engagement with the English fleet, during the
            first French revolution, has been latterly put out of
                <span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h3" xml:id="s13" from="#s13" to="#s14"/>
                countenance. The story in France was, that, being
            terribly damaged, this ship sunk with all on board,
            her flag flying, and the crew shouting, "Long live
            the republic!" Carlyle adopted this version in his 
            history, and makes quite a cartoon of it, in his own
            outlandish phraseology. But on the appearance of
            the story in an English work, a naval officer who
            witnessed the affair of the <hi rend="italic">Vengeur</hi>, wrote a letter to
            the Times, in which he stated that, instead of going
            down with true republican devotion, the poor French
            sailors, small blame to them! jumped overboard, and 
            tried to save themselves, and that some hundreds of<anchor xml:id="s14"/>
                <span rend="bracket-right" hand="#h3" xml:id="s15" from="#s15" to="#s16"/>
                them were rescued in the British boats. That message,
            said to have come from the dying Dessaix to
            Bonaparte, on the field of Marengo, ("Tell the First
            Consul I die regretting I can no farther serve him
            and France,") <hi rend="underline" hand="#h3" xml:id="s17">was fabricated in the bulletin by the</hi><anchor xml:id="s16"/>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h3" place="bottom left" target="#s17">☝</note>
                <cb/>
                <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h3" xml:id="s18" from="#s18" to="#s19"/><span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h3" xml:id="s20" from="#s20" to="#s21"/>
                aforesaid consul himself. The story of the Duke of
                Wellington lying in the hollow square of the Guards 
                at Waterloo, and, on the advance of the French,
                crying, "Up, Guards, and at them!" is as untenable
                as our own famous saying—"A little more grape,
                Captain Bragg!" or the military speeches of the
                great generals of antiquity, as recorded by Tacitus,
                Sallust, Cæsar, and the rest of the writers.<anchor xml:id="s19"/> Then,
            as regards great facts, different nations give different
            accounts. Ask who gained Waterloo? "We did,"<anchor xml:id="s21"/>
            say the Prussians. "We gave vast assistance," say
            the Belgians. Ask John Bull, or rather, don't; his
                answer would be rather brief than polite. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h3" xml:id="s22">We should
                like to see a history of the campaigns in Greece of
                Darius, Xerxes, and Mardonius, written by Persians.</hi><note type="authorial" place="top right" resp="#h3" target="#s22"><hi rend="circled">Yes—an ancient history <hi rend="underline">not</hi><lb/>
                    written by a Greek or Roman<lb/>
                    —what a face that would<lb/>
                    put upon old times</hi></note>
                
                All history is more or less deserving of Sir Robert
                <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h3" xml:id="s23" from="#s23" to="#s24"/>Walpole's designation. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h3">Hume, in one of his letters
                to Robertson, alluding to the publication of Murdin's
                State Papers, which threw unexpected light
                upon the annals, exclaims, "We are all in the 
                wrong!"</hi> And, indeed, Hume himself is among
                those to whom we are mostly indebted for the imaginative<anchor xml:id="s24"/>
                character of history. He had little of the 
                industry of Gibbon, and trusted very much to his own
                sagacity for his views. He was also a tory, and became,
                in his scorn for whiggery, the apologist of the 
                Stuarts. His history is charming as a composition,
                but errs in its colorings of facts and its conclusions
                from them.</p>
            
            <p><span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h3" xml:id="s25" from="#s25" to="#s26"/>
                Imagination, as we have said, seems the complement
                of the world of facts and things, in all mental
                exercises, except the logical and mathematical. If
                we contemplate nature it enhances what we behold.
                <hi rend="underline" hand="#h3" xml:id="s27">The mountains, rivers, forests, and the elements that
                gird them round about, would be only blank conditions of matter, if the mind did not fling its own
                divinity around them.</hi><note type="authorial" resp="#h3" place="right" target="#s27">☜</note>
                <note type="authorial" resp="#h3" place="bottom right" target="#s27"><hi rend="circled">This I think is one of<lb/> 
                    the most indicative <lb/>
                    sentences I ever read.</hi></note> 
                Nature was thus endowed 
                from the beginning—when men heard voices in the
                winds, and the supernatural inhabitants of terra
                firma,<anchor xml:id="s26"/>
                
                <q type="extract">
                    <floatingText>
                        <body>
                            <lg type="linegroup">
                                <l>"Met on the hill, the dale, forest or mead,</l>
                                <l>By paved fountain, or by rushy brook,</l>
                                <l>Or on the beached margent of the sea;"</l>
                            </lg>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                </q>
                
            or, in the train of powerful Poseidon, <note type="authorial" resp="#h3" place="inline">(Po.sid.e.on)</note>
                
                <q type="extract">
                    <floatingText>
                        <body>
                            <lg type="linegroup">
                                <l>"Took in by lot, 'twixt high and nether Jove,</l>
                                <l>Imperial rule of all the sea-girt isles."</l>
                            </lg>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                </q>
                
                And the modern lovers of nature, though they no
                longer recognize the mythologic people of the ancient
            beliefs in her picturesque wildernesses, clothe them
            with the attributes of the mysterious abstract power
            which is over all things. And, in the towering of her
            peaks, the murmur of her forests and seas, the roar of
            her storms, the singing of her nightly stars, they find
            revelations and prophecies of higher and farther existences.
            In this respect, the modern poetry of nature 
            has a nobler scope and purer inspiration than the 
            ancient. Wordsworth and Byron speculate more
            sublimely than Lucretius.</p>
            
            <p>In another sense, the imagination materially 
            imposes upon facts. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h3">In contemplating cities, works of
            art, ruins, or scenes of nature, we almost always 
            appreciate them for the associations that belong to
            them—the imaginations they excite</hi>. Look at a gray
             
            <pb xml:id="leaf005r" facs="duk.00038.004.jpg" type="recto"/>
                
            <fw type="header" place="top">WINTER.</fw>
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top right">43</fw>
            <cb/>
            
            
            bleak sort of plateau between mountains and the
            sea, and you see little to admire. But let somebody
            say, "that is Marathon!" while the blood thrills at
            the name, a flood of glory flashes over the immortal
            ground; the air is thick with phantoms—
            
            <q type="extract">
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <lg type="linegroup">
                            <l>To the hearer's eye appear,</l>
                            <l>The camp, the host, the fight, the conqueror's career—</l>
                            <l>The flying Mede, his shaftless, broken bow;</l>
                            <l>The fiery Greek, his red pursuing spear;</l>
                            <l>Mountains above, earth's, ocean's plain below;</l>
                            <l>Death in the front, destruction in the rear!</l>
                        </lg>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </q>
                
                <span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h3" xml:id="s28" from="#s28" to="#s29"/>
                   <hi rend="underline" hand="#h3">It is this quality of the imagination which gives old
            countries their superior attractions when compared
            with new soils.</hi><anchor xml:id="n2"/> At the sight of battle-fields, religious
            houses, cathedrals, castles, either in ruins or
            otherwise, we are pleased in calling up a crowd of
            shadows from the dust, and finding a sort of mysterious
            companionship with them during our passing
            reveries.</p>
            
            <p><span rend="singleLine-left" hand="#h3" xml:id="s30" from="#s30" to="#s31"/>
                Campbell says very well, that distance lends 
                enchantment to the view, and it is generally true of 
                the human mind that it regards the past with a
                feeling of tenderness—a disposition to make the best
                of it. There is a certain charm in Time, whom we
                regard as the dominator of us all; and the ruins or
                remnants of any thing speak an impressive warning
                of our own evanescent fate. That belief in the
                good old time is an instinct too strong for the 
                philosophy of most of us. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h3">We have a thousand proofs
                that they were rude, bad, ignorant times.</hi> But the
                poetry of our nature will not be reasoned with, and
                we believe with the bard—
                
                <q type="extract">
                    <floatingText>
                        <body>
                            <lg type="linegroup">
                                <l>Not rough or barren are the winding ways</l>
                                <l>Of hoar Antiquity, but strewn with flowers.</l>
                            </lg>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                </q>
            </p><anchor xml:id="s31"/>
            
            <p>Any thing old or historic is appreciated in proportion
                to the scope it gives to the imagination—to
            point a moral or adorn a tale. We gaze on the
            wild hill, vale, stream or forest of a new country,
            with none of those feelings which fill us in beholding
            similar objects in an old land. The former may be
            as fair or fairer to see; but, as
            
            <q type="extract">
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <lg>
                            <l>"A primrose by the river's brim,</l>
                            <l>A yellow primrose was to him."</l>
                        </lg>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </q>
            <cb/>
            
            of whom Wordsworth speaks, so the latter is a
            stream, a forest, a hill—nothing more. The nameless
            savages had the palce from the beginning, and
            the solitude. The other is a tradition, a romance,
            a memory. <hi rend="underline" hand="#h3">In the valley is the legendary well, and
            the fairy ring; by the stream is the fortalice of the
            feudal period, or the abbey dwindled to a few ivied
            walls and the oriel, on the site of a blood battle
            where a king fell fighting, a thousand years ago;
            and, on the slope of the hill stand the Druid stones,
            in a circle, set there, certainly, in the ancient time
            of the giants, who descended from Thor and</hi>

                <q type="extract">
                    <floatingText>
                        <body>
                            <lg type="linegroup">
                                <l>Lived in the oldé days of King <choice><orig>Artour</orig><reg>Arthur</reg></choice>.</l>
                            </lg>
                        </body>
                    </floatingText>
                </q>
            
            As Webster, the old English dramatist, says:
            
            <q type="extract">
                <floatingText>
                    <body>
                        <lg type="linegroup">
                            <l>We love these ancient ruins;</l>
                            <l>We never tread upon them, but we set</l>
                            <l>Our foot upon some reverend history.</l>
                        </lg>
                    </body>
                </floatingText>
            </q> 
            
            They receive all their witchery from the imagination
            of him who surveys them. This faculty is 
            potentially mingled with all that is most real in nature;
            nay, it would seem to be as much a reality as any 
            thing else we call such. The preacher calls the
            world a vain shadow, and <hi rend="underline" hand="#h3">the Berkleyan philosopher
            calls it a huge accident of the five</hi> senses; and
                <choice>
                    <orig>Shakspeare</orig>
                    <reg>Shakespeare</reg>
                </choice> is inclined to think there is nothing
            that is but thinking makes it so. The practical
            men, therefore,—the directors of railways, the
            managers of stock, and the owners of electric telegraphs
            cannot be considered to have matters all to
            themselves. The poet and the romanticist control as 
            much of the "thick rotundity of the world" as they;
            and certainly the most enchanting portion. Schiller
            gives us in an admired lyric, the idea that the imaginative
            being was forgotten by Jove in the <span rend="singleLine-right" hand="#h3" xml:id="s32" from="#s32" to="#s33"/>distribution
                of the earth; but received a general invitation
            to the Court of Olympus. Our nether "maker,"
            or "finder," does still, of course, avail himself of this
            privilege; but not as one without alternative. He
            has a great share and dominion in all sublinary
            things; and his castles in the air may be found as 
            firmly fixed, after all, and as well tenanted, as any
            existing on any other element.<anchor xml:id="s33"/></p>
            
            <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
        </div1>
            
            <gap reason="cut away" extent="rest of the page"/>
            
            <pb xml:id="leaf005v" facs="duk_ap_00162.jpg" type="verso"/>
            
            <fw type="pageNum" place="top left">44</fw>
            <fw type="header" place="top">GRAHAM'S MAGAZINE.</fw>

        <div1>
                <lg type="linegroup">
                    <l>Then, with his black beard glistening in the frost,</l>
            <l>Under the icy arches of the north,</l>
            <l>And o'er the still graves of the seasons lost,</l>
            <l>Blustered the winter forth.</l>
            <l>Spring, with your crown of roses budding news,</l>
            <l>Thought-nursing and most melancholy fall,</l>
            <l>Summer, with bloomy meadows wet with dew,</l>
            <l>Blighting your beauties all.</l>
                </lg>
            
            <lg type="linegroup">
                <l>O heart, your spring-time dream will idle prove,</l>
            <l>Your summer but forerun the autumn's death</l>
            <l>The flowery arches in the home of love</l>
            <l>Fall, crumbling, at a breath;</l>
            <l>And sick at last with that great sorrow's shock,</l>
            <l>As some poor prisoner pressing to the bars</l>
            <l>His forehead, calls on mercy to unlock</l>
            <l>The chambers of the stars:</l>
            <l>You, turning off from life's first mocking glow,</l>
            <l>Leaning it may be still on broken faith,</l>
            <l>Will down the vale of autumn gladly go</l>
            <l>To the chill winter, death.</l>
            </lg>
            
                <lg type="linegroup">
                    <l>Hark! from the empty bosom of the grove</l>
                <l>I hear a sob, as one forlorn might pine—</l>
                <l>The white-limbed beauty of a god is thine,</l>
                <l>King of the seasons, and the night that hoods</l>
                <l>Thy brow majestic, brightest stars enweave—</l>
                <l>Thou surely canst not grieve.</l>
                </lg>
            
            <lg type="linegroup">
                <l>But only far away</l>
            <l>Mak'st stormy prophecies—well lift them higher,</l>
            <l>Till morning on the forehead of the day</l>
            <l>Presses a seal of fire.</l>
            <l>Dearer to me the scene</l>
            <l>Of nature shrinking from thy rough embrace,</l>
            <l>Than summer, with her rustling robe of green,</l>
            <l>Cool blowing in my face.</l>
            </lg>
            
            <lg type="linegroup">
                <l>The moon is up—how still the yellow beams</l>
            <l>That slantwise lie upon the stirless air,</l>
            <l>Sprinkled with frost, like pearl-entangled hair,</l>
            <l>O'er beauty's cheek that streams.</l>
            <l>How the red light of Mars their pallor mocks.</l>
            <l>And the wild legend from the old time wins,</l>
            <l>Of sweet waves kissing all the drowning locks</l>
            <l>Of Ilia's lovely twins.</l>
            </lg>
            
            <cb/>
            <lg type="linegroup">
                <l>Come, Poesy, and with thy shadowy hands</l>
            <l>Cover me softly, singing all the night—</l>
            <l>In thy dear presence find I best delight;</l>
            <l>Even the saint that stands</l>
            <l>Tending the gate of heaven, involved in beams</l>
            <l>Of rarest glory, to my mortal eyes</l>
            <l>Pales from the blest insanity of dreams</l>
            <l>That round thee lies.</l>
            </lg>
            
            <lg type="linegroup">
                <l>Unto the dusky borders of the grove</l>
            <l>Where gray-haired Saturn, silent as a stone,</l>
            <l>Sat in his grief alone,</l>
            <l>Or where young Venus, searching for her love,</l>
            <l>Walked through the clouds, I pray,</l>
            <l>Bear me to-night away.</l>
            </lg>
            
            <lg type="linegroup">
                <l>Or wade with me through snows</l>
            <l>Drifted in loose fantastic curves aside,</l>
            <l>From humble doors where love and faith abide,</l>
            <l>And no rough winter blows,</l>
            <l>Chilling the beauty of affections fair,</l>
            <l>Cabined securely there.</l>
            </lg>
            
            <lg type="linegroup">
                <l>Where round their fingers winding the white slips</l>
            <l>That crown his forehead, on the grandsire's knees,</l>
            <l>Sit merry children, teasing about ships</l>
            <l>Lost in perilous seas;</l>
            <l>Or listening with a troublous joy, yet deep,</l>
            <l>To stories about battles, or of storms,</l>
            <l>Till weary grown, and drowsing into sleep,</l>
            <l>Slide they from out his arms.</l>
            </lg>
            
            <lg type="linegroup">
                <l>Where, by the log-heap fire,</l>
            <l>As the pane rattles and the cricket sings,</l>
            <l>I with the gray-haired sire</l>
            <l>May talk of vanished summer-times and springs,</l>
            <l>And harmlessly and cheerfully beguile</l>
            <l>The long, long hours—</l>
            <l>The happier for the snows that drift the while</l>
            <l>About the flowers.</l>
            </lg>
            
            <lg type="linegroup">
                <l>Winter, wilt keep the love I offer thee?</l>
            <l>No mesh of flowers is bound about my brow;</l>
            <l>From life's fair summer I am hastening now.</l>
            <l>And as I sink my knee,</l>
            <l>Dimpling the beauty of thy bed of snow,</l>
            <l>Dowerless, I can but say,</l>
            <l>O, cast me not away!</l>
            </lg>
            <milestone unit="undeclared" rend="horbar-short-center"/>
        </div1>
            
            <div1>
                <head type="section">IMPROMPTU TO THE AUTHOR OF "THE OCEAN-BORN."</head>
                <gap reason="cut away" extent="rest of page"/>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>